<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>die_brucke</id>
    <name>Die Brücke</name>
    <type>movement</type>
    <active_section>movements</active_section>
    <years>1905 - 1913</years>
    <keywords>die brucke, brucke, the bridge, bridge, art story, movement, art movement, foundation, art, education, analysis, artworks, resources, ideas, topics, beginnings, themes, concepts, styles, information, history, legacy</keywords>
    <description>Die Brucke artists confronted alienation from the modern world by reaching back to earlier arts including woodcuts, carved sculptures, and the "primitive".</description>
    <art_description>Famous paintings and prints of Die Brücke group with analysis, achievements, and overall contributions to the arts.</art_description>
    <use_big_images>true</use_big_images>
    <profession />
    <highlight>4</highlight>
    <start>1905</start>
    <end>1913</end>
    <image_desc>true</image_desc>
    <pub_time>5/21/2015</pub_time>
    <big_bio_box_img>Detail from Kirchner's &lt;i&gt;Street with Red Streetwalker&lt;/i&gt; (1914-25)</big_bio_box_img>
    <bio_highlight>Describing  “the years 1911-14 [as] .. one of the loneliest times of my life, during which an agonizing restlessness drove me out onto the streets day and night,” Ernst Ludwig Kirchner painted alienated street scenes. Their expressive angst epitomized Die Brücke.</bio_highlight>
  </main>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>kirchner_ernst_ludwig</artist>
    <artist>nolde_emil</artist>
    <artist>schmidt_rottluff_karl</artist>
    <artist>munch_edvard</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>expressionism</movement>
    <movement>der_blaue_reiter</movement>
    <movement>post_impressionism</movement>
    <movement>symbolism</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <do_not_miss>
    <entry>expressionism</entry>
    <entry>der_blaue_reiter</entry>
  </do_not_miss>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true" author="kirchner_ernst_ludwig">"Whoever renders directly and authentically that which impels him to create is one of us."</q>
    <q author="Karl Schmidt-Rottluff">"There is a war in the air. In the museums, the hard-won cultural achievements of the last 20 years are being destroyed, and yet the reason we founded Die Brücke was to encourage truly German art, made in Germany."</q>
    <q author="Emil Nolde">"The art of an artist must be his own art. It is...always a continuous chain of little inventions, little technical discoveries of one's own, in relation to the tool, the material and the colors."</q>
    <q author="Ernst Ludwig Kirchner">"You too, find release only in art, you are one of those privileged people who have that gift, and you will be free and at peace so long as you make use of it."</q>
    <q author="Emil Nolde">"Wherever I looked, Nature was alive: the sky, the clouds, on every stone and among the branches of the trees, everywhere my creatures stirred or lived their still or wild, lively lives, arousing my excitement and crying out to be painted."</q>
    <q author="Ernst Ludwig Kirchner">"You too, find release only in art, you are one of those privileged people who have that gift, and you will be free and at peace so long as you make use of it."</q>
    <q author="Emil Nolde">"Every color holds within it a soul, which makes me happy or repels me, and which acts as a stimulus. To a person who has no art in him, colors are colors, tones tones... and that is all. All their consequences for the human spirit, which range between heaven to hell, just go unnoticed."</q>
    <q author="Ernst Ludwig Kirchner">"All art needs this visible world and will always need it. Quite simply because, being accessible to all, it is the key to all other worlds."</q>
    <q author="Ernst Ludwig Kirchner">"A painter paints the appearance of things, not their objective correctness; in fact, he creates new appearances of things."</q>
    <q author="Max Pechstein">"Art is not a pastime, it is a duty with respect to the people, a public affair."</q>
    <q author="Karl Schmidt-Rottluff">"I really feel pressure to create something that is as strong as possible. The war has really swept away everything from the past."</q>
    <q author="Ernst Ludwig Kirchner">"The German artist creates out of his imagination, inner vision. The forms of visible nature are to him only a symbol."</q>
    <q author="Karl Schmidt-Rottluff">"The essence of art can never change. I'm convinced you can't talk about art. At best, you will have a translation, a poetic paraphrase, and as for that I'll leave that to the poets."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="top">The Art Story Contributors</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Progenitors of the movement later known as German &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-expressionism"&gt;Expressionism&lt;/span&gt;, Die Brücke formed in Dresden in 1905 as a bohemian collective of artists in staunch opposition to the older, established bourgeois social order of Germany. Their art confronted feelings of alienation from the modern world by reaching back to pre-academic forms of expression including woodcut prints, carved wooden sculptures, and "primitive" modes of painting. This quest for authentic emotion led to an expressive style characterized by heightened color and a direct, simplified approach to form.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Die Brücke is typically seen as the fountainhead of German Expressionism, chronologically the first of two groups (the other being &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-der_blaue_reiter"&gt;Der Blaue Reiter&lt;/span&gt;) that pushed German modern art onto the international &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-avant_garde"&gt;avant-garde&lt;/span&gt; scene.</idea>
      <idea>None of the four founding members of Die Brücke, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-kirchner_ernst_ludwig"&gt;Ernst Ludwig Kirchner&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-bleyl_fritz"&gt;Fritz Bleyl&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-heckel_erich"&gt;Erich Heckel&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-schmidt_rottluff_karl"&gt;Karl Schmidt-Rottluff&lt;/span&gt;, had received any formal education in the visual arts. They stressed the value of youth and intuition in escaping the intellectual cul-de-sac of academic thought focused on copying earlier models.</idea>
      <idea>The name Die Brücke was chosen to indicate the group's desire to "bridge" the past and present. From the past, they chose to reassert Germany's rich artistic history, taking inspiration from the print and painting techniques of Albrecht Dürer, Matthias Grünewald, and Lucas Cranach the Elder. Developing the modern example of expressive colorists like &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-van_gogh_vincent"&gt;Vincent van Gogh&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-munch_edvard"&gt;Edvard Munch&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-matisse_henri"&gt;Henri Matisse&lt;/span&gt;, sharp and sometimes violently clashing colors are often used in Die Brücke painting to jolt the viewer into the experience of a particular emotion.</idea>
      <idea>For the artists of Die Brücke, escaping the academy was part of a larger mission to escape the strictures of modern middle-class life. Nudity and explorations of free sexuality in their work (in domestic interiors and in nature) are often contrasted with images of the city, where human interaction is uncomfortably negotiated through prescribed social attitudes.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Beginnings">
        <subsection title="Birth of Die Brücke in Dresden, 1905">
          <p type="p">Ernst Ludwig Kirchner and Fritz Bleyl met in 1901 at the Technical Institute of Dresden as architecture students interested in Germany's &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-art_nouveau"&gt;Jugendstil&lt;/span&gt; tradition, a local variant of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-art_nouveau"&gt;Art Nouveau&lt;/span&gt;, and became fast friends. Erich Heckel and Karl Schmidt-Rottluff, a few years younger, met in grammar school in 1902 before enrolling in the Technical Institute in 1904 and 1905, respectively. In June 1905, the four students, now friendly colleagues, decided to form an artist's group opposed to tradition and the academic nature of their prior education. The idea of being a collective of artists was central to their thought, and it was established early on that Die Brücke artists would not exhibit outside of the group without permission from the other members. They exhibited aggressively, mounting over 70 shows in their brief eight-year tenure as a collective.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="A Bohemian Colony">
          <p type="img" alt="Ernst Ludwig Kirchner and Erna Schilling (later married) in his studio in Berlin (c. 1912-14). Photo gives a sense of the intimate and behemian setting for the group's various explorations." show="1">/images20/photo/die_brucke_1.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">At the group's genesis, the artists of Die Brücke envisioned themselves primarily as a bohemian collective of artists. This idea was likely influenced by the precedent of Worpswede, an artists' colony in northern Germany established in the 1880s that brought cultural luminaries such as the early Expressionist painter &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-modersohn_becker_paula"&gt;Paula Modersohn-Becker&lt;/span&gt; and the writers Thomas Mann and Rainer Maria Rilke into a communal living and working situation.</p>
          <p type="p">If Worpswede suggested to Die Brücke that a communal, outdoor lifestyle might be preferable and more natural than city life, Modersohn-Becker's paintings of female nudes (including some self-portraits) in domestic and outdoor settings set the tone for their choice of theme. In Die Brücke's early stages, Kirchner's apartment served as a &lt;i&gt;laissez-faire&lt;/i&gt; venue for nude life-drawing sessions and casual lovemaking. This led to what has been referred to as the "vital eroticism" of Die Brücke painting.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="New Members, New Personalities">
          <p type="img" alt="Street with Red Streetwalker by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner (1914-25) is a street scene that was popular to depict." show="1">/images20/photo/die_brucke_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Despite their collective mentality, certain members of Die Brücke held distinct roles in the group. Heckel, for example, became the &lt;i&gt;de facto&lt;/i&gt; business manager of the group due to his personable attitude and art world connections. However, Kirchner is typically considered the group's leader, largely due to his attempts to theoretically direct the group, the widely held opinion that his art best exemplified the Die Brücke style, and the fact that he wrote the group's first history, the &lt;i&gt;Chronik der Brücke&lt;/i&gt;, in 1913.</p>
          <p type="p">Bleyl, who would leave the group in 1907, is often considered as less "important" than &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pechstein_max"&gt;Max Pechstein&lt;/span&gt;, who joined in 1906. Having met Heckel in 1906 while studying at the Royal Art Academy in Dresden, Pechstein joined the group's lively discussions and came to them as the first member with prior education in painting. Art critics quickly identified him as the "purest" painter of the group, and he was the most financially successful during the group's tenure. &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-nolde_emil"&gt;Emil Nolde&lt;/span&gt;, who was thirteen years older than Kirchner and Bleyl and had been producing work for decades, was invited to join Die Brücke after the artists saw his work at a local exhibition.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="The First Die Brücke Exhibition, 1906">
          <p type="p">In 1906, Heckel obtained permission to host the group's first exhibition at the Karl-Max Seifert lamp factory and showroom in September and October that year. The theme of the exhibition was the female nude, which was advertised by a lithographic poster of a semi-abstract woman created by Bleyl. The exhibition was accompanied by a woodcut leaflet by Kirchner that stated the group's ideals:</p>
          <p type="p">"With faith in evolution, in a new generation of creators and connoisseurs, we call together all youth. And as youths, who embody the future, we want to free our lives and limbs from the long-established older powers. Anyone who renders his creative drive directly and genuinely is one of us."</p>
          <p type="p">Though the show was not a critical success, the experimentation of the young group was on display for the first time, heralding the rise of Germany's first &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-avant_garde"&gt;avant-garde&lt;/span&gt; movement. Moreover, the group marketed itself to ensure financial sustainability in the future, seeking both "active members" (artists) and "passive members" (donors).</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Developing the Die Brücke Aesthetic">
          <p type="p">Bleyl broke with the group in 1907 to start a family, and Nolde left shortly after, apparently unwilling to follow the group's rigid exhibition policy. The core of the group was still set, however, with Kirchner, Heckel, Schmidt-Rottluff, and Pechstein working together to establish a radical modern style in German art.</p>
          <p type="p">From 1907 to 1911, the group spent a large portion of its time in Dresden, planning exhibitions and using Kirchner's apartment as a hangout and studio. Pechstein moved to Berlin in 1908, but he would often return in the summers, and the artists would pair off and head out of the city to seek the simplicity of nature, particularly near the lakes of Moritzburg. It was during this time that the artists also began frequenting Dresden's Ethnological Museum, developing an interest in &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-primitivism"&gt;Primitivism&lt;/span&gt;, which would prove highly influential on their group style.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Inspiring New Expressionisms">
          <p type="p">After his move to Berlin, Pechstein exhibited with the Berlin Secession, until his and some of his young contemporaries' work was rejected from one of their exhibitions for being too "expressionist," and he helped found the Neue Sezession (New Secession) in 1910. Pechstein succeeded in bringing his Die Brücke cohorts to exhibit with the Neue Sezession in 1910, where they came into contact with and ultimately recruited &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-mueller_otto"&gt;Otto Mueller&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
          <p type="p">By 1910, the Expressionist style had developed in Dresden, and Die Brücke had become so popular among young artists that it inspired secession movements in the nation's capital. Indeed, the movement had become known across Germany via its wide-traveling exhibitions. Beyond Berlin, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-kandinsky_wassily"&gt;Wassily Kandinsky&lt;/span&gt; had formed the Neue Kunstvereinigung Munchen (Munich New Artists' Association) in Munich in 1909, which was something of an incubator for the artistic and theoretical ideas he would promulgate in &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-der_blaue_reiter"&gt;Der Blaue Reiter&lt;/span&gt; (The Blue Rider) group from 1911 to 1914.</p>
          <p type="p">The other major movement within German Expressionism, Der Blaue Reiter focused on abstraction in art and claimed that colors held a spiritual value beyond the emotional value attributed to them by Die Brücke. Though they pursued different goals, the two movements tilled common artistic ground and often addressed similar themes, and by the 1910s, works from both groups could be seen in the same exhibitions.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="The Move to Berlin">
          <p type="p">In 1911, Kirchner persuaded the rest of the Dresden painters to move to Berlin, where he had joined Pechstein to found the private art school Moderner Unterricht im Malen Institut (Modern Teaching of Painting Institute) as a way of promoting their new, modern artistic convictions. The group became more involved with the international avant-garde movements of Italian &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-futurism"&gt;Futurism&lt;/span&gt; and French &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-cubism"&gt;Cubism&lt;/span&gt; as a result of the move to the major metropolis, with each artist responding differently to new stimuli. Kirchner, for better or worse, felt enervated in Berlin, and his work took on a more agitated, dynamic quality. Heckel felt alienated by the metropolis, and his color palette became more subdued, while Schmidt-Rottluff embraced its modernity and began to incorporate the fragmented geometry of Cubism and Futurism in his work. The Die Brücke artists would remain in Berlin until their formal breakup in 1913.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section title="Concepts, Styles, and Trends">
        <subsection title="In the City, or Of the City?">
          <p type="img" alt="Ernst Ludwig Kirchner's painting: Artist community (1926-27), which shows the members of the group, but was actually painted many years later." show="1">/images20/photo/die_brucke_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">The artists of Die Brücke derived a great deal of tension in their art from a paradox: though the artists lived in the cities of Dresden and then Berlin, to some extent they never considered themselves &lt;i&gt;of&lt;/i&gt; the city. The modern city, as depicted in Die Brücke paintings, is a fantastic realm of attraction and repulsion. To separate themselves from their bourgeois backgrounds, the artists settled into a rebuilt butcher shop in a working-class neighborhood; however, it is unclear how often they roamed those streets for their art, as many of their city images depict wealthy or at least commercial areas.</p>
          <p type="p">Nevertheless, the formal qualities of their art were undoubtedly influenced by their experience of urban living. Clashing tones and angular, almost belligerent brushstrokes compose many of their images, even before their contact with the faceting of Cubism and Futurism. While their color choices took on some of the luminosity of the country during their ex-urban travels, their work largely speaks of the experience of modernity through city life.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Nature and Naturism">
          <p type="p">The artists of Die Brücke did, however, spend quite a lot of time outside of the city, in an attempt to escape the urban landscape. Among Germany's lakes and forests, they were able to live closer to their ideal of a bohemian artists' collective. Their canvases reflected this, turning from urban alienation to themes of happy men and women cavorting naked in nature. Naturism, the philosophy of social nudity, had been defended in German intellectual circles around the turn of the century, and the Die Brücke artists embraced it as part of their radical rejection of bourgeois social norms.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Primitivism and Ethnology">
          <p type="p">Another concept with which Die Brücke hoped to overturn stale social and academic conventions was Primitivism. Both Dresden and Berlin housed ethnological museums that allowed the group to view African, Pacific, and American artifacts, which they studied for aesthetic inspiration. Though "Primitivism" has negative connotations in the postcolonial era, its use in the arts constituted a genuine attempt on the behalf of modern artists to break through the intellectual constraints of modern Western society by reaching to a "simpler" and potentially "freer" means of expression in less-developed parts of the world. For the artists of Die Brücke (and, for that matter, their contemporaries the Fauves, the Cubists, and the artists of Der Blaue Reiter), this meant their art often evinced a less laborious, more direct rendering of form far from the obsessive pursuit of naturalism and beauty that had previously been considered the highest goal of art.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Printmaking: the Woodcut and the Linocut">
          <p type="p">Perhaps one of Die Brücke's most original contributions to modern art was the reintroduction of woodblock printing. Germany possessed a storied lineage of printmaking that reached back through the Renaissance-era masters Martin Schongauer and Albrecht Dürer to the stark, angular, and often grainy prints that survived from the Middle Ages. In an attempt to find the most direct form of expression, the artists of Die Brücke regained the techniques of artisan printmakers almost one-thousand years deceased and used them to make powerful statements with strong contrasts. In addition, they modernized this age-old technique by innovating the linocut, which accomplished a similar effect through the use of modern linoleum, which was easier to gouge into than wood.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section title="Later Developments">
        <subsection title="">
          <p type="p">The collective impulse that pushed Die Brücke to its greatest work was ultimately part of the group's undoing. In 1912, Pechstein was expelled from the group for exhibiting work at the Neue Sezession without their consent. The artists' attitudes toward each other began to deteriorate, with some arguments centering around cordial disagreements over artistic and theoretical issues, and some moving beyond to personal conflict. The final straw was Kirchner's authorship of the Chronik der Brücke in 1913, where he emphasized his achievements, claimed that Pechstein had "betrayed" the group by exhibiting with the Neue Sezession, and denied any outside influence from Cubism or Futurism. The other members of the group rejected the draft, and Die Brücke dissolved.</p>
          <p type="p">As the largely figurative German Expressionist corollary to Kandinsky and Der Blaue Reiter's semi-abstract group, Die Brücke was extremely influential for twentieth-century modernism. Despite Kirchner's assertion that Die Brücke was a wholly German movement, the internationally followed 1912 Sonderbund exhibition in Cologne was centered around the debt that modern art, including Expressionism, owed to van Gogh, Munch, and other modern artists. This ensured that Die Brücke would be recognized internationally as an important player in the development of the later avant gardes.</p>
          <p type="p">The following decades saw a host of artists from across Europe take up the figurative Expressionist style begun by Die Brücke. In Germany, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-dix_otto"&gt;Otto Dix&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-grosz_george"&gt;George Grosz&lt;/span&gt; were Expressionists influenced by the group who ultimately developed the next major German art movement &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-new_objectivity"&gt;Neue Sachlichkeit&lt;/span&gt;. In Austria, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-schiele_egon"&gt;Egon Schiele&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-kokoschka_oskar"&gt;Oskar Kokoschka&lt;/span&gt; exemplified an idea of artist-as-outcast in a style that drew on Kirchner's example.</p>
          <p type="p">And if the abstract variant of Expressionism cultivated by Der Blaue Reiter was a touchstone for &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionism&lt;/span&gt; in the United States in the work of artists like &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pollock_jackson"&gt;Jackson Pollock&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rothko_mark"&gt;Mark Rothko&lt;/span&gt;, Die Brücke remained an influence on its semi-figurative painters like &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-de_kooning_willem"&gt;Willem de Kooning&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-guston_philip"&gt;Philip Guston&lt;/span&gt;, whose post-World War II images revised some of the alienation of late Die Brücke canvases. The same could be said for the art of post-WWII Britain, where &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-bacon_francis"&gt;Francis Bacon&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-freud_lucian"&gt;Lucian Freud&lt;/span&gt; created distorted and psychologically penetrating figural paintings, often of individuals.</p>
          <p type="p">&lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-neo_expressionism"&gt;Neo-Expressionism&lt;/span&gt;, a painterly reaction to the popularity of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-conceptual_art"&gt;Conceptual art&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalism&lt;/span&gt; in the 1970s, was an explicit reach back to Die Brücke artists like Nolde and Kirchner, and the style dominated the art world well into the 1980s through the works of artists like &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-baselitz_georg"&gt;Georg Baselitz&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-kiefer_anselm"&gt;Anselm Kiefer&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-basquiat_jean_michel"&gt;Jean-Michel Basquiat&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-schnabel_julian"&gt;Julian Schnabel&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-hockney_david"&gt;David Hockney&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="movement" page="post_impressionism">Portrait of Doctor Gachet (1890)</artwork>
    <artwork from="movement" page="der_blaue_reiter">Composition VII (1913)</artwork>
    <artwork from="movement" page="expressionism">Mad Woman (1920)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top />
    <bottom />
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Programme</title>
      <artist>Ernst Ludwig Kirchner</artist>
      <year>1906</year>
      <materials>Woodcut on paper</materials>
      <desc>The charismatic center of Die Brücke, Ernst Ludwig Kirchner composed and printed their original group statement a year after their formation, championing in it their youth and claims of authenticity. The statement, seen here, was turned into a leaflet and distributed at the group's first exhibition. Kirchner's choice of the woodcut medium indicates Die Brücke's reverence for German precedents and direct representation. Moreover, his formal style suggests Johannes Gutenberg's innovations in moveable type, with a large capital "M" serving as the first letter, leading compact lines of printed script. However, a closer look reveals the artistic, handmade nature of &lt;i&gt;Programme&lt;/i&gt;, which is evident in Kirchner's irregular lettering. That natural, artisanal approach to art and design was a remnant of his education in the &lt;i&gt;Jugendstil&lt;/i&gt; mode of architecture and the applied arts, which would greatly influence early Die Brücke art and philosophy.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Poster for the first Die Brücke Exhibition</title>
      <artist>Fritz Bleyl</artist>
      <year>1906</year>
      <materials>Color lithograph</materials>
      <desc>In September and October of 1906, Die Brücke mounted its first exhibition, focused on the theme of the female nude. The group held the event in the showroom of the Karl-Max Seifert lamp factory, a venue procured through one of Erich Heckel's connections from design school. In contrast to the factory polish of the chandeliers and candelabras on display, Fritz Bleyl designed an expressionistic poster for the event featuring a partially abstracted nude woman. For Die Brücke and its proponents, the figure was striking and direct, reflecting the group's attitude toward open sexuality and the natural state of nudity. Reduced formally by Bleyl's style and the printed medium to a series of curves and contours, the poster was nonetheless deemed too sexually suggestive for public view and banned under the pornography clause in Germany's national penal code.</desc>
      <collection>Die Brücke Museum, Berlin</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Self-Portrait with Monocle</title>
      <artist>Karl Schmidt-Rottluff</artist>
      <year>1910</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Karl Schmidt-Rottluff's &lt;i&gt;Self-Portrait with Monocle&lt;/i&gt; exemplifies the lively, enervating brushstroke common among many Die Brücke painters. Rather than representing himself in a recognizable domestic interior, Schmidt-Rottluff simplified the background in an angular composition of flat panes of vibrant color. He depicted himself in the pose and garb of a bohemian intellectual, complete with brooding visage, green turtleneck, and thoughtful gesture. With the focus placed on his eye and his painting hand, he modernized the pose of Albrecht Dürer, one of the few masters Die Brücke acknowledged, in his well-loved &lt;i&gt;Self-Portrait Wearing a Coat with Fur Collar&lt;/i&gt; (1500).</desc>
      <collection>Staatliche Museen, Berlin</collection>
      <use_big_image>false</use_big_image>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Sitzender Akt (Fränzi) (Seated Nude (Fränzi))</title>
      <artist>Erich Heckel</artist>
      <year>1910</year>
      <materials>Woodcut</materials>
      <desc>In their studies toward a modern, expressionistic art, the Die Brücke group regularly sketched, painted, and printed images of two young neighborhood girls they used as models, one of whom, "Franzi," (Lina Franziska Fehrmann) Erich Heckel depicts here. The artists' desire for freedom of expression was mirrored in the free movement and relative lack of inhibition of their young muses. In Heckel's woodcut &lt;i&gt;Seated Nude (Fränzi)&lt;/i&gt;, Franzi's pose and slight grin indicate a lack of shame about her nakedness, while her skinny, immature body provides a visual analog for the artist's angularity and simplification of form. Rendered in stark, unmodulated white, her nudity contrasts with the red and green background tones. Heckel also continued the contour of her nose into the accentuated curves of her eyebrows, a formal convention he culled from non-Western masks he studied in Dresden's Ethnological Museum.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Masks</title>
      <artist>Emil Nolde</artist>
      <year>1911</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>The oldest member of Die Brücke, Emil Nolde, already a seasoned painter, joined the group in 1906. The jarring tonal combinations in &lt;i&gt;Masks&lt;/i&gt; show both his maturity as a colorist and his respect for the northern Symbolist heritage of artists like James Ensor and Edvard Munch. These artists often incorporated the mask in their art as the visual language of alienation and disconnect; in Nolde's &lt;i&gt;Masks&lt;/i&gt;, the masks melt into and rise from the canvas, creating a grotesque, mocking chorus of faces. His inclusion of the motif was also based on his intense study of African and Pacific masks in the Ethnological Museum in Berlin, where he lived intermittently throughout his adult life. However, his representation of the masks is neither a simple copy nor a transplantation of those forms onto figures in his painting; rather, Nolde enhances the masks with his figural distortions.</desc>
      <collection>Nelson-Atkins Museum of Art, Kansas City, Missouri</collection>
      <use_big_image>false</use_big_image>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Under the Trees (Nudes in the Open)</title>
      <artist>Max Pechstein</artist>
      <year>1911</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>The artists of Die Brücke were often compared to the Fauve painters in Paris due to their bright, vivid canvases and their semi-abstract handling of the human form. And there is certainly common ground between Max Pechstein's &lt;i&gt;Under the Trees (Nudes in the Open)&lt;/i&gt; and Henri Matisse's &lt;i&gt;Joy of Life&lt;/i&gt;, both of which feature nude figures rendered in vibrant colors in an idyllic landscape. However, while Matisse and his cadre were still borrowing from the Classical tradition, with muses playing flutes, dancing, and making love, Pechstein depicted the landscape and events of actual trips he and his bohemian artist's group took to the country to escape from society and its strictures. Among the radical philosophies Die Brücke espoused was naturism (nudism) as a counterpoint to the industrialization of the modern city. Painted in the year the Die Brücke group moved to the Berlin metropolis, &lt;i&gt;Under the Trees&lt;/i&gt; stands as an iconic example of that anti-urban impulse.</desc>
      <collection>Detroit Institute of Art</collection>
      <use_big_image>false</use_big_image>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Street, Berlin</title>
      <artist>Ernst Ludwig Kirchner</artist>
      <year>1913</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Though Max Pechstein moved first, the choice to move the Die Brücke group to Berlin was made largely by Ernst Ludwig Kirchner, who saw greater artistic opportunity in the more populous cultural center. Painted shortly after the breakup of Die Brücke, however, &lt;i&gt;Street, Berlin&lt;/i&gt; exemplifies the destabilizing effect the city had on Kirchner, who referred to the years 1911 to 1914 as "the loneliest times of my life." In the forefront are two garishly painted prostitutes who stroll down a street so drastically flattened that they appear to be sliding off the canvas. They are as much on view, for sale, and separate as the trinkets in the storefront window a man peruses on the right. Kirchner would later write that as an artist he identified with the prostitute, being constantly asked to sell himself to survive. Thus, the work can be read as an iconic self-portrait depicting both his formal innovations and the psychological motivations that produced them.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="key artists" is_recommended="false">
      <subcategory name="not_to_show" class="">
        <entry>
          <id>kirchner_ernst_ludwig</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>bleyl_fritz</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>schmidt_rottluff_karl</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>heckel_erich</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>nolde_emil</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>pechstein_max</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="art story website features" />
    <category name="current exhibitions" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="not_to_show" class="">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Brücke: The Birth of Expressionism in Dresden and Berlin, 1905-1913</title>
          <link>377572351X</link>
          <info>By Reinhold Heller</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Brücke</title>
          <link>377572351X</link>
          <info>By Ulrike Lorenz</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>New Perspectives on Brücke Expressionism: Bridging History</title>
          <link>1409412032</link>
          <info>By Christian Weikop</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>German Expressionism: Die Brücke and Der Blaue Reiter</title>
          <link>0882547461</link>
          <info>By Barry Herbert</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography" />
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by" />
      <subcategory name="paintings" class="artwork" />
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Brücke Museum</title>
          <link>http://www.bruecke-museum.de/themuseum.htm</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Artists of Brücke: Themes in German Expressionist Prints</title>
          <link>http://www.moma.org/interactives/exhibitions/2002/brucke/</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>BMA Exhibit Explores German Expressionism</title>
          <link>http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2014-02-01/entertainment/bs-ae-bma-german-expressionism-20140201_1_bma-exhibit-bma-show-german-expressionism</link>
          <info>
						By Tim Smith
						&lt;br&gt;
						The Baltimore Sun 
						&lt;br&gt;
						February 1, 2014
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Die Brücke: Origins of Expressionism</title>
          <link>http://www.theguardian.com/culture/2012/may/08/die-bruke-german-expressionist-review</link>
          <info>
						By Philippe Dagen
						&lt;br&gt;
						The Guardian 
						&lt;br&gt;
						May 8, 2012
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>An Expressionist from a Brutal Time</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/07/arts/design/07SMIT.html</link>
          <info>
						By Roberta Smith
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times 
						&lt;br&gt;
						March 7, 2003
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="interviews" class="interviews" />
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips" />
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Friday Morning Lecture &amp; Tour Series: German Expressionist Art 1905-1937***</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DIJELjmOnzU</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The BBL Series: German Expressionism</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m20td2mb_Ww</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips" />
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop">
        <entry>
          <title>Die Brücke: The Birth of Modern Art in Germany</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/movies/movie/13710/Die-Brucke-The-Birth-of-Modern-Art-in-Germany/overview</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
</data>