<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>washington_color_school</id>
    <name>Washington Color School</name>
    <type>movement</type>
    <active_section>movements</active_section>
    <years>1958 - 1980</years>
    <keywords>washington color school, color, school, washington, art story, movement, art movement, foundation, art, education, analysis, artworks, resources, ideas, topics, beginnings, themes, concepts, styles, information, history, legacy</keywords>
    <description>Washington D.C. saw a flourishing of abstract art that emphasized the form-making capabilities of pure color.</description>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <profession />
    <highlight>1</highlight>
    <start>1958</start>
    <end>1980</end>
    <image_desc>true</image_desc>
    <pub_time>11/12/2017</pub_time>
  </main>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>noland_kenneth</artist>
    <artist>louis_morris</artist>
    <artist>truitt_anne</artist>
    <artist>still_clyfford</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>abstract_expressionism</movement>
    <movement>color_field_painting</movement>
    <movement>post_painterly_abstraction</movement>
    <movement>op_art</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <do_not_miss>
    <entry>abstract_expressionism</entry>
    <entry>color_field_painting</entry>
    <entry>post_painterly_abstraction</entry>
  </do_not_miss>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true" author="noland_kenneth">"I do open paintings. I like lightness, airiness, and the way color pulsates. The presence of the painting is all that's important."</q>
    <q author="Howard Mehring">"I prefer to work flat on the floor with the canvas unsized and unstretched. Raw canvas seems more open to me. I am closer to the painting, more in contact with it."</q>
    <q author="Sam Gilliam">"If you are concerned about whatever it is you want to do, you dream about it. You wake up in the morning and you've got a solution. You work it out. There is always tomorrow."</q>
    <q author="Sam Gilliam">"Whether I am teaching or making art, the process is fundamentally the same; I am creating."</q>
    <q author="Sam Gilliam">"Just work and let things go"</q>
    <q author="Sam Gilliam">"This was actually the idea of staining, to make the grain a part of the paint surface as well as the pigment. Color was, of course, the principal element that was used to construct with."</q>
    <q author="Thomas Downing">"One of the more intelligent questions ever asked regarding my work was asked by a child. The question was 'Why do you paint circles instead of squares?' My answer at the moment was 'because circles are easier to paint. There are no corners to go into and then get out of.'"</q>
    <q author="Alma Thomas">"Man's highest aspirations come from nature. A world without color would seem dead. Color is life. Light is the mother of color. Light reveals to us the spirit and living soul of the world through colors."</q>
    <q author="Gene Davis">"I became convinced that the way to make really good art was to do the outrageous, the unexpected - to be a renegade. That was my philosophy - to explore the seemingly impossible in art, to do things that were new for their own sake, whether they were good or bad."</q>
    <q author="Gene Davis">"Instead of simply glancing at the work, select a specific color - and take the time to see how it operates across the painting. - Enter the painting through the door of a single color, and then you can understand what my painting is all about."</q>
    <q author="Anne Truitt">"What is important to me is not geometrical shape per se, or color per se, but to make a relationship between shape and color which feels to me like my experience. To make what feels to me like reality."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="seiferle">Rebecca Seiferle</author>
  </authors>
  <editors>
    <editor link="hellstein">Valerie Hellstein</editor>
  </editors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>
			In the latter half of the 1950s, Washington D.C. saw a flourishing of abstract art that emphasized the form-making capabilities of pure color. Known as The Washington Color School, the loosely affiliated group of abstract painters knew each other through various teaching experiences. The moniker has an uncertain origin but likely originated with the title of a 1965 exhibition at the Washington Gallery of Modern Art, "Washington Color Painters," curated by Gerald Nordland. The show exhibited the works of Kenneth Noland, Paul Reed, Morris Louis, Howard Mehring, Thomas Downing, and Gene Davis. Additionally, Leon Berkowitz and Sam Gilliam along with V.V. Rankine, Alma Thomas, Hilda Thorpe and Anne Truitt were also associated with The School.
			&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
			Using innovative techniques that expanded on &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionist&lt;/span&gt; experiments with color and paint application, the Washington Color School created deceptively simple compositions that evoked dynamism and tension. Championed by the art critic &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-greenberg_clement"&gt;Clement Greenberg&lt;/span&gt; as part of the larger trend of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-post_painterly_abstraction"&gt;Post-Painterly Abstraction&lt;/span&gt;, the work of the group was seen as the culmination of modernist painting, with its emphasis on the two-dimensional surface of the picture plane and its lack of reference to any subject matter. The Washington Color School embraced the larger trend of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-color_field_painting"&gt;Color Field painting&lt;/span&gt;, and some of its practitioners experimented with &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-hard_edge_painting"&gt;Hard Edge painting&lt;/span&gt; as well. In many ways, these D.C. artists anticipated the style of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalism&lt;/span&gt; and then evolved alongside it, and the teaching legacy of the Washington Color School left its mark on a generation of artists in Washington. While many saw these experiments as a way of moving out of and beyond Abstract Expressionism, others saw them as a formal dead end and divorced from the tumultuous atmosphere of the 1960s.
		</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>The Washington Color School used color, and not drawing, to create and delineate simple geometric forms. They often spoke of wanting to put pure color on the canvas to create an immediate, all at once, visual experience for the viewer. This optical experience became more important than conveying subject matter.</idea>
      <idea>Many of the artists associated with the Washington Color School used a soak stain technique whereby thinned acrylic paint saturates the raw canvas. Instead of sitting on top of the canvas, the color becomes one with the canvas. Without the physical layers of paint, this technique emphasizes the two-dimensional nature of the picture plane, which according to Clement Greenberg was one of the main goals of modernist painting.</idea>
      <idea>As part of the larger trend of Color Field painting, The Washington Color School shunned the histrionic personas that had grown up around the Abstract Expressionist artists. Instead, the execution of their paintings were more anonymous, without the gestural presence of the artist. In downplaying the presence of the artist, the viewer's experience comes more to the fore. This switch in emphasis from the artist to the viewer was in line with other artistic experiments of the 1960s, including &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-happenings"&gt;Happenings&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalism&lt;/span&gt;.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Beginnings">
        <subsection title="Precedents">
          <p type="p">The Washington Color School evolved from the Abstract Expressionist experiments with color and all-over composition. &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-still_clyfford"&gt;Clyfford Still&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-newman_barnett"&gt;Barnett Newman&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rothko_mark"&gt;Mark Rothko&lt;/span&gt;, sometimes referred to as Color Field painters, created bold compositions with large expanses of color. Clyfford Still created canvases with jagged areas of impasto color applied with a palette knife, and Newman punctuated large fields of color with vertical lines he called "zips". Rothko's vertically formatted canvases juxtapose rectangular areas of color that seem to float on the canvas. While the Washington Color School developed the techniques used by the Abstract Expressionists and adopted the new technique of staining, the artists tended to eschew the emotional and dramatic rhetoric used by the older generation.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Kenneth Noland">
          <p type="p">&lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-noland_kenneth"&gt;Kenneth Noland&lt;/span&gt;, as a teacher and artist, became the center of what was to become the Washington Color School. After serving in World War II, Noland took advantage of the G.I. Bill and enrolled at Black Mountain College, the storied &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-avant_garde"&gt;avant-garde&lt;/span&gt; school, where he studied with &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-albers_josef"&gt;Josef Albers&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-bolotowsky_ilya"&gt;Ilya Bolotowsky&lt;/span&gt; and was introduced to the paintings of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-mondrian_piet"&gt;Piet Mondrian&lt;/span&gt;. After a year in Paris, Noland began teaching at the Institute of Contemporary Art in Washington, D.C. In 1950, he returned to Black Mountain College for the summer session where he met Clement Greenberg, the outspoken critic who championed Abstract Expressionism, who was also to play a prominent role in shaping and promoting the Washington Color School.</p>
          <p type="p">After his return to D.C., Noland continued teaching at Catholic University, where his students included Thomas Downing and Howard Mehring, and at the Washington Workshop Center for the Art, where he met and befriended &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-louis_morris"&gt;Morris Louis&lt;/span&gt; in 1952. The two became close colleagues, and their subsequent collaborative efforts and explorations of the new "soak stain" technique advanced the development of the Washington Color School style.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Helen Frankenthaler and The “Soak Stain”">
          <p type="img" alt="This photograph shows (left to right) Kenneth Noland, Helen Frankenthaler, and Clement Greenberg on a summer excursion in Stamford, Connecticut, August 1979" show="0">/images20/photo/photo_washington_color_school_1.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">The criticism of Clement Greenberg and the work of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-frankenthaler_helen"&gt;Helen Frankenthaler&lt;/span&gt; were primary influences in the development of the Washington Color School. In 1953 Noland and Louis visited Greenberg in New York City, and he took them to Frankenthaler's studio, where they saw her newly finished &lt;i&gt;Mountains and Sea&lt;/i&gt; (1952), a painting that launched her career when it was exhibited. Greenberg felt that Frankenthaler's work pushed beyond Abstract Expressionism in new and productive ways.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Helen Frankenthaler's &lt;i&gt;Mountains and Sea&lt;/i&gt; (1952) with its soak stain technique that she invented and which the Washington Color School, led by Noland and Louis, adopted" show="0">/images20/photo/photo_washington_color_school_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Frankenthaler uniquely transformed Jackson Pollock's method of pouring paint onto the canvas while it was on the floor. Her "soak stain" technique involved pouring oil paint thinned with turpentine directly onto the unprepared canvas. The color would then be absorbed, merging with the canvas, creating a luminous effect, like a halo or penumbra. With this process, Frankenthaler managed to make oil paint look like water color. Louis and Noland enthusiastically adopted the technique, and, returning home, they began to experiment, working together on the same painting, thinning paint to watercolor consistency and applying it to raw canvas. As Noland said of the process "Thin it, use it in the same way as dye. Thinness reveals color."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="First Works: Veils and Circles">
          <p type="img" alt="Kenneth Noland, &lt;i&gt;Globe&lt;/i&gt; (1956)" show="0">/images20/photo/photo_washington_color_school_3.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Unfortunately, none of the collaborative works that Noland and Louis created in their early experimentation with the soak stain technique remain, yet they each began to explore and apply related techniques at the time. Louis created a number of paintings that were described as "veils," or sometimes "florals." like &lt;i&gt;Iris&lt;/i&gt; (1954). By 1956 Noland was creating "proto-circles," like &lt;i&gt;Globe&lt;/i&gt; (1956), showing an irregular circle, reminiscent of an organic form. In these early works, Noland and Louis experiment with creating form with color and without delineations; that is to say, the forms created by the soft color abut one another without being outlined or otherwise differentiated.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Hard Edge Painting">
          <p type="p">In the 1950s, the works of both Louis and Noland evolved toward more definition, using regularized shapes, or hard edge simple geometric forms, with clean straight lines. Noland's proto-circles became simplified concentric circles like &lt;i&gt;Beginning&lt;/i&gt; (1958). Louis's paintings were never as hard-edged as Noland's, but beginning around the year 1960, his poured color areas became more like delineated stripes with their edges less blurred, as in &lt;i&gt;Where&lt;/i&gt; (1960).</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Gene Davis's &lt;i&gt;Hot Beat&lt;/i&gt; (1964)" show="0">/images20/photo/photo_washington_color_school_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Extensively connected to the New York City artistic community, the artists of the Washington group were familiar with &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-stella_frank"&gt;Frank Stella's&lt;/span&gt; innovative &lt;i&gt;Black Paintings&lt;/i&gt; (1959), canvases with parallel black stripes separated by thin exposures of bare canvas. Subsequently in the 1960s, the movement toward regularization and hard edge geometric shape gained impetus among the Washington School painters, as seen in works like Noland's &lt;i&gt;Shoot&lt;/i&gt; (1964), Gene Davis' &lt;i&gt;Hot Beat&lt;/i&gt; (1964) and Paul Reed's &lt;i&gt;#1D&lt;/i&gt; (1965).</p>
          <p type="a_small" alt="Hard Edge Painting Movement Page">/movement/hard-edge-painting/</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Post-Painterly Abstraction - 1964">
          <p type="p">In 1964 Greenberg curated an exhibition, &lt;i&gt;Post-Painterly Abstraction&lt;/i&gt; at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, which helped publicly launch the Washington Color School. Greenberg included paintings by Noland, Louis, Howard Mehring, Gene Davis, and Thomas Downing, along with painters associated with other movements like hard-edge abstraction and Color Field painting. Greenberg felt a painting's formal and non-subjective qualities were most important and sufficient to appreciate the work. In his accompanying catalogue, he did not so much define Post-Painterly Abstraction as posit that it was not the "painterly abstraction" of the Abstract Expressionists that had emphasized the gesture and the use of thick oil paints. As a result of Greenberg's exhibition and critical writing, Washington Color School Painting was seen as one of the primary trends in the new wave of abstraction.</p>
          <p type="a_small" alt="Post-Painterly Abstraction Movement Page">/movement/post-painterly-abstraction/</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section title="Concepts, Styles, and Trends">
        <subsection title="The Shaped Canvas">
          <p type="p">In the 1960s, a number of New York artists, including Frank Stella, were exploring the shaped canvas to emphasize the painting as an object inhabiting space. Among the Washington Color School, Thomas Downing, Paul Reed, Gene Davis, and Kenneth Noland all created a variety of works employing a shaped canvas. Davis experimented with the idea as early as 1952 when he had a lumberyard cut his Masonite panels into other shapes, but the compositions of those canvases had more in common with Abstract Expressionist surfaces, being built up with gravel to create texture and sculptural depth. In 1962, he was to return to the idea of a shaped canvas in works like &lt;i&gt;Wall Stripes No. 3&lt;/i&gt; (1962), in which seven differently colored stripe canvases were arranged horizontally on a wall, one on top of the other with a fixed distance between each.</p>
          <p type="p">The artist who most consistently focused on the shaped canvas was Paul Reed, as he built upon his earlier &lt;i&gt;Satellite&lt;/i&gt; (1963) series that incorporated the wall into the pictorial space. Described by the art critic Barbara Rose as "checks of color unfurling in Arp-like shapes," the &lt;i&gt;Satellite&lt;/i&gt; series consisted of a spinning organic shape on a large canvas with a "satellite," a smaller canvas with a related form and color precisely placed near it. Subsequently Reed began to explore further shaped canvases in series like &lt;i&gt;Emerging&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Topeka&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Hackensack&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;Zig-Fields&lt;/i&gt;, all painted in 1967. Other series were to follow, as he used more radical shapes, as shown in his &lt;i&gt;Barcelona&lt;/i&gt; series (1968-1969)</p>
          <p type="p">Also, in 1965-1966 Thomas Downing employed his dot motifs in parallelograms and subsequently made works like &lt;i&gt;Troll&lt;/i&gt; (1967), a complex shape that depicts two chevrons in a bended shape. Kenneth Noland first began using a diamond shaped canvas in 1964, as he turned his square canvas at a diagonal, perhaps influenced by Piet Mondrian's use of the diamond shaped canvas in the 1920s. In the 1970s Noland again took up the form, only using more complex shaped canvases, as shown in his &lt;i&gt;Vault&lt;/i&gt; (1977), a painting that becomes a sculptural object.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Sculpture">
          <p type="p">Several Washington Color School artists explored the potentialities of color within sculpture. Experimenting in a variety of media, Helen Thorpe used gauze, balsa wood, glass, clay and metal, and included found objects in her pieces. Her most well-known works were her sculptures using handmade paper, like &lt;i&gt;Edged Blue&lt;/i&gt; (1963). In the later 1960s, Paul Reed explored welded steel sculptures like &lt;i&gt;Step&lt;/i&gt; (1966) that drew upon the clean line, geometric complexity, and modularity of his paintings.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Anne Truitt contemplates one of her large sculptures in her studio in Washington, D.C." show="0">/images20/photo/photo_washington_color_school_5.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Anne Truitt, however, was the only major sculptor associated with the school. Her artistic breakthrough in the early 1960s was influenced by the works of Color Field painters like Barnett Newman, as she saw the primacy of color could allow her new possibilities of expression. She said, "What is important to me is not geometrical shape per se, or color per se, but to make a relationship between shape and color which feels to me like my experience. To make what feels to me like reality." Living in Washington, D.C., her works were often shown at Pyramid Gallery, though she remained a more peripheral member of the group, in part out of her own individualistic approach. Despite Helen Frankenthaler's recognized role in the shaping of the Washington Color School, Truitt still had to negotiate the gender assumptions of the group, as Noland and Greenberg, in advancing her first solo exhibition in 1963, referred to her as "the gentle wife of James Truitt" and encouraged her to conceal her gender by dropping her first name. Her sculpture emphasized basic geometric forms, often a vertical rectangle made of wood, and a reductive color palette, as seen in works like &lt;i&gt;Insurrection&lt;/i&gt; (1962).</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Draped Paintings and Installations">
          <p type="img" alt="Sam Gilliam's &lt;i&gt;Relative&lt;/i&gt; (1968), one of his first draped paintings, launched a new approach to the canvas as a dynamic object" show="0">/images20/photo/photo_washington_color_school_6.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">In 1965, Sam Gilliam, a second generation Washington Color School painter who had studied with Thomas Downing, decided to set the canvas free of its frame. Soak staining twenty-foot long pieces of canvas, then twisting, folding, and shaping them before suspending them, he created works like &lt;i&gt;Relative&lt;/i&gt; (1968) in which a vibrantly color soaked canvas hangs from a wall at four points, creating triangular shapes at the point of suspension and vertical lines of movement. Inventing this technique, he fundamentally redefined the relationship of the painting to space.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Henry Groskinsky's photograph of Gene Davis painting the final touches on &lt;i&gt;Franklin's Footpath&lt;/i&gt; (1972)" show="0">/images20/photo/photo_washington_color_school_7.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Installation work among the Washington Color School was primarily done by Gene Davis, as his stripe paintings were painted on streets and the steps of notable buildings. Davis painted 414 feet of the street leading up to the Philadelphia Museum of Art's in his &lt;i&gt;Franklin's Footpath&lt;/i&gt; (1972). Later, in 1987, 8&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; Street NW in Washington D.C. was painted in color stripes in honor of Davis and the installation was recreated in Washington D.C. again in 2007.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Gene Davis's &lt;i&gt;Sun Sonata&lt;/i&gt; (1983), viewed at night" show="0">/images20/photo/photo_washington_color_school_8.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Davis also created other installations employing different media, like his &lt;i&gt;Sun Sonata&lt;/i&gt; (1983), a solar panel of color striped neon tubes installed outside Muscarelle Museum of Art in Virginia. Both his light installations and his stripe paintings in public spaces enlarged the scope of the Washington Color School art by making it part of cultural consciousness.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section title="Later Developments">
        <subsection title="">
          <p type="p">The Washington Color School's geometric, flat paintings and the sculpture of Anne Truitt influenced the development of Minimalism. As art historian James Meyer noted, Truitt's work also anticipated the work of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-horn_roni"&gt;Roni Horn&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-gonzalez_torres_felix"&gt;Félix González-Torres&lt;/span&gt; in the post-1990s. During the 1980s &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-neo_geo"&gt;Neo Geo&lt;/span&gt; movement ironically reinterpreted the Washington Color School's geometrical compositions. Noland and other painters associated with the group influenced subsequent generations of abstract artists in the Washington, D.C. area, both by the presence of their work and their teaching. Contemporary artist, Mark Dagley acknowledges being "heavily influenced" by Noland, whom he called "one of the last great colorists of the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century." In 2000, curator Rita Bartolo said that Hilda Thorpe had "probably taught half of the artists working in the city right now."</p>
          <p type="p">Some of the Washington Color School artists fell into obscurity in the 1980s but have since been rediscovered. In 2007, a citywide event celebrating Color Field painting was held in Washington, D.C., and subsequently, the Washington Color School Project was created to promote the work of the group in 2011. Several of Alma Thomas's works were prominently displayed in the White House during the Barack Obama administration. Sam Gilliam's work has also risen to contemporary prominence and was featured at the 2017 Venice Biennale.</p>
          <p type="p">Gene Davis's work has had a long lasting artistic and cultural impact, as shown in the installation of his &lt;i&gt;Sun Sonata&lt;/i&gt; (1983). Installed in 2008 on the William and Mary campus as the first "light painting" on campus, the university created an event where students would take silhouette shots in front of it. Contemporary artists Dan Cole and Polly Apfelbaum paired up for an exhibition &lt;i&gt;For Love of Gene Davis&lt;/i&gt; in 2014 in Philadelphia, in which both explored their debts to Davis; Apfelbaum in her installation and Cole in his videos.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks></similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top></top>
    <bottom></bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Beginning</title>
      <artist>Kenneth Noland</artist>
      <year>1958</year>
      <materials>Magna on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				Aptly named, this work marks the beginning of Noland's Washington Color School style. Its basic geometric form explores the lively effects of contrasting and complementary colors, depicted in concentric circles, centered on a square canvas. Noland eschewed representation and pictorial depth in favor of focusing on the relationships of the colors. Noland compared his painting to music, saying, "painting without subject matter as music without words." The slight irregularity of the circles and the outer ragged halo of black paint give the work a kind of spontaneous energy, while the circular form draws the viewer's eye back toward the hypnotic center. 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				&lt;i&gt;Beginning&lt;/i&gt; exemplifies the artist's desire to create what he called "one shot" compositions. Noland's technique of staining the canvas meant that his paintings were extremely difficult to revise; what he put on the canvas had to stand as it was without second-guessing. Noland's "one shot" painting sought to overcome, in his estimation, the overworked compositions of the Abstract Expressionists. The Abstract Expressionists claimed that spontaneity was a cornerstone of their processes, but often their canvases were carefully built up over a period of time, sometimes years. Noland felt his paintings were truly spontaneous. As Greenberg wrote of Noland's circles, "His color counts by its clarity and its energy; it is not there neutrally, to be carried by the design and drawing; it does the carrying itself." The concentric circle on a square canvas became an iconic feature of Noland's work. In later works like &lt;i&gt;Birth&lt;/i&gt; (1961), he reduced the number of colors, eliminated the penumbra effect, and regularized the concentric circles with hard edges, evolving his reductive approach. 
			</desc>
      <collection>Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Faces</title>
      <artist>Morris Louis</artist>
      <year>1959</year>
      <materials>Acrylic resin (Magna) on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				This large canvas exemplifies Louis's &lt;i&gt;Veil&lt;/i&gt; (1958-1960) series of paintings, each depicting a similar shape, rendered in translucent 'veils' or layers of magna paint diluted with turpentine. Rather than emphasizing a geometric shape like Noland, Louis creates a more organic form, not nested, but enfolded, while exploring color and transparency. As art historian Karen Wilkin explains, Louis and other Color Field painters believed "that a painting, no matter how apparently restrained, could address the viewer's whole being - emotions, intellect, and all - through the eye, just as music did through the ear." 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				Creating works like &lt;i&gt;Faces&lt;/i&gt; in a very small studio, Louis began by stapling the 20-foot canvas to the wall, then pouring and manipulating streams of paint down the surface. Rather than the artist's brushstroke, the fluidity of the material, drawn by gravity to flow down the pictorial surface, is emphasized. The soak stain approach resulted in the colors melding with the weave of the raw canvas to create a diaphanous, layered effect. Through a veil of darker surface color, remnants of vibrant orange and green create a sense of movement. Relinquishing artistic control over the unpredictable results, Louis let the medium take on its own organic process to create the final result, as the paint itself became the subject. With this emphasis on the paint's own properties, Louis subverts the presence of the artist seen on the canvas, eschewing the unique gesture associated with Abstract Expressionists like Jackson Pollock and Willem de Kooning. Of the &lt;i&gt;Veil&lt;/i&gt; series, Greenberg wrote, "The effect conveys a sense not only of color as somehow disembodied, and therefore more purely optical, but also of color as a thing that opens and expands the picture plane," and the art critic Michael Fried wrote, "the surfaces themselves...[spread]... with tremendous authority across the veil configurations as if in compliance with impersonal forces." These forces were to find analogous feelings within the viewer.
			</desc>
      <collection>Smithsonian Museum of American Art, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Insurrection</title>
      <artist>Anne Truitt</artist>
      <year>1962</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on wood</materials>
      <desc>
				This minimal and static object generates a dynamic energy that belies its simplicity. This large vertical sculpture, including the base, is divided asymmetrically into two shades of red, cleanly delineated from one another. As a result, the asymmetricality creates a kind of optical movement, with the dividing line both receding and projecting depending on one's perspective, and the two reds vie for foreground and background positions. Truit said, "Painted into color, this wooden structure is rendered virtually immaterial. The color is thus set free into space." Trained as a psychologist, she felt color had a psychological vibration, which could be clarified in an artwork, becoming an event, felt as a visual sensation. 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				Truitt, more than her colleagues in Washington D.C., felt more emotional resonances with the Abstract Expressionists' goals. Residing in Washington, D.C., Truitt's artistic breakthrough in the early 1960s was influenced by the work of Barnett Newman, particularly by his subtle color modulations in the blue double paneled work, &lt;i&gt;Onement VI&lt;/i&gt; (1953). As she said of the gallery encounter with Newman's work, "I looked at them, and from that point on I was home free. I had never realized you could do it in art. Have enough space. Enough color."
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				While her work largely anticipated Minimalist sculpture of the later 1960s, she is more often than not, associated with the Minimalists. She herself insisted, however, "I have never allowed myself, in my own hearing, to be called a minimalist. Because minimal art is characterized by nonreferentiality. And that's not what I am characterized by. [My work] is totally referential. I've struggled all my life to get maximum meaning in the simplest possible form." 
			</desc>
      <collection>The National Gallery of Art, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Untitled</title>
      <artist>Howard Mehring</artist>
      <year>1962</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				This square canvas, symmetrically divided into concentric squares and employing a color palette of speckled blue, orange, and violet, displays Mehring's interest in the surface of color. The basic geometric form of the square becomes, by repetition and variations in size, a complex arrangement of interlocking shapes that draws the viewer's eye to the center. The use of blue in the center of the composition creates dynamic movement, as the adjacent areas, broken up by purples and oranges, have a zigzag effect.
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				Unlike most of the Washington Color School artists, Mehring preferred to use thick pigments, creating a weight of luminosity. Each inch of the canvas becomes its own field of color, illuminated by specks of varying hues. As a result, while his work eschews the illusion of pictorial depth, the flat image takes on a dense but luminous materiality that sets his work apart from his Washington colleagues.
			</desc>
      <collection>The Phillips Collection, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Black Grey Beat</title>
      <artist>Gene Davis</artist>
      <year>1964</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				This painting, with its hard-edged stripes of equal width in different colors and shades, exemplifies Davis's emphasis on what he called the "color interval," the rhythmic effect created by the irregular appearance of color. Here yellow, red, green, and pink stripes pop vibrantly among black and grey stripes. Though the hard edge and uniform size of the stripes creates an orderly, almost calculated effect, the unpredictability of color creates the visual equivalent of jazz improvisation. He creates a complex schema of simplified forms to invite extended viewing and convey an unpredictable beat of spontaneity and play. 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				Considered a leader in the Washington Color School, Davis emphasized what the art critic Barbara Rose called the "primacy of color." Davis was also a relentless experimenter. He subsequently explored a variety of formats, including video, neon, collages, modular compositions, as well as what he called micropaintings, an inch square, and public installations like his &lt;i&gt;Franklin's Footpath&lt;/i&gt; (1972), a stripe painting filling the street in front of the Philadelphia Museum of Art. His work brought a playful intensity to the abstract forms of color field painting. As art critic Paul Richards wrote, "[O]n the lintel of his doorway he would inscribe one word ...'Whim.'"
			</desc>
      <collection>Smithsonian American Art Museum, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Shoot</title>
      <artist>Kenneth Noland</artist>
      <year>1964</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				In the 1960s, Noland led the way as the Washington Color School moved toward a hard edge approach to their compositions. Having explored the concentric circle in hard-edged images like &lt;i&gt;Birth&lt;/i&gt; (1961), he began to explore the chevron's V-shape, its straight lines of color outlined by thin lines of the neutral color of the canvas. The hard-edged, geometric form divides the canvas itself into triangles, two in neutral color on either side of the chevron's inverted triangular shape. 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				Noland explored the relationships of contrasting and complementary colors when adjacent to one another while, at the same time, exploiting a nested shape. As the apex of the chevron intersects with the lower edge of the canvas, a sense of energetic tension is created. The work itself becomes what Noland called a "color structure," where color determines the outer edge of the composition. Noland's chevrons draw attention to the tension between flatness and depth, foreground and background.
			</desc>
      <collection>Smithsonian American Art Museum, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Marmara</title>
      <artist>Paul Reed</artist>
      <year>1968</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				Reed titled this radically shaped canvas for a sea in Turkey. Trapezoids of various shapes in hues of red, orange, yellow, and brown surround a blue center, shaped almost like a key hole. Painted with matte and fluorescent pigment, the shapes create a sense of movement that lifts the overall shape off the wall, creating a dynamic, three-dimensional effect. 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				Reed's reference to Turkey, suggests that we are looking through an Islamic arch, abstracted to the geometric shape of the center blue, which was meant to reference a body of water. However, in essence, the abstract shape becomes an object without reference that seems to inhabit space, receding and advancing as it effects the viewer's perception. The work both exemplifies the 1960s hard-edged style for which the Washington Color School became known and emphasizes the sculptural possibilities of painting. 
			</desc>
      <collection>D. Wigmore Fine Art, New York, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Swing</title>
      <artist>Sam Gilliam</artist>
      <year>1969</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas, aluminum</materials>
      <desc>
				With this innovative work, Gilliam stained then squeezed and folded a large sheet of canvas and hung it in draping folds. In doing so, he freed the color field from its frame. The work takes on a sculptural materiality, both organic in its folds and geometric in its four triangular points attached to the wall. Gilliam's intent was to make color move, taking on an intense physicality. 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				Dubbed "the father of the draped canvas," Gilliam began using unsupported canvas in 1965 and is credited with inventing the technique, inspired by watching laundry being hung on a clothesline. Deeply influenced by the jazz music of artists like John Coltrane, Gilliam expressed his artistic intent as to "just work and let things go," and he felt a painting should exist in real space, not separated from it by a frame. In the later 1970s, Gilliam fell out of the limelight, in part because as an African American artist, his abstract paintings did not speak directly to the plight of black Americans during the civil rights movements, and it is only since the first decade of the 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century that his work is being reevaluated. 
			</desc>
      <collection>Smithsonian American Art Museum, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Sky Light</title>
      <artist>Alma Thomas</artist>
      <year>1973</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				A crackled and interlocking field of blue shapes on white canvas exemplifies Thomas's mosaic approach to creating an abstraction of luminous color. While avoiding any illusion of depth, the surface is energetic with darker and lighter intensities of blue, outlined and lit up by thin outlines of white. In the flat pictorial plane, the varying shapes evoke both a finely fractured piece of colored glass and a fractal, where an organic shape dissolves into similar shapes on an ever-smaller scale. As a result, the field conveys a sense of infinity, which led art critic Ken Johnson to call her "an incandescent pioneer."
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				Thomas, an African American woman, turned to painting full time only in her sixties, after she had retired from teaching. Her earliest works, like &lt;i&gt;Red Abstraction&lt;/i&gt; (1959), were Abstract Expressionist in style, but she soon became an energetic presence in the Washington Color School, evolving her own unique idiom of jewel-like colors and a kind of Byzantine mosaic effect. Though many of her works were inspired by what she called her "impressions of nature" and in the 1970s included her interest in space travel, her approach was profoundly abstract. Alma Thomas's work has garnered more recent interest, as &lt;i&gt;Sky Light&lt;/i&gt; and two more of her paintings were displayed at the White House during President Barack Obama's administration. 
			</desc>
      <collection>Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden , Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="key artists" is_recommended="false">
      <subcategory name="not_to_show" class="">
        <entry>
          <id>noland_kenneth</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>louis_morris</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>truitt_anne</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>mehring_howard</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>davis_gene</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>reed_paul</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>gilliam_sam</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <id>thomas_alma</id>
          <link />
          <title />
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="art story website features" />
    <category name="current exhibitions" />
    <category name="videos">
      <subcategory name="" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>USA Artists: The New Abstraction: Morris Louis, Kenneth Noland (1966)</title>
          <link>https://archive.org/details/artiststhenewabstractionmorrislouisandkennethnoland</link>
          <info>By National Educational Television and Radio Center; Indiana University, Bloomington. Audio-Visual Center</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Washington Color and Light at the Corcoran Gallery of Art</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="youtube">rQyqCzGhkP8</link>
          <info>
						PBS News Hour
						&lt;br&gt;
						August 5, 2011
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Washington Color and School</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="youtube">HXa06GqKGQs</link>
          <info>
						Robert Aubry Davis with Janice Goodman and Bill Dunlap
						&lt;br&gt;
						February 2, 2011
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="Artist Specific Videos:" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Meet Sam Gilliam</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="youtube">SjHpTmzGg4o</link>
          <info>Smithsonian</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Artist Anne Truitt on Her Work</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="youtube">CAg-97Wiz3Q</link>
          <info>Simon and Schuster Books</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Anne Truitt Perception and Reflection</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="vimeo">21678311</link>
          <info>
						PBS NewsHour's Art Beat
						&lt;br&gt;
						October 2009
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Gene Davis</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="youtube">HFuYqgIFh9Q</link>
          <info>Phoenix Film and Video</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="Lectures/Talks:" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Morris Louis: Court Painter of the Kennedy Era</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="youtube">6czZ3nxfhR4</link>
          <info>By WGBH Forum</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Who's Afraid of Morris Louis?</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="youtube">zTGKHhusYss</link>
          <info>WGBH Forum</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>For the Love of Gene Davis: The Legacy of Color Field Painting</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="youtube">iQiUeYd1G7E</link>
          <info>Smithsonian</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>About the Arts: Kenneth Noland and Diane Weinstein, 1977</title>
          <link is_inline_video="true" inline_video_type="youtube">XfQAI2-LX5I</link>
          <info>DukeLibDigitalColl</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="not_to_show" class=""></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry>
          <title>Daybook: The Journal of an Artist</title>
          <link>1476740984</link>
          <info>By Anne Truitt, Introduction by Audrey Niffenegger</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="artworks" class="artwork">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Kenneth Noland: A Retrospective : The Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, New York</title>
          <link>0892070099</link>
          <info>By Diane Waldman</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Anne Truitt: Perception and Reflection</title>
          <link>190483261X</link>
          <info>By Kristen Hileman, James Meyer and Anne Truitt</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Memory Work: Anne Truitt and Sculpture</title>
          <link>0520286618</link>
          <info>By Miguel de Baca</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Morris Louis Now</title>
          <link>1932543104</link>
          <info>By Kelly Morris, Lori Cavagnaro, and Jeffrey Grove</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Sam Gilliam: A Retrospective</title>
          <link>0520246454</link>
          <info>By Jonathan P. Binstock, Walter Hopps, and Jacqueline D. Serwer</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Gene Davis: A Memorial Exhibition</title>
          <link>0874748542</link>
          <info>By Jacqueline Days Serwer</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Anne Truitt official website</title>
          <link>http://www.annetruitt.org</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Morris Louis official website</title>
          <link>http://morrislouis.org/paintings</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Kenneth Noland official website</title>
          <link>http://www.kennethnoland.com/works/1950-1960.php</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Sam Gilliam</title>
          <link>https://americanart.si.edu/artist/sam-gilliam-1811</link>
          <info>By Smithsonian Museum of American Art</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Alma Thomas</title>
          <link>https://americanart.si.edu/artist/alma-thomas-4778</link>
          <info>By Smithsonian Museum of American Art</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Gene Davis</title>
          <link>https://americanart.si.edu/artist/gene-davis-1147</link>
          <info>By Smithsonian Museum of American Art</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Paul Reed and the Shaped Canvas in the 1960s</title>
          <link>https://abstractcritical.com/note/paul-reed-and-the-shaped-canvas-in-the-1960s/index.html</link>
          <info>
						By Deedee Wigmore
						&lt;br&gt;
						Abstract Critical 
						&lt;br&gt;
						October 2, 2013
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Beer with a Painter: Sam Gilliam</title>
          <link>https://hyperallergic.com/284543/beer-with-a-painter-sam-gilliam/</link>
          <info>
						By Jennifer Samet
						&lt;br&gt;
						Hyperallergic 
						&lt;br&gt;
						March 19, 2016
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>A Guide to the CIA's Favorite Artists</title>
          <link>https://www.format.com/magazine/features/art/guide-to-cia-favorite-artists</link>
          <info>
						By Jake Romm
						&lt;br&gt;
						October 17, 2016
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Kenneth Noland, Abstract Painter of Brilliantly Colored Shapes, Dies at 85</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2010/01/06/arts/06noland.html</link>
          <info>
						By William Grimesian
						&lt;br&gt;
						New York Times 
						&lt;br&gt;
						January 6, 2010
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Anne Truitt's Artistic Journey</title>
          <link>https://www.smithsonianmag.com/arts-culture/anne-truitts-artistic-journey-143259617/</link>
          <info>
						By Katy June-Friesen
						&lt;br&gt;
						Smithsonian Magazine 
						&lt;br&gt;
						September 29, 2009
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>A Black Woman Stands Out Among the Washington Color School Artists</title>
          <link>https://hyperallergic.com/313199/a-black-woman-stands-out-among-the-washington-color-school-artists/</link>
          <info>
						By Seph Rodney
						&lt;br&gt;
						Hyperallergic 
						&lt;br&gt;
						October 11, 2016
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Painter Who Earned His Stripes:Gene Davis</title>
          <link>https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smithsonian-institution/painter-who-earned-his-stripes-180961348/</link>
          <info>
						By Roger Catlin
						&lt;br&gt;
						Smithsonian Magazine 
						&lt;br&gt;
						December 13, 2016
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="interviews" class="interviews"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop"></subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
</data>