<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>benglis_lynda</id>
    <name>Lynda Benglis</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1960s - present</years>
    <description>Lynda Benglis posed for an outrageous advertisement, an infamous act of protest, made her famous but failed to call attention to the artist's superb sculptures.</description>
    <art_description>Important art &amp; artworks analysis by Lynda Benglis including: Artforum advertisement, Quartered Meteor &amp; more in Conceptual Art, &amp; Feminist Art.</art_description>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <highlight>1</highlight>
    <occupation>Sculptor, Painter, Conceptual and Performance Artist</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>October 25, 1941</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Lake Charles, Louisiana</birthPlace>
    <img_version>?1</img_version>
    <art_type>Sculptures</art_type>
    <pub_time>12/7/2015</pub_time>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>conceptual_art</include>
    <include>performance_art</include>
    <include>feminist_art</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>conceptual_art</movement>
    <movement>performance_art</movement>
    <movement>feminist_art</movement>
    <movement>body_art</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>morris_robert</artist>
    <artist>stella_frank</artist>
    <artist>riley_bridget</artist>
    <artist>guerrilla_girls</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"I can't deny anything the viewer reads into the work; that is the viewer's pleasure, hopefully. I am a permissive artist. I allow things to happen. I believe the viewer is half the work. Duchamp said it and I believe it."</q>
    <q>"I just wanted to go beyond, and create something that was visually more. I was interested in excess, buoyancy, weight, gesture of material. It was very different from abstract expressionism."</q>
    <q>"I think mediums are all about form. They're mediums that I can make sketch as I think of myself as doing drawings and paintings in these different mediums. I think of them as forms from nature, about nature and having illusion. Some are dependent on the walls, some are dependent on the floor and some are outside pieces."</q>
    <q>"My work is an expression of space. What is the experience of moving? Is it pictorial? Is it an object? Is it a feeling? It all comes from my body. [...] I am the form."</q>
    <q author="Susan Richmond on Lynda Benglis' &quot;fallen paintings&quot;">"The method of pouring latex directly onto the floor was, for Benglis, a pragmatic solution to what she considered to be an illogical attachment to a rectilinear ground. The constrictions of the conventional painting format prohibited the kinds of composition she sought to achieve with her material processes; by attending to the interactions of color on color, rather than color on canvas, she effectively dissolved the two-dimensional surface and its assertion as a physical ground."</q>
    <q author="Amelia Jones">"The images of Benglis producing her large-scale sculptures [...] aggressively stage the act of production."</q>
    <q author="Roberta Smith on Lynda Benglis' career">"Whether you have been watching Ms. Benglis's varied career for decades or know her primarily from the latex pieces and her star turn in Artforum, this exhibition pulls together and elaborates her remarkable career in a thrilling way. It proves her work to be at once all over the place and very much of a piece, as well as consistently, irrepressibly ahead of its time. This would seem to be every renegade artist's dream."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="souter">Anna Souter</author>
  </authors>
  <editors>
    <editor link="epstein">Ruth Epstein</editor>
  </editors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Though best-described as a sculptor, Lynda Benglis is impossible to align with a single movement or medium. In 1968, she began pouring latex or polyurethane foam onto the floor of her studio and into the corners. The resulting forms were both painterly and sculptural. By the 1970s she was casting these works in bronze and incorporating other metals in unusual combinations. Furious when her innovations were ignored by the New York art world, she posed for an outrageous advertisement for an upcoming exhibition of her work, oiled up, wearing nothing but sunglasses, and brandishing an enormous dildo. This infamous act of protest, a deservedly unforgettable moment in Feminist art history, made Benglis famous but failed to call attention to the artist's superb sculptures. Only over the past decade has Benglis begun to receive recognition as a major contributor to late-20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;- and 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;-century art.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Benglis was the first artist to make sculptures out of paint, eliminating the boundary between painting and sculpture - two traditionally separate art forms.</idea>
      <idea>Benglis's work is a continuation of the Abstract Expressionist tradition of dripping and pouring pigment from above. She takes the process one step further, however, eliminating the canvas and pouring directly onto the floor, allowing the walls and corners to shape the piece.</idea>
      <idea>In her use of candy colors, glitter and other craft materials, she distanced herself from the serious, brooding color and macho materials used by her contemporaries. In doing so, she sought to question traditional gendered distinctions in art, above all the opposition between art and craft.</idea>
      <idea>Her willingness to use her own body in art films and play stereotypically feminine roles (her pornstaresque appearance in &lt;i&gt;Artforum&lt;/i&gt; in 1974, for example) paved the way for Cindy Sherman and other artists who specialize in experimental role play, and ushered in a new era in self-portraiture.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">The eldest of five children, Lynda Benglis was born into a Greek-American family and raised in Lake Charles, Louisiana. Her mother was the daughter of a preacher from Mississippi. Her father ran a business selling building materials, an early influence on her work: "I'm a real fan of surfaces. My father ... had samples of colors and plastics and laminates and woods in his car. I was always very interested."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="img" alt="Lynda Benglis Biography" show="0">/images20/photo/benglis_1.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">In 1964, she received a BFA from Newcomb College, New Orleans, and she subsequently became a teacher at Jefferson Parish, Louisiana. At this time she married her first husband, art historian Michael Kampen, whom she describes as "the only good-looking graduate-school guy at a girls' school." The marriage lasted only a matter of months and ended with Benglis throwing a brick at his car. Very soon afterward she moved to New York, where she continues to live and work.</p>
          <p type="p">Benglis went to study painting under abstract artist Reuben Tam at the Brooklyn Museum Art School. It was here that she met Gordon Hart, a Scottish painter whom she would later marry. She would later say that she only married Hart to help him avoid the draft. During her time at art school, she met budding artists &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-stella_frank"&gt;Frank Stella&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-riley_bridget"&gt;Bridget Riley&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-newman_barnett"&gt;Barnett Newman&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
          <p type="p">Despite her training in painting and her frequent use of paint as a material in her work, she soon moved away from a traditional canvas-based approach and started to make a series of sculptural works in various media. Her work was first exhibited at the influential Bykert Gallery in New York in 1968, where she had been working as an assistant to the gallery's owner, Klaus Kertess. Her first solo show was exhibited by the Paula Cooper Gallery, the first gallery to open in New York's SoHo district. Paula Cooper subsequently represented her for several years.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Lynda Benglis Photo" show="0">/images20/photo/benglis_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">In the late 1960s and 1970s, Benglis' experimentations with a range of media and art forms began to receive widespread notice. She says of herself, "I think I thrived in the New York scene. When I arrived pop art was peaking and pop art had a lot of irony and took on a kind of irony about the artists themselves, they were not shy ... they mocked the material which is art. So when I was in the art world, at a very young age, I saw that I didn't want to think just one way. That I wanted to ask many questions within the context of the materials that I use, and I continue to do that." She freed paint from canvas, pouring it directly onto the floor. In 1970, &lt;i&gt;Life&lt;/i&gt; magazine ran a double-page spread on her which compared her process to that of Jackson Pollock, cementing her growing reputation.</p>
          <p type="p">Pop art and Minimalism were beginning to dominate the art scene. Among the older and more established artists who were supportive of her work, were the Minimalist &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-andre_carl"&gt;Carl Andre&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-warhol_andy"&gt;Andy Warhol&lt;/span&gt;. Warhol asked her to appear naked in one of his films. She refused. Benglis was among the women artists who noticed a male hegemony that was defining artistic practice, and permitting the use of certain materials considered masculine (stone, bricks, clay, steel, paint, etc.) while forbidding others. She sought to undermine this through her alternative use of materials that ran against the grain, and through her presentation of herself as a work of art.</p>
          <p type="p">In spite of this, Benglis and her work have a complex relationship with feminism. She is the author of one of the most controversial images in the history of feminist art. When &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-morris_robert"&gt;Robert Morris&lt;/span&gt;, an artist with whom she had worked collaboratively and in dialogue, placed an advertisement in Artforum magazine depicting himself in S&amp;M gear, she soon replied with her own advertisement in the magazine in November 1974. She filled the spread with a confrontational image of herself wearing nothing but a pair of sunglasses and holding an oversized dildo (Robert Morris helped her pick it out). The image continues to spark conversation on gender bias in the art world; in the 1970s, it provoked a range of reactions from humor to outrage, and raised questions about persistent sexism in New York art circles, the role of pornography in contemporary life, and what it meant to be a feminist. To some, the image was a brave protest against the unequal treatment of women. To others, the artist's hyper-sexualized nudity perpetuated the very problem she sought to confront. The image itself provided no easy answers or helpful solutions.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Lynda Benglis" show="0">/images20/photo/benglis_3.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Despite being predominantly based in New York, she also traveled the world, spending time at her grandparents' house on the Greek island of Megisti, which she now owns. She also became acquainted with New Mexico, and has two studios in the desert outside Santa Fe. She continues to be a keen traveler, saying that "travel is when I can relax."</p>
          <p type="p">In 1979, she traveled to Ahmedabad, India, where she was the artist-in-residence for a well-known family who lived in a door-less house designed by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-le_corbusier"&gt;Le Corbusier&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rauschenberg_robert"&gt;Robert Rauschenberg&lt;/span&gt; and Robert Morris had both previously held the position, and had recommended her. It was on this trip that she met her life partner Anand Sarabhai, her host's son. Sarabhai died in 2003, an event which affected her and her work deeply. Talking about some of her mid-2000s ceramic sculptures, she says "there was a lot of black in the beginning because I lost my partner of over 30 years, Anand Sarabhai."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Lynda Benglis Portrait" show="0">/images20/photo/benglis_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Benglis continues to practice as an artist today, and the variety of her work is testament to the current pluralism of artistic styles which was born in the 1970s, and which she herself helped to create. Elisabeth Lebovici argues that Benglis wants to avoid being pigeon-holed, and consequently pursues "an extraordinary undermining operation", both of her own work and of dominant trends in whatever period she is working in. This creative freedom has allowed her to create such recent works as her 2013 &lt;i&gt;Jicarilla&lt;/i&gt; series in semi-glazed ceramics and &lt;i&gt;Pi Tangerine&lt;/i&gt; in 2009, a ball of urethane dyed with orange pigment.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">Until recently, Lynda Benglis' work received relatively little critical notice and surprisingly few large solo exhibitions. In recent years, however, several notable institutions have exhibited her work. Retrospectives have been held at the Irish Museum of Modern Art, Dublin (2009), the Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles (2011) and the Hepworth Wakefield, West Yorkshire (2015). Her work has also been included in the seminal 2007 exhibition, "WACK! Art and the Feminist Revolution" at MOCA, Los Angeles.</p>
          <p type="p">Her influence on a younger generation of artists is also becoming more evident and is now fairly well documented. For example, the photographer Cindy Sherman has claimed that seeing Benglis' &lt;i&gt;Artforum&lt;/i&gt; advertisement constituted "one of the most pivotal moments of my career." As Laura Hoptman, a curator at MoMA puts it, "anybody who is using that bodily biomorphism is Benglis. Anybody who is being very out with her sexuality is Benglis."</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="chicago_judy">Through the Flower (1973)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="morris_robert">Advertisement for Castelli-Sonnabend Exhibition (1974)</artwork>
    <artwork from="movement" page="feminist_art">Anatomy of a Kimono (1974)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Fallen Painting</title>
      <year>1968</year>
      <materials>Pigmented Latex Rubber</materials>
      <desc>This work is around 30ft long and dates from a breakthrough period in Benglis's career. The artist poured latex rubber pigment in brightly-colored hues onto the floor of her studio. Unlike conventional oil or acrylic paint, the rubber remained in the shape of the artist's spill, preserving her gesture, and needed no canvas. It was a self-sufficient artwork. As Susan Richmond points out, "each pour was the product of a complex choreography, necessitating a balance of spontaneity and precision, not to mention physical endurance, as the artist frequently wielded five-gallon cans of the pigmented medium." The resulting form is sculptural; it is meant to be exhibited on the floor, and takes up a significant portion of the space in which the work is exhibited. For feminist scholar and art historian Amelia Jones, &lt;i&gt;Fallen Painting&lt;/i&gt; is about "the depravity of the fallen woman", and resembles a "prone victim of phallic male desire."</desc>
      <collection>Albright-Knox Art Gallery, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Now</title>
      <year>1973</year>
      <materials>Video (Color, Sound)</materials>
      <desc>Lynda Benglis made several video pieces in the 1970s, when she was working at the University of Rochester and could use the school's equipment. &lt;i&gt;Now&lt;/i&gt; is the most well-known of these works, and made a significant impact on the field of video art and critical theory. The screen shows the artist standing in front of a monitor, viewing another recording of herself inside it. These dual versions of the artist talk throughout the film, while the artist's voice can be heard in an additional voiceover. Throughout the film, these three different versions of the artist shout instructions and questions, such as: "now!", "now?", "start recording", and "do you wish to direct me?" The theme of auto-eroticism is palpable. At one point Benglis French-kisses her double inside the monitor. The overall effect is disorienting, yet sensuous, beckoning the viewer into the self-referential world of the video. It was the inspiration for Rosalind Krauss' seminal essay on video art, 'Video: The Aesthetics of Narcissism.' (1976) As Krauss acknowledged, Benglis had broken new ground in examining how the artist's voice and image might act as subject, object, and raw material for the artwork.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Psi</title>
      <year>1973</year>
      <materials>Aluminum, cotton bunting, plaster, silver paint, enamel, and "sparkles"</materials>
      <desc>One of a series of works named after letters of the Greek alphabet, Psi is a sculptural knot made from various materials. Its twisting shapes are heavily reminiscent of organs or intestines. The momentum inherent in its never-ending form takes the eye on an endless journey. Like &lt;i&gt;Now&lt;/i&gt; (1973), Benglis' film of the same year, it is self-referential, self-contained, and apparently infinite. Here the use of glitter, a distinctly "girlish" material, invites the viewer to consider the work from a gendered perspective, but is simultaneously confrontational about why the viewer makes assumptions about the gendering of the material in the first place.</desc>
      <collection>Cheim and Read Gallery, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Artforum advertisement</title>
      <year>1974</year>
      <materials />
      <desc>
				After being refused editorial space in &lt;i&gt;Artforum&lt;/i&gt;, an eminent art magazine, the enraged Benglis paid for an advertisement that consisted of a full-page photograph of herself, nude except sunglasses, and masturbating with an oversized double-ended dildo. It was the ultimate F--- you to the art world, and one that became so famous it has often eclipsed the rest of her art.
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				The advertisement was in part a response to an earlier ad by her friend, Robert Morris, who featured an equally sensational image: himself, naked from the waist up, bound in S&amp;M regalia. Both images were intended to highlight the absurdity of the sort of hyper-masculinity that dominated the art world. As Richard Meyer has put it, what was particularly shocking about the image was "its refusal to fall comfortably into either a feminist critique of pornography or a pornographic critique of feminism". The artist's active, even hostile stance, cropped hair, and of course, her penis, do not conform to the conventional guidelines of heterosexual eroticism, some feminists felt she was too willing to make a joke out of deep divisions in the art world, capitalizing on the attractiveness of her own spectacular body.
			</desc>
      <collection>Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, library collection</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Quartered Meteor</title>
      <year>1969</year>
      <materials>Lead</materials>
      <desc>
				This work, cast in lead in 1975, was based on an earlier composition created in Benglis' studio. In the earlier sculpture, she used her signature technique: pouring polyurethane into the corner of her studio, and allowing the effects of gravity to shape the slowly hardening substance, forming its sloping, rounded edges. The bottom and two sides are essentially a cast of the space created by the walls and floor. 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				In seeking to minimize her control over the work, her process is aligned with that of action painters (Pollock, for example, or Helen Frankenthaler, who put their canvases directly on the floor and dripped or poured the paint directly over it). Like the Abstract Expressionists, she welcomed the unpredictability of this process. She takes the process a step further, making a sculpture out of paint.
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				The work also challenges our preconceived notions about materials. Lead is characteristically hard and heavy, properties that are at odds with the malleability of the polyurethane sculpture on which this is based. Critic and curator Elisabeth Lebovici argues that Benglis constantly pursues an "extraordinary undermining operation" in her works. In recasting this work in lead, she undermined her own earlier use of materials, calling into question the nature of hard and soft, and alerting us to the changing nature of her process.
			</desc>
      <collection>Collection of the Tate, United Kingdom</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Eridanus</title>
      <year>1984</year>
      <materials>Bronze, zinc, copper, aluminum, wire</materials>
      <desc>In the 1980s Benglis continued to work with metal, but added wire, zinc, corrugated aluminium and other lighter materials that could be folded, bent, or twisted. These lighter, wall-mounted pieces resemble knots or folded ribbons, a significant departure from her earthbound pieces. &lt;i&gt;Eridanus&lt;/i&gt;, a knot-like form, hovers over the surface of the wall with the apparent lightness of a paper flower. In her choice and manipulation of materials, she remained focused on the tension between masculine and feminine characteristics, using metal (a traditionally masculine substance) to evoke ribbon, associated with frilly femininity. Here as in &lt;i&gt;Psi&lt;/i&gt;, Greek culture is a source of inspiration - Eridanus is a mythological river.</desc>
      <collection>National Museum of Women in the Arts</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>bourgeois_louise</entity>
        <entity>warhol_andy</entity>
        <entity>pollock_jackson</entity>
        <entity>newman_barnett</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>stella_frank</entity>
        <entity>riley_bridget</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>pop_art</entity>
        <entity>performance_art</entity>
        <entity>abstract_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>process_art</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>sherman_cindy</entity>
        <entity>baldessari_john</entity>
        <entity>harrison_rachel</entity>
        <entity>paine_roxy</entity>
        <entity>barney_matthew</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>morris_robert</entity>
        <entity>andre_carl</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>video_art</entity>
        <entity>body_art</entity>
        <entity>feminist_art</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" />
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="not_to_show" class="" />
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Lynda Benglis: Beyond Process</title>
          <link>1784534366</link>
          <info>By Susan Richmond</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Lynda Benglis</title>
          <link>2840663589</link>
          <info>By Dave Hickey and Elisabeth Lebovici</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by" />
      <subcategory name="analysis and movements" class="written-by">
        <entry>
          <title>WACK! Art and the Feminist Revolution</title>
          <link>0914357999</link>
          <info>By Cornelia Butler</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Body Art: Performing the Subject</title>
          <link>0816627738</link>
          <info>By Amelia Jones</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry>
          <title>Cheim and Read</title>
          <link>http://www.cheimread.com/artists/lynda-benglis</link>
          <info>Gallery representing the Lynda Benglis</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Shape Shifter: Lynda Benglis</title>
          <link>https://www.artinamericamagazine.com/news-features/magazines/lynda-benglis/</link>
          <info>
						By Julian Kreimer
						&lt;br&gt;
						Art in America 
						&lt;br&gt;
						December 1, 2009
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>A Life of Melting the Status Quo</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/13/arts/design/13benglis.html?_r=1</link>
          <info>
						By Hilarie M. Sheets
						&lt;br&gt;
						New York Times 
						&lt;br&gt;
						February 10, 2011
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>'I keep arriving'</title>
          <link>http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/2/57fa0484-4d13-11e1-8741-00144feabdc0.html#axzz2yz1pKn9y</link>
          <info>
						By Julie L. Belcove
						&lt;br&gt;
						Financial Times 
						&lt;br&gt;
						February 3, 2012
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Lynda Benglis - Sensuality, sex toys and sea creatures in major retrospective</title>
          <link>http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2015/feb/05/lynda-benglis-sensuality-sex-toys-sea-creatures-retrospective</link>
          <info>
						By Hannah Ellis-Peterson
						&lt;br&gt;
						The Guardian 
						&lt;br&gt;
						February 5, 2015
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Lynda Benglis</title>
          <link>https://frieze.com/article/lynda-benglis</link>
          <info>
						By Julian Myers
						&lt;br&gt;
						Frieze Magazine 
						&lt;br&gt;
						June-August, 2004
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="interviews" class="interviews">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Lynda Benglis - "You cannot kill creativity"</title>
          <link>http://www.dazeddigital.com/artsandculture/article/23484/1/lynda-benglis</link>
          <info>
						Dazed Digital
						&lt;br&gt;
						February 6, 2015
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Dancing with Clay: An Interview with Lynda Benglis</title>
          <link>http://www.artinamericamagazine.com/news-features/interviews/dancing-with-clay-an-interview-with-lynda-benglis/</link>
          <info>
						Art in America
						&lt;br&gt;
						January 30, 2014
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips" />
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry>
          <title>TateShots - Lynda Benglis</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=33Fay9DOzZM</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Lynda Benglis discusses adhesive products</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7igJ08xWH-8</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips" />
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop" />
    </category>
  </sidebar>
</data>