<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>close_chuck</id>
    <name>Chuck Close</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <is_influences>true</is_influences>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1965 - 2021</years>
    <description>Chuck Close's methodical, system-driven portraits are inseparable from his own daily reckoning with the body's own vulnerable, material condition.</description>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <highlight>2</highlight>
    <image_desc>true</image_desc>
    <occupation>Painter and Photographer</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>July 5, 1940</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Monroe, Washington</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>August 19, 2021</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>Oceanside, New York</deathPlace>
    <img_version>?2</img_version>
    <pub_time>8/1/2011</pub_time>
    <big_bio_box_img>Chuck Close, self-portrait (2016). Ceramic tile at the 86th's Street Subway Station in New York City</big_bio_box_img>
    <bio_highlight>Describing how, "I discovered about 150 dots is the minimum number of dots to make a specific recognizable person," Chuck Close pioneered &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-photorealism"&gt;Photorealism&lt;/span&gt;. "By putting little marks together," he said his monumental portraits conveyed how, "a face is a road map of someone's life."</bio_highlight>
    <hero>true</hero>
    <custom_logo>true</custom_logo>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>photorealism</include>
    <include>american_realism</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>photorealism</movement>
    <movement>pop_art</movement>
    <movement>neo_dada</movement>
    <movement>conceptual_art</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>katz_alex</artist>
    <artist>yuskavage_lisa</artist>
    <artist>flack_audrey</artist>
    <artist>warhol_andy</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"I'm pre-pixel.  They got it from me."</q>
    <q>"I realized that to deal with your nature is also to construct a series of limitations which just don't allow you to behave the way you most naturally want to behave.  So, I found it incredibly liberating to work for a long time on something even though I'm impatient.  It did not seem like such a dichotomy or a denial of who I was.  It seemed like I was taking care of who I was."</q>
    <q>"Photography is the easiest medium with which to be merely competent. Almost anybody can be competent. It's the hardest medium in which to have some sort of personal vision and to have a signature style."</q>
    <q>"I think I was driven to paint portraits to commit images of friends and family to memory. I have face blindness, and once a face is flattened out, I can remember it better."</q>
    <q>"Always the best time to paint is when people decide that painting is dead because the traditions and conventions are up for grabs."</q>
    <q>"I always thought that inspiration is for amateurs. The rest of us just show up and get to work. You sign onto a process and see where it takes you."</q>
    <q>"What difference does it make whether you're looking at a photograph or looking at a still life in front of you? You still have to look."</q>
    <q>"You don't have to reinvent the wheel every day. Today you will do what you did yesterday, and tomorrow you will do what you did today. Eventually you will get somewhere."</q>
    <q>"A photograph doesn't gain weight or lose weight, or change from being happy to being sad. It's frozen. You can use it, then recycle it."</q>
    <q>"Ease is the enemy of the artist. When things get too easy, you're in trouble."</q>
    <q>"A face is a road map of someone's life. Without any need to amplify that or draw attention to it, there's a great deal that's communicated about who this person is and what their life experiences have been."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="top">The Art Story Contributors</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Chuck Close is globally renowned for reinvigorating the art of portrait painting from the late 1960s to the present day, an era when photography had been challenging painting's former dominance in this area, and succeeding in steadily gaining critical appreciation as an artistic medium in its own right. Close emerged from the 1970s painting movement of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-photorealism"&gt;Photorealism&lt;/span&gt;, also known as Super-Realism, but then moved well beyond its initially hyper-attentive rendering of a given subject to explore how methodical, system-driven portrait painting based on photography's underlying processes (over its superficial visual appearances) could suggest a wide range of artistic and philosophical concepts. In addition, Close's personal struggles with dyslexia and subsequently, partial paralysis, have suggested real-life parallels to his professional discipline, as though his methodical and yet also quite intuitive methods of painting are inseparable from his own daily reckoning with the body's own vulnerable, material condition.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Photorealist painting of the 1970s celebrated the glossy, mirror-like "look" of the photograph, but after achieving that ideal, Close swiftly turned to portraiture, suggesting it as a means for exploring unsettling aspects of how self identity is always a composite and highly constructed, if not ultimately conflicted fiction.</idea>
      <idea>Close's dependence on the grid as a metaphor for his analytical processes, which suggest that the "whole" is rarely more (or less) than the sum of its parts, is a conceptual equivalent for the camera's analytical, serial approach to any given subject. Every street-smart, colorful Polaroid is as much a time-based and fragmentary gesture as any more laborious stroke of the painter's brush in the cloistered studio.</idea>
      <idea>Close has worked with oil and acrylic painting, photography, mezzotint printing, and various additional media. Shifting confidently from one to the other, Close suggests that his conceptual intentions are ultimately timeless, whereas his tools or materials are infinitely interchangeable. This is partly why Close's practice of portrait painting has for over forty years remained surprisingly "contemporary," even while the larger movement of Photorealism, his earliest chosen stylistic idiom, has long receded into history.</idea>
      <idea>Close's slow, accumulative processes, which enlist numerous abstract color applications in the service of producing "realistic," or illusory portraits, most recently finds application in the art of modern tapestry via a highly illusionistic, computer-aided method of industrial weaving that Close favors for its ability to suggest the hyper-real appearance of 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century glass photographs(daguerreotypes).</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Charles Thomas Close was born at home to Leslie and Mildred Close, a couple with a leaning toward artistic pursuits. Leslie Close was a jack-of-all-trades with a flair for craftsmanship; he built Charles his first easel. His mother was a trained pianist but unable to pursue a musical career due to financial constraints. Determined to provide her son with opportunities she herself never enjoyed, Mildred pushed Charles to take up a myriad of extracurricular activities during his school years and hired a local tutor to give  him private art lessons.</p>
          <p type="p">Charles had a difficult time with academics due to dyslexia, although teachers were often impressed with his creative approach to projects. He was also diagnosed at a young age with facial blindness and a neuromuscular condition that prevented him from engaging in athletics, making the social aspects of school life difficult. Once in college, and upon deciding to make a career in art, he excelled.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="p">Close received a scholarship to attend the Yale Summer School of Music and Art after his junior year at the University of Washington in Seattle, which facilitated his subsequent acceptance to the Yale MFA program in 1962. The challenging environment at Yale put him in competition with a host of talented peers, such as Nancy Graves, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-marden_brice"&gt;Brice Marden&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-mangold_robert"&gt;Robert Mangold&lt;/span&gt;. Jack Tworkov, the new director of the MFA program, supported the teaching of contemporary art movements (e.g. &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pop_art"&gt;Pop art&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalism&lt;/span&gt;) in addition to the standard focus on &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionism&lt;/span&gt;; the revised curriculum indeed proved to be a major influence on Close's later work. While at Yale, Close served as a studio assistant to printmaker Gabor Petardi. In his senior year, Close won a Fulbright scholarship, providing him with the opportunity to study art in Europe.</p>
          <p type="p">In 1965, after completing his travels abroad, Close began teaching classes at the University of Massachusetts in Amherst.  Deciding that his own Abstract Expressionist style of painting had grown stagnant, he began to experiment with alternative forms and materials. One of his more ambitious ideas of the time involved painting a large nude from a series of photographs, but he set the project aside due to unresolved problems with color and texture. In January 1967, the college held a solo exhibition of other Pop-inspired works by Close, sparking an outrage from the administration due to his use of full-frontal nude male images. The American Civil Liberties Union defended Close in the resulting lawsuit, brought on by the university president, John Lederle. Ultimately, the ruling was in favor of the university, a decision that effectively ended his time in Amherst.</p>
          <p type="p">Taking a new teaching job at the School of Visual Arts in New York City that fall, Close moved to Manhattan, where he reunited with Leslie Rose, a former student. The two subsequently  married that December. Close's search for a signature style was a persistent frustration to him, and with Rose's support, he continued to experiment with different styles drawn from contemporary art. In particular, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-process_art"&gt;Process art&lt;/span&gt; was highly popular at the moment, due to the rising fame of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-lewitt_sol"&gt;Sol LeWitt&lt;/span&gt; and others. Returning to the large photographic-based nude he had begun in Amherst, Close decided to approach the problem from a methodical angle. Working again from photographs, he parsed the image into a grid, which he then transferred onto a nine-foot-long canvas. Painstakingly hand-copying the photograph's gridded segments onto each corresponding cube of the canvas, Close built a larger-than-life, black and white copy of the female nude's image. The resulting &lt;i&gt;Big Nude&lt;/i&gt; (1967), reads as both an abstract and a figurative painting. In addition, depending on the viewing distance, the painting reads as a traditional figure drawing, or as an abstract landscape of a close up, yet barely recognizable subject.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Chuck Close Photo" show="1">/images20/photo/photo_close_chuck_1.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Close's career gained momentum from the sale of a similarly conceived &lt;i&gt;Big Self-Portrait&lt;/i&gt; (1967-68) to the Walker Art Museum in 1969, which prompted other sales shortly thereafter. Motivated by the newly-developed method of painting, he sought to refine his technique in his first "Heads" series. Also in black and white, these paintings emphasized their photographic roots. Close used the large-scale format to exaggerate the more unflattering interpretations of the camera, creating close-up views that he describes as mug shots. In December 1969, the Whitney Museum of American Art acquired a Close portrait of composer Philip Glass, and the museum also included one of the artist's works in the Whitney Annual. Earlier in the year, Close had joined Bykert Gallery, where he participated in his first New York City group exhibition with &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-benglis_lynda"&gt;Lynda Benglis&lt;/span&gt;, David Paul, and Richard van Buren. Prior to the opening of the show, writer Cindy Nemser conducted an interview with Close for the January 1970 issue of &lt;i&gt;Artforum&lt;/i&gt; magazine, which accidentally published his name as "Chuck Close." The artist subsequently adopted it as a professional moniker from that time to the present.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Chuck Close Photo" show="1">/images20/photo/photo_close_chuck_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Searching for a way to reintroduce color to his work, Close returned to photography for inspiration.  Imitating the photographic dye-transfer process, Close developed a method that utilized separate layers of cyan, magenta and yellow.  Painted on top of each other, the colors compel the eye of the observer to mix them in order to arrive at a realistic, full-color image. The first portrait executed by this method was &lt;i&gt;Kent&lt;/i&gt; (1970-71), which took Close almost a full year to complete.  He spent the next several years working on three-color-process portraits, during which his first child, Georgia, was born.</p>
          <p type="p">In the summer of 1972, Parasol Press invited Close to produce a series of prints by any method he desired. Intrigued, Close chose the mezzotint, a virtually abandoned printmaking technique common to 18&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-century portrait reproductions. Reproducing an already gridded photograph of Keith Hollingworth, the print unintentionally revealed the schematic checkerboard pattern. These unexpected results led to a Close repeated use of the same photographs for paintings executed via different techniques and in various media. Some of the more unorthodox methods he employed included fingerprinting, the use of pulp paper, and resourcing instant Polaroid, "snapshot" photographs.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Current Work">
          <p type="p">Close's current method of painting originated with his pastel portraits of 1981. These portraits are derived by Closes's juxtaposing of different colors within each cube of the grid, a process critic Christopher Finch has colorfully referred to as a "pimiento-stuffed olive." The loose handling of color and richness of the pastels resulted in a lush, tactile surface, which Close maintains in his more recent work. Through more complex combinations of color and mark-making, Close's style of portraiture has also grown closer to abstraction, which makes its integrity to certain aspects of the photographic medium all the more notable. </p>
          <p type="p">In December 1988, Close suffered from intense chest pains that led to complete paralysis below the neck, a watershed moment in his life that the artist refers to as "the Event." With the dedication of his wife, who insisted that his physical therapy focus on the act of painting, Close was able to regain enough movement and control in his upper body to allow him to continue working. Steadily strengthening his arms, he completed &lt;i&gt;Alex II&lt;/i&gt; (1989) during his rehabilitation period. The painting is much smaller than Close's previous works (&lt;i&gt;Alex II&lt;/i&gt; is only 36 x 30 inches), and it conveys a sadness that the artist describes as representative of his conflicted mindset at the time. It exhibits, however, no loss of technique. Close has since built a studio to accommodate his wheelchair and a two-storey, remote-control easel, where he continues to dynamically develop his artistic processes with the help of studio assistants. Now, in his early 70s, and continuing to evolve in his artistic practices, Close has been applying his methods to the production of highly illusionistic imagery in the format of portraits of his friends, colleagues, and others.</p>
          <p type="p">Utilizing the modern computer-aided methods of tapestry, in final years of his life Close was able to approximate, in woven images, the mirror-like illusionism characteristic of the 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century photographic glass daguerreotype (of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-daguerre_louis"&gt;Louis Daguerre&lt;/span&gt; fame). As if coming full circle, Close may be said to have reinvigorated the genre of Photorealism just when everyone had assumed it had been relegated to history.  Close died of heart failure at the age of 81.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">Coming of age at a moment when &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionism&lt;/span&gt; was still a major force in the art world and, for some, a rather inhibiting one, Close suggested that a return to a former category of painting, or realistic portraiture, could be a viable route for an artist's development. Close married this premise to his early fascination for photographic realism, focusing on the sequential and time-based process of transferring a photographic image to canvas as the conceptual premise for suggesting the construction of self identity, or the "persona," as a highly tentative undertaking, indeed despite its apparently seamless outcome. This conceptual foundation of Close's work has been his essential legacy to his many admirers and successors. The genre of portraiture itself, as well as the gridded, sequential conceptual artwork, have since the 1970s taken a very active role in &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-avant_garde"&gt;avant-garde&lt;/span&gt; circles. The mix of the photographic sequence and its painterly reconstruction is seen early on, for instance, in the late 1970s work of Jennifer Bartlett, and it resurfaces time and again in the work of more portrait-based photographers of the 1980s, such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-sherman_cindy"&gt;Cindy Sherman&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-leibovitz_annie"&gt;Annie Leibovitz&lt;/span&gt;, Cass Bird, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-goldin_nan"&gt;Nan Goldin&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-smith_kiki"&gt;Kiki Smith&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-serrano_andres"&gt;Andres Serrano&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-mapplethorpe_robert"&gt;Robert Mapplethorpe&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="pollock_jackson">Yellow Islands (1952)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="katz_alex">Red Smile (1963)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="de_kooning_willem">Woman III (1951-53)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>pollock_jackson</entity>
        <entity>lewitt_sol</entity>
        <entity>de_kooning_willem</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>glass_philip</entity>
        <entity>katz_alex</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>pop_art</entity>
        <entity>conceptual_art</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>bleckner_ross</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>glass_philip</entity>
        <entity>finch_christopher</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>photorealism</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Big Nude</title>
      <year>1967</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>"Big Nude" is the first painting completed in Close's signature grid process, and both its size and self-conscious title indicate its ambitious nature. Although the transferred image "reads" as a flat transcription of light and dark characteristic of a photograph, the painting's variegated brushstrokes reveal &lt;i&gt;Big Nude&lt;/i&gt; to be more of a prototype for future development than a fully resolved picture. Poised precariously between a common studio exercise in figure drawing and a 1960s girlie magazine shoot, "Big Nude" also challenges the future of representational painting at a moment in history when the genre would seem to have long ago exhausted its potential for future development. Only the antiseptic whiteness of the canvas hints at a new approach to the figure that might perfectly marry an instant, unforgiving photographic record of a subject with the artist's reconsideration of its every component over months of studied, methodical transcription.</desc>
      <collection>Collection Jon and Mary Shirley</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Big Self-Portrait</title>
      <year>1967-68</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>The tentative air of experimentation that might be said to characterize &lt;i&gt;Big Nude&lt;/i&gt; is nowhere apparent in &lt;i&gt;Big Self-Portrait&lt;/i&gt;, a watershed painting that virtually showcases Close's unique method. Abandoning the full-body view, Close turned to one of the oldest traditions anywhere in art history, the self-portrait. Close had partially set out to refute the critic Clement Greenberg's claim that it was impossible for an "advanced" artist to work in portraiture. Closes's untraditional approach involved conceiving of and creating a unique kind of "mug shot," a black-and-white idiom that exacerbated the subject's blemishes and the original photographic distortion caused by the camera. The devotion to the idea of an unsparing, head-on view led him to refuse all commissions, as Close used only his own "mug" and that of close friends for his subjects.</desc>
      <collection>Walker Art Center, Minneapolis</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Kent</title>
      <year>1970</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>For &lt;i&gt;Kent&lt;/i&gt;, Close made use of preparatory drawings for the first time to explore the three-color process, an imitation, or re-employment, of the photographic dye-transfer method. By adopting a mechanical procedure and mimicking it physically, or  by  hand crafting what is normally carried out  by the camera, Close suggests that illusion is ultimately in the eye of the beholder, whose own optical apparatus finally "completes" the picture. Although Close literally painted the same image three times, one atop the other in separate colors, he was surprised when the work ended up taking three times as long to complete. In order to facilitate the process, Close wore cellophane filters over his eyeglasses in order to view marks in one color at a time.</desc>
      <collection>Art Gallery of Ontario, Toronto</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Keith/Mezzotint</title>
      <year>1972</year>
      <materials>Mezzotint</materials>
      <desc>The large format of &lt;i&gt;Keith&lt;/i&gt;, although not nearly as large as Close's earlier portrait paintings, did not translate well to the outdated mezzotint process. Due to its gradual erosion, the plate made only ten good prints, and the surface coloring is noticeably lighter in the middle around the sitter's nose. The mezzotint printmaking process yields a soft, light-infused surface, here seen to best effect in Closes's rendering of the sitter's hair. The random effects typical of printmaking inspired Close to experiment further with various media.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Fanny/Fingerpainting</title>
      <year>1985</year>
      <materials>Oil-based acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Close's enjoyment of the physical interaction between artist and material gave him a particular affinity for working in the fingerprint method. Criticized by some as a kitschy version of an art already informed by Pop, the unsophisticated technique, so reminiscent of child's play, seems doubly appropriate for this informal, yet subtly monumental portrait of the artist's grandmother. The numerous, individual touches of oil pigment gradually creating the appearance of supple flesh lends to the painting a sense of intimacy so appropriate to the underlying relationship between artist and his chosen subject.</desc>
      <collection>The National Gallery of Art, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Self-Portrait</title>
      <year>1997</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Chuck Close's work is most often associated in the popular mind with his own likeness. Although it has been chosen by the artist largely for the sake of convenience, Close's  self portraits provide an interesting arena for gauging the development of his thought and work over four decades. The insouciant stare of the young man in &lt;i&gt;Big Self-Portrait&lt;/i&gt; makes a striking counterpart to the stolid, knowing gaze of the older Close as represented in this self-portrait of 1997. Indeed, the comparison illustrates the evolution from fledgling artist to international icon.  Compared to the earlier work, the 1990s &lt;i&gt;Self-Portrait&lt;/i&gt; also shows how abstraction has come to play a more prominent role in Closes's portraits. Each of the individual units of the grid is a miniature abstract painting unto itself, comprising a panoply of colors and shapes that seem to have jumped directly to the canvas from the artist's palette.</desc>
      <collection>Private Collection</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Andres</title>
      <year>2006</year>
      <materials>Jacquard tapestry</materials>
      <desc>In recent years, Close has extended his investigations into various media to the ancient genre of tapestry, the repetitive and episodic weaving process in many ways paralleling his own painstaking juxtaposition of various colors in much of his portraiture. Using computerized photo transfers of glass daguerreotypes (for black-and-white versions) or Polaroid snapshots, the tapestry medium is ideally suited for Close's interest in large-scale work that nonetheless depends on pinpoint-like precision. Here, a portrait of artist-colleague Andres Serrano, notorious for his irreverent &lt;i&gt;Piss Christ&lt;/i&gt; (1987) photograph that continues to roil conservative Christians, beams triumphant from the weave, which is deftly composed of numerous threads of various colors intertwining with such precision that the human eye is virtually seduced  into believing that this is a real man pressing his face to a window.</desc>
      <collection>PaceWildenstein Gallery, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" />
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Chuck Close: Life</title>
          <link>3791336770</link>
          <info>By Christopher Finch</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="artwork" class="artwork">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Chuck Close: Work </title>
          <link>3791344668</link>
          <info>By Christopher Finch</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Portraits Speak: Chuck Close in Conversation with 27 of His Subjects</title>
          <link>0923183183</link>
          <info>By Chuck Close, Dave Hickey, William Bartman, Joanne Kesten</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Close Reading: Chuck Close and the Artist Portrait </title>
          <link>0810959208</link>
          <info>By Martin Friedman</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by" />
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry>
          <title>Chuck Close: Process and Collaboration</title>
          <link>http://chuckclose.coe.uh.edu/</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Chuck Close: Photo Gallery</title>
          <link>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/museums/photogallery/chuckclose/chuckclose1.htm</link>
          <info>Washington Post's overview of Chuck Close and good visual insights into his techniques</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>Pixels and Painting: Chuck Close and the Fragmented Image</title>
          <link>http://archopht.ama-assn.org/cgi/content/full/126/8/1148</link>
          <info>By James Ravin and Peter Odell&lt;br/&gt;
					Ophthalmology
					&lt;br/&gt;
					August 2008</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Chuck Close</title>
          <link>http://www.brooklynrail.org/2008/06/art/chuck-close-with-phong-bui</link>
          <info>By Phong Bui
					&lt;br/&gt;
					Brooklyn Rail 
					&lt;br/&gt;
					June 2008</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Following the Light, and Making Faces</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2004/02/22/nyregion/following-the-light-and-making-faces.html?ref=chuckclose&amp;gwh=2696F9F9D5CBA2D18F90AD03CD39944A</link>
          <info>By Helen A. Harrison
					&lt;br/&gt;
					New York Times
					&lt;br/&gt;
					February 22, 2004</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Persistence of the Portraitist</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/1998/02/01/magazine/the-persistence-of-the-portraitist.html</link>
          <info>By Deborah Solomon
					&lt;br/&gt;
					New York Times 
					&lt;br/&gt;
					February 1, 1998</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="transcripts" class="transcripts">
        <entry>
          <title>Archives of American Art Oral History Interview - 1987</title>
          <link>http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/interviews/oral-history-interview-chuck-close-13141</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Navigating the Self: Chuck Close discusses portraiture and the topography of the face - 2005</title>
          <link>http://visualarts.walkerart.org/detail.wac?id=2036&amp;title=Articles</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Chuck Close on NPR - 2004</title>
          <link>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=1748083</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Interview with Chuck Close - 2010</title>
          <link>http://fnewsmagazine.com/2010/05/interview-with-chuck-close/</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Appearance on Charlie Rose - Brain Series</title>
          <link>https://charlierose.com/videos/14590</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Interview with Christopher Finch - 2010</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9DFUGsqEqG8</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop" />
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item />
      <a_image />
      <a_name />
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>