<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>cornell_joseph</id>
    <name>Joseph Cornell</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <is_influences>true</is_influences>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1925 - 1972</years>
    <description>Cornell's dream-like, glass-fronted boxes with arranged bric-a-brac, old photographs, dime-store trinkets inspired viewers and contributed to Surrealism.</description>
    <barnebys_item>156</barnebys_item>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <highlight>1</highlight>
    <occupation>Sculptor</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>December 24, 1903</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Nyack, New York</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>December 29, 1972</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>Queens, New York</deathPlace>
    <art_type>Sculptures</art_type>
    <pub_time>1/21/2012</pub_time>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>surrealism</include>
    <include>assemblage</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>surrealism</movement>
    <movement>assemblage</movement>
    <movement>dada</movement>
    <movement>pop_art</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>duchamp_marcel</artist>
    <artist>tanning_dorothea</artist>
    <artist>ernst_max</artist>
    <artist>schwitters_kurt</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"Life can have significance even if it appears to be a series of failures."</q>
    <q>"Beauty should be shared for it enhances our joys. To explore its mystery is to venture towards the sublime."</q>
    <q>"Shadow boxes become poetic theater or settings wherein are metamorphosed the elements of a childhood pastime. The fragile, shimmering globules become the shimmering but more enduring planets—a connotation of moon and tides—the association of water less subtle, as when driftwood pieces make up a proscenium to set off the dazzling white of sea foam and billowy cloud crystallized in a pipe of fancy."</q>
    <q>"collage=reality"</q>
    <q>"Among the barren wastes of the talking films there occasionally occur passages to remind one again of the profound and suggestive power of the silent film to evoke an ideal world of beauty, to release unsuspected floods of music from the gaze of a human countenance in its prison of silver light."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="ditolla">Tracy DiTolla</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Using the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealist&lt;/span&gt; technique of unexpected juxtaposition, Joseph Cornell's best-known works are glass-fronted boxes into which he placed and arranged Victorian bric-a-brac, old photographs, dime-store trinkets, and other found elements. Generally referred to as "shadow boxes," the resulting pieces are dream-like miniature tableaux that inspire the viewer to see each component in a new light. Cornell often used the shadow boxes to address recurrent themes of interest such as childhood, space, and birds, and they represented an escape of sorts for their creator, who was famously reclusive. Among the earliest examples of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-assemblage"&gt;assemblage&lt;/span&gt;, the shadow boxes also helped give rise to a host of other Modern and Contemporary American art forms, from &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-installation_art"&gt;Installation&lt;/span&gt; art to &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-fluxus"&gt;Fluxus&lt;/span&gt; boxes.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Cornell's signature art form is the shadow box. Infused with a dream-like aura, the shadow boxes invite the viewer into Cornell's own private, magical world. Alternately known as "memory boxes" or "poetic theaters," the boxes evoke the memories associated with the items contained within, while also containing parallels with, or expressing reverence for, other art forms, such as theater, ballet, and film. </idea>
      <idea>Inspired by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-duchamp_marcel"&gt;Marcel Duchamp's&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-readymade"&gt;readymades&lt;/span&gt;, Cornell elevated the found object to the center of his &lt;i&gt;oeuvre&lt;/i&gt; and embodied a new paradigm of the artist as collector and archivist. Often purchased on Cornell's frequent visits to New York secondhand shops or cut out from magazines, these objects comprise the primary materials of his art; they not only inhabit Cornell's shadow boxes, they are also key to other aspects of his artistic practice, such as his famous "dossiers," which were organized repositories of visual-documentary source material collected by the artist.</idea>
      <idea>Although he was never officially part of the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealist&lt;/span&gt; movement and came to dismiss the Surrealist label in relation to his own work, Surrealism was a major influence on Cornell, most notably inspiring his embrace of unexpected juxtapositions. Rejecting Surrealism's violent and erotic aspects, Cornell preferred instead what he described as the "white magic" side of Surrealism embodied by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-ernst_max"&gt;Max Ernst&lt;/span&gt;. Cornell played a major role in America Surrealism; in 1939, his art was famously described by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-dali_salvador"&gt;Salvador Dalí&lt;/span&gt; as "the only truly Surrealist work to be found in America."</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Joseph Cornell was born in Nyack, New York, on Christmas Eve of 1903. He was the oldest child of four including two sisters, Elizabeth and Helen, and a brother, Robert, who suffered from cerebral palsy. When Cornell was thirteen, his father died of leukemia after battling the disease for several years. After his father's death, the family moved to Douglastown, Long Island where his mother took on several odd jobs to support her children. With the help of his father's former employer, Joseph Cornell was able to attend Phillips Academy in Andover, Massachusetts, for a few years. While at Phillips, the headmaster took notice of Cornell's extreme shyness and insecurity and expressed his concern to Cornell's mother. Cornell seemed to be overly fearful of many things, and he once confided in his sister Elizabeth how frightened he was at the concept of infinity. When he was in his twenties, he learned about Christian Science and became a devout follower of the religion, as he believed it had cured him of recurring stomach ailments.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="p">Cornell received no formal art training and did not attend college. In 1929, his family moved to Utopia Parkway in Queens, where he lived for the remainder of his life. Cornell worked as a salesman at Whitman's wool shop on Madison Avenue, a job which he lost in the Depression; however, he was eventually hired as a textile designer at the Traphagen Studio. By 1932, he was also bringing home a small income from sales of his artwork.</p>
          <p type="p">Though Cornell was not formally educated, he was extremely well read and sought out culture independently, regularly attending the theater and the ballet, listening to classical music, and frequently visiting museums and art galleries. He perused small Asian shops in Manhattan to see Japanese prints, and it was at one of these shops that Cornell discovered the first boxes he would use for his art, which eventually became his signature shadow boxes.</p>
          <p type="p">During his early years, Cornell made &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-collage"&gt;collages&lt;/span&gt;, and would often buy books just so he could cut out the images inside. He also photocopied from books and magazines at the library and used them in his collages as well.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="p">In the 1930s, the New York art scene centered on a few small galleries, one being the Julien Levy Gallery where Cornell spent much of his time and encountered many &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealist&lt;/span&gt; poets and painters. Cornell designed the catalogue cover for the gallery's 1932 Surrealist show—the show that launched the Surrealism movement in America—and also had a piece in the exhibition.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Joseph Cornell Biography">/images20/photo/cornell_joseph_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">During the 1930s, Cornell often used glass bells to cover found objects and in the fall of 1932 he had his first solo exhibit at The Julien Levy Gallery, entitled &lt;i&gt;Minutiae, Glass Bells, Coups d'Oeil, Jouet Surrealistes&lt;/i&gt;. In 1936 Cornell was included in &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-museum_of_modern_art"&gt;The Museum of Modern Art's&lt;/span&gt; seminal exhibition &lt;i&gt;Fantastic Art, Dada, Surrealism&lt;/i&gt;; Cornell was represented in the show by one of his earliest boxes, &lt;i&gt;Untitled (Soap Bubble Set)&lt;/i&gt; (1936), a work later acquired by the Wadsworth Atheneum. From this point on, Cornell regularly exhibited and sold his work, in addition to doing freelance design work for magazines such as &lt;i&gt;Vogue&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;House &amp; Garden&lt;/i&gt;.</p>
          <p type="p">Cornell was also interested in filmmaking. He cut and re-edited a Hollywood film &lt;i&gt;East of Borneo&lt;/i&gt;(1931) and collaged it into a short, experimental, avant-garde film that he named after the star of the original, Rose Hobart. He also wrote film scenarios such as &lt;i&gt;Monsieur Phot&lt;/i&gt;, which was featured in Julien Levy's landmark 1936 volume, &lt;i&gt;Surrealism&lt;/i&gt;. Cornell, who was entranced by the technical side of filmmaking and had several books on the subject in his vast library, never lost his interest in the medium, and in the 1950s he made another film composed of edited outtakes of the movie &lt;i&gt;The Wonder Ring&lt;/i&gt;. His love of film was evident in his art, and he often included images of movie stars in his boxes, as in his famous piece &lt;i&gt;Untitled (Penny Arcade Portrait of Lauren Bacall)&lt;/i&gt;(1945-46).</p>
          <p type="p">Throughout the 1940s and 1950s, Cornell continued to show his work, mainly in New York but occasionally in other locations in the U.S. By the 1940s, he was known for his boxes, each of which featured mixed media and collage in a shadow box fronted with glass. His work always maintained a Surrealist quality in its removal of objects from their usual context and paired with other surprising objects, although he ultimately rejected the Surrealist label. His circle of friends included many well-known artists, such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-duchamp_marcel"&gt;Marcel Duchamp&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-motherwell_robert"&gt;Robert Motherwell&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-schneemann_carolee"&gt;Carolee Schneemann&lt;/span&gt;. </p>
          <p type="p">Cornell did all of his work in the basement of his home, which became increasingly crowded with found objects that he intended to use in his boxes. He assembled more than one hundred and sixty "dossiers," or files containing his scribbled notes and found photographic images on a variety of themes, among them space, birds, ballet, specific actresses, dancers, and films, all organized according to subject. During the later 1950s and 1960s, he produced less as he spent more time caring for his family. </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Later Years">
          <p type="img" alt="Joseph Cornell Photo">/images20/photo/cornell_joseph_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Cornell's brother died in 1965, and his mother passed away the following year, leaving him alone. He continued working for the next several years, although he was in poor health by that time. Cornell began making collages again and did not produce any new boxes, although he did tear apart and restructure some of his existing boxes. He kept extensively detailed diaries in which he wrote about his work, the look of certain sunsets, and what he ate for dinner. He continued to write letters to his mother and buy gifts for his brother even after their deaths. Cornell died of heart failure at his home just a few days after his sixty-ninth birthday.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">Cornell's influence on postwar American art was immense and varied. His shadow boxes constituted some of the earliest examples of assemblage and later helped inspire both &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-installation_art"&gt;Installation&lt;/span&gt; art and the box assemblage works of the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-fluxus"&gt;Fluxus&lt;/span&gt; movement. Cornell's use of preexisting artworks and the visual imagery of popular culture made his work an important forerunner of appropriation art and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pop_art"&gt;Pop&lt;/span&gt; art, inspiring such as artists as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-warhol_andy"&gt;Andy Warhol&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rauschenberg_robert"&gt;Robert Rauschenberg&lt;/span&gt;. Cornell also made a major contribution to the development of cinema; he was described by the film critic J. Hoberman as a "progenitor of American avant-garde film."</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="duchamp_marcel">The Bride Stripped Bare by Her Bachelors, Even, or The Large Glass (1915-1923)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="ernst_max">Celebes (1921)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="de_chirico_giorgio">Gare Montparnasse (The Melancholy of Departure) (1914)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>ernst_max</entity>
        <entity>duchamp_marcel</entity>
        <entity>de_chirico_giorgio</entity>
        <entity>schwitters_kurt</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>duchamp_marcel</entity>
        <entity>tanning_dorothea</entity>
        <entity>motherwell_robert</entity>
        <entity>sontag_susan</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>surrealism</entity>
        <entity>dada</entity>
        <entity>constructivism</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>warhol_andy</entity>
        <entity>rauschenberg_robert</entity>
        <entity>johnson_ray</entity>
        <entity>schneemann_carolee</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>schneemann_carolee</entity>
        <entity>duchamp_marcel</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>fluxus</entity>
        <entity>neo_dada</entity>
        <entity>pop_art</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Untitled (Tilly-Losch)</title>
      <year>c. 1935</year>
      <materials>Wood, glass, paper, box construction</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Tilly-Losch&lt;/i&gt; is one of Cornell's many signature shadow boxes: glass-fronted boxes filled with found items carefully arranged in small-scale tableaux. With its dream-like imagery and subject matter that revolves around childhood memory, &lt;i&gt;Tilly-Losch&lt;/i&gt; addresses themes that would recur throughout Cornell's &lt;i&gt;oeuvre&lt;/i&gt;. It features a cut-out image of a girl suspended by strings against a sky-blue background, hovering above an image of a mountain range as she holds a wooden bead on a string. The piece takes its name from the Viennese actress and dancer Tilly Losch, who lived and worked in the United States, appearing in several Hollywood films of the 1930s and 1940s. As such, it evokes Cornell's interest in filmmaking and movie stars, both of which would figure largely in his work, while the piece's stage-like setting is a nod to Cornell's love of theater.</desc>
      <collection>The Robert Lehman Art Trust, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Untitled (Soap Bubble Set)</title>
      <year>1936</year>
      <materials>Wood, glass, plastic, paper, box construction</materials>
      <desc>Made for the 1936 Museum of Modern Art exhibition &lt;i&gt;Fantastic Art, Dada, and Surrealism&lt;/i&gt;, this work was the first of Cornell's shadow boxes, containing many of the characteristic features of his signature art form. In these works, Cornell used the Surrealist practice of juxtaposing unrelated found objects, in this case, a doll's head, a clay pipe used to make soap bubbles, a bird's egg, a glass, an antique map of the moon, and a print of the leaning tower at Pisa. Some writers have interpreted the piece as a family portrait, with the doll's head "depicting" the artist, the egg symbolizing his mother, the pipe his father, and the four blocks at the top as Cornell and his three siblings. The box was one of numerous works titled &lt;i&gt;Soap Bubble Set&lt;/i&gt;, a theme linked by their creator not only with childhood but also with the cosmos.</desc>
      <collection>Wadsworth Atheneum Museum, Hartford</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Taglioni's Jewel Casket</title>
      <year>1940</year>
      <materials>Wood box, velvet, glass cubes, glass necklace</materials>
      <desc>In addition to shadow boxes, Cornell created other box works as well, including this piece. &lt;i&gt;Taglioni's Jewel Casket&lt;/i&gt; notably lacks the protective glass covering of the shadow boxes and resembles a real jewelry box, with its velvet lining and open lid (from which hangs a rhinestone necklace purchased at a New York Woolworth's dime store) the box seems to beckon to the viewer not only to gaze at but also handle the objects within.
					&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				This work, one of dozens of boxes the artist created referencing specific 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-century ballerinas, reflects Cornell's practice of working in series—appropriate to an artist who liked to collect and categorize. It also reflects Cornell's love of ballet. Among his favorite ballerinas was the acclaimed Italian dancer Marie Taglioni, who according to legend, kept an imitation ice cube in her jewelry box to commemorate dancing in the snow at the behest of a Russian highwayman. The legend is printed on the inside cover of &lt;i&gt;Taglioni's Jewel Casket&lt;/i&gt; and referenced in the rows of glass cubes, suggestive of both ice and precious jewels.
			</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Untitled (Medici Boy)</title>
      <year>1942–52</year>
      <desc>In addition to combing disparate objects, Cornell sometimes also juxtaposed far-flung eras and locales. The early-15&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century and the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century come together in &lt;i&gt;Medici Boy&lt;/i&gt;. Part of Cornell's &lt;i&gt;Medici Slot Machine&lt;/i&gt; series, &lt;i&gt;Medici Boy&lt;/i&gt; features repeated renderings of the early Italian Renaissance painter Bernardino Pinturicchio's &lt;i&gt;Portrait of a Boy&lt;/i&gt;, within the context of a modern-day slot machine. An image of the boy appears at center, with smaller-scale renderings repeated along the two sides, alongside numbers and letters. The piece reflects some of the ways in which Cornell's &lt;i&gt;oeuvre&lt;/i&gt; was a precursor of future innovative artistic developments. Its early use of a reproduction of an existing artwork heralded postmodern appropriation art, while its serial repetition of imagery and combination of "high" and "low" forms anticipate the work of Andy Warhol and Pop art.</desc>
      <materials>Wood, paper, wire, glass, box construction</materials>
      <collection>Estate of Joseph Cornell</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Untitled (Penny Arcade Portrait of Lauren Bacall)</title>
      <year>1945-46</year>
      <materials>Wood, paper, glass, box construction</materials>
      <desc>Evoking a pinball machine, &lt;i&gt;Penny Arcade Portrait of Lauren Bacall&lt;/i&gt; combines Cornell's fascination with Bacall, then at the peak of her stardom, with his childhood memories of New York's penny arcades. Directly inspired by Cornell's dossier on the noted film actress, this piece is essentially a shrine to the movie star, who here appears as an object to be worshipped but never touched, thanks to the protective glass covering. As in &lt;i&gt;Medici Boy&lt;/i&gt;, a central photograph of Bacall is flanked by smaller images of her, including scenes of city skyscrapers, perhaps included to refer to Bacall's time living in New York. This top row of images also suggests a filmstrip—further homage to the artist's love of cinema. Some writers have related the piece to the artist's similarly montage-like 1936 film &lt;i&gt;Rose Hobart&lt;/i&gt;, named after the film star with whom Cornell was also obsessed, made by snippets from the actress' film &lt;i&gt;East of Borneo&lt;/i&gt; in combination with shots from a documentary film of an eclipse.</desc>
      <collection>Collection Mr. and Mrs. E. A. Bergman, Chicago</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Cassiopeia 1</title>
      <year>1960</year>
      <materials>Wood, metal, paper, glass, box construction</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Cassiopeia 1&lt;/i&gt; is dedicated to another of Cornell's primary interests: outer space. Darker in mood than many of Cornell's other works, the box focuses on the eponymous constellation placed beside an image of Taurus on the right side and, to the upper left, Orion. A white moon-like ball rests on two thin metal bars that are positioned vertically within the walls of the box. The central cosmic image suggests considerable depth, and makes the viewer feel as if she is looking through a window to another world. Created when the health of the artist's mother and brother began to worsen, the piece may be seen in poignant personal terms as a meditation on what lies beyond this world, as well as perhaps an image of the sense of alienation the reclusive artist experienced throughout his life.</desc>
      <collection>Estate of Joseph Cornell</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Untitled (Oriental Painting of Bird with Cherry Blossoms)</title>
      <year>1964</year>
      <materials>Paper collage</materials>
      <desc>With his mother and brother's worsening health in the 1960s, Cornell's family responsibilities increased and his time for his artwork correspondingly lessened. He returned to collage, which was less physically demanding than the shadow boxes. Most of the present piece is devoted to a bird pursuing an insect; along the bottom are three smaller images, including an outdoor garden structure and an insect stamp. The collage reflects the artist's knowledge of art history, acquired through his trips to New York City art museums. In particular, it evokes the genre of Chinese bird-and-flower painting. The work also reflects the artist's love of nature, particularly birds. Cornell, who created a series of boxes on the aviary theme, reportedly used to leave his windows open and spread birdseed out on his kitchen table to try and lure them into his home.</desc>
      <collection>Smithsonian American Art Museum, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" />
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Utopia Parkway: The Life And Work Of Joseph Cornell</title>
          <link>0878466843</link>
          <info>By Deborah Solomon</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>A Joseph Cornell Album</title>
          <link>0306803720</link>
          <info>By Dore Ashton</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Joseph Cornell: Master of Dreams</title>
          <link>0810992523</link>
          <info>By Diane Waldman</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Dime-Store Alchemy: The Art of Joseph Cornell (New York Review Books Classics)</title>
          <link>1590174860</link>
          <info>By Charles Simic</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Joseph Cornell and Astronomy: A Case for the Stars</title>
          <link>0691134987</link>
          <info>By Kirsten Hoving</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Joseph Cornell: Stargazing in the Cinema (Yale Publications in the History of Art)</title>
          <link>0300078382</link>
          <info>By Jodi Hauptman</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="artwork" class="artwork">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Joseph Cornell: Navigating the Imagination</title>
          <link>0300111622</link>
          <info>By Lynda Roscoe Hartigan</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Joseph Cornell Box: Found Objects, Magical Worlds</title>
          <link>1933662425</link>
          <info>By Joan Sommers, Ascha Drake</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Joseph Cornell: Shadowplay...Eterniday</title>
          <link>0500976287</link>
          <info>By Lynda Roscoe Hartigan, Walter Hopps, Richard Vine, Robert Lehrman</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Joseph Cornell's Theater of the Mind: Selected Diaries, Letters, and Files</title>
          <link>0500282439</link>
          <info>By Joseph Cornell, Mary Ann Caws</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="works of fiction inspired by artist's work" class="artwork">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Convergence of Birds</title>
          <link>0241142156</link>
          <info>By Jonathan Safran Foer</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>The Grand Hotels (of Joseph Cornell) (Burning Deck Fiction)</title>
          <link>1886224528</link>
          <info>By Robert Coover</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Celestial Navigation</title>
          <link>0449911802</link>
          <info>By Anne Tyler</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>The Joseph Cornell Box</title>
          <link>http://www.josephcornellbox.com/</link>
          <info></info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Joseph Cornell: Navigating the Imagination</title>
          <link>http://www.pem.org/sites/cornell/</link>
          <info>By Anne Tyler</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>Pandora's Box: Joseph Cornell Unlocks the Museum of Contemporary Art Collection</title>
          <link>http://www.artdaily.org/index.asp?int_sec=11&amp;int_new=48419</link>
          <info>
						ArtDaily.org
						&lt;br/&gt;
						June 20, 2011
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Joseph Cornell's Cabinets of Wonder at SFMOMA</title>
          <link>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2007/10/05/DDA2SKB6J.DTL</link>
          <info>
						By Kenneth Baker
						&lt;br/&gt;
						San Francisco Chronicle
						&lt;br/&gt;
						October 6, 2007
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Poetic Theaters, Romantic Fevers</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/13/arts/design/13corn.html?ref=josephcornell</link>
          <info>
						By Holland Cotter
						&lt;br/&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br/&gt;
						July 13, 2007			
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Art Review; An Artist Who Assembled A Life in Dozens of Boxes</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/13/arts/design/13corn.html?ref=josephcornell</link>
          <info>
						By Ben Genocchio
						&lt;br/&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br/&gt;
						July 2, 2006
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Art in Review; Joseph Cornell</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/22/arts/art-in-review-joseph-cornell.html</link>
          <info>
						By Ken Johnson
						&lt;br/&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br/&gt;
						November 22, 2002
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Joseph Cornell/Marcel Duchamp...in resonance</title>
          <link>http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0268/is_10_37/ai_55015175/</link>
          <info>
						By Bruce Hainley
						&lt;br/&gt;
						ArtForum
						&lt;br/&gt;
						Summer 1999
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Stay-at-Home Life as Muse</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/1997/03/20/garden/the-stay-at-home-life-as-muse.html</link>
          <info>
						By Deborah Solomon
						&lt;br/&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br/&gt;
						March 20, 1997
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="radio broadcast" class="audioclips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Piecing Together Joseph Cornell</title>
          <link>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=1523240</link>
          <info>
						NPR; All Things Considered
						&lt;br/&gt;
						November 26, 2003
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>"Rose Hobart" (1936)</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XnbbqiD7C7A</link>
          <info>Part 1 (Part 2 available on YouTube)</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Gnir Rednow (1955)</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bhk8jrt4dfU</link>
          <info>Short film by Joseph Cornell &amp; Stan Brakhage</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop">
        <entry>
          <title>Cornell is mentioned in the novel The Time Traveler's Wife (2010)</title>
          <link>http://www.amazon.com/Time-Travelers-Wife-Audrey-Niffenegger/dp/0547119798/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1329162978&amp;sr=8-2</link>
          <info>By Audrey Niffenegger</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The British band The Clientele has a song titled "Joseph Cornell" on the album "Suburban Light" (2000)</title>
          <link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suburban_Light</link>
          <info></info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Musician Mary Chapin Carpenter's song "Ideas Are Like Stars" on the album "A Place in the World" (1996) is about Cornell</title>
          <link>http://www.songlyrics.com/mary-chapin-carpenter/ideas-are-like-stars-lyrics/</link>
          <info></info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Off-broadway play Hotel Cassiopeia (2006), by Charles L. Mee, is based on the life and work of Cornell</title>
          <link>http://theater.nytimes.com/2007/10/11/theater/reviews/11hotel.html</link>
          <info></info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item></a_item>
      <a_image></a_image>
      <a_name></a_name>
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>