<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>dix_otto</id>
    <name>Otto Dix</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1906 - 1969</years>
    <description>Otto Dix painted nudes, prostitutes, and often savagely satirical portraits of celebrities from Germany's intellectual circles in dark and allegorical works.</description>
    <use_big_images>true</use_big_images>
    <highlight>4</highlight>
    <occupation>Painter and Printmaker</occupation>
    <nationality>German</nationality>
    <birthDate>December 2, 1891</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Untermhaus, Germany</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>July 25, 1969</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>Singen, Germany</deathPlace>
    <pub_time>1/22/2012</pub_time>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>new_objectivity</include>
    <include>magic_realism</include>
    <include>photomontage</include>
    <include>degenerate_art</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>new_objectivity</movement>
    <movement>interwar_classicism</movement>
    <movement>magic_realism</movement>
    <movement>capitalist_realism</movement>
    <movement>degenerate_art</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>grosz_george</artist>
    <artist>schad_christian</artist>
    <artist>kollwitz_kathe</artist>
    <artist>goya_francisco</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"Art is exorcism. I paint dreams and visions too; the dreams and visions of my time. Painting is the effort to produce order; order in yourself. There is much chaos in me, much chaos in our time."</q>
    <q>"Artists shouldn't try to improve or convert. They are far too insignificant for that. They must only bear witness." </q>
    <q>"If one paints someone's portrait, one should not know him if possible. No knowledge. I do not want to know him at all. I want only to see what is there, the outside. The inner follows by itself. It is mirrored in the visible." </q>
    <q>"Trust your eyes."</q>
    <q>"I have to experience all the ghastly, bottomless depths for life for myself; it's for that reason that I went to war, and for that reason I volunteered."</q>
    <q>"I'm not that obsessed with making representations of ugliness. Everything I've seen is beautiful."</q>
    <q>"I will either be famous or infamous."</q>
    <q>"Everybody thinks they know what art should be. But very few of them have the sense that is necessary to experience painting, that is the sense of sight, that sees colors and forms as living reality in the picture."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="remer">Ashley Remer</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Otto Dix has been perhaps more influential than any other German painter in shaping the popular image of the Weimar Republic of the 1920s. His works are key parts of the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-new_objectivity"&gt;Neue Sachlichkeit&lt;/span&gt; ("New Objectivity") movement, which also attracted &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-grosz_george"&gt;George Grosz&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-beckmann_max"&gt;Max Beckmann&lt;/span&gt; in the mid 1920s. A veteran haunted by his experiences of WWI, his first great subjects were crippled soldiers, but during the height of his career he also painted nudes, prostitutes, and often savagely satirical portraits of celebrities from Germany's intellectual circles. His work became even darker and more allegorical in the early 1930s, and he became a target of the Nazis. In response, he gradually moved away from social themes, turning to landscape and Christian subjects, and, after serving in the army during WWII, enjoyed some considerable acclaim in his later years.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Otto Dix is one of modern painting's most savage satirists. After many artists had abandoned portraiture for abstraction in the 1910s, Dix returned to the genre and injected sharp caricatures into his depictions of some of the leading lights of German society. His other narrative subjects are remembered for their indictment of corrupt and immoral life in the modern city.</idea>
      <idea>Otto Dix was initially drawn to &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-expressionism"&gt;Expressionism&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-dada"&gt;Dada&lt;/span&gt;, but like many of his generation in Germany in the 1920s, he was inspired by trends in Italy and France to embrace a cold, linear style of drawing and more realistic imagery. Later, his approach became more fantastic and symbolic, and he began to depict nudes as witches or personifications of melancholy.</idea>
      <idea>Dix always balanced his inclination toward realism with an equal tendency toward the fantastic and the allegorical. For example, his images of prostitutes and injured war veterans serve as emblems of a society damaged both physically and morally.</idea>
      <idea>Although Dix's work is often noted for its sharp-eyed depiction of the human figure, his early fixation with crippled veterans and his resort to caricature suggest that he was uncomfortable with celebrating the human body - and the triumphant human spirit - in his paintings.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Wilhelm Heinrich Otto Dix was born to Franz and Pauline Dix on December 2, 1891. His father was a mold maker in an iron foundry, and Dix inherited his strength of character and steel-blue eyes. From his mother, a seamstress, he received a love of music and poetry. He first displayed his artistic talent - especially in drawing - during elementary school. At the age of ten, he modeled for painter Fritz Amann and, impressed by his experience in the studio, decided to become a painter himself. His school art teacher, Ernst Schunke, guided his study and helped him get financial assistance. The award required that he learn a craft while he continued to study art with Schunke, so he became an apprentice decorator for four years. </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="p">In 1909, Dix began his study at the Dresden Academy of Fine Arts. There was a huge creative output in the city, with a well-established and internationally renowned art and music scene that hosted large exhibitions and events. Dix did not struggle financially during art school; after the first semester he was exempt from paying fees and received a stipend. He also made extra money selling small portraits and genre paintings as well as coloring photographs. The Academy did not offer academic painting, but a more craft-oriented education. As a result, Dix was essentially a self-taught painter. But he did try sculpting under the guidance of Richard Guhr. A bust of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-nietzsche_friedrich"&gt;Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/span&gt; he created was purchased for the Dresden State Museum, but was later destroyed by the Nazis.</p>
          <p type="p">Through his intensive study of the Old Dutch, Italian, and German Masters, Dix taught himself how to paint with their methods - building up layers of paint to create depth and luminescence. However, he was also impressed by the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-expressionism"&gt;Expressionists&lt;/span&gt; and the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-post_impressionism"&gt;Post-Impressionists&lt;/span&gt; and in particular by a &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-van_gogh_vincent"&gt;Vincent van Gogh&lt;/span&gt; exhibition that he saw in 1913. Primarily painting portraits and landscapes, Dix experimented with pen and ink and made his first prints in 1913.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Otto Dix Biography" show="0">/images20/photo/dix_otto_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">When WWI began, Dix volunteered, somewhat eagerly, for service, and was drafted into a field artillery regiment; but by 1915 he was a machine gunner at the frontlines in France, and his experience of several horrific battles began to sour his enthusiasm. He was wounded several times, but managed to create sketches of many of the tragic scenes he witnessed. After the war, Dix resumed his art education with Max Feldbauer and Otto Gussman at the Dresden Academy of Art (1919-22). </p>
          <p type="p">In the aftermath of the war, Dresden was a shadow if its former self. No longer a seat of government, it suffered a huge drop in income and severe rationing. However, the artistic scene adapted and came back full force. With the value of money and political ideas in constant flux, Dix was driven to experiment. He had already taken on some elements of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-futurism"&gt;Futurism&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-cubism"&gt;Cubism&lt;/span&gt; during the war years; now he began integrating Dadaist and Expressionist elements into his work. In 1919, he co-founded the Dresdner Sezession Gruppe and participated in two of their exhibitions at the Galerie Emil Richter. He created surreal portraits and woodcuts, even delving into &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-collage"&gt;collage&lt;/span&gt; and mixed media. </p>
          <p type="p">After 1920, Dix synthesized and transformed these styles into his own brand of realism. Over the next few years, he composed some of his most disturbing canvases of sexual violence, murder, and cruelty. His &lt;i&gt;Skat Players (Card-Playing War Cripples)&lt;/i&gt; (1920) is an example of this grotesque, yet poignant imagery. In 1921, he participated in exhibitions in Berlin and Dresden before moving to Düsseldorf in 1922. This relocation was an important shift as he studied with new teachers, Heinrich Nauen and Wilhelm Herbeholz, and became a part of both Johanna Ey's art salon circle and the German modernist Das Junge Rheinland group. </p>
          <p type="p">In 1923, Dix married Martha Koch and over the next decade had three children, all of whom were captured on canvas throughout their childhoods. </p>
          <p type="img" alt="Otto Dix Photo" show="0">/images20/photo/dix_otto_3.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Throughout the 1920s Dix was included in many of the most significant exhibitions of new art in Germany. Most importantly, he was included in &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-new_objectivity"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Neue Sachlichkeit&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, the exhibition at the Kunsthalle Mannheim in 1925 that gave its name to the movement that Dix would forever be associated with. Neue Sachlichkeit evolved out of Expressionism, but took on qualities of the classical, linear realism that was becoming prevalent in Italy and France.</p>
          <p type="p">It appeared more sober and realistic than previous styles, though in the hands of artists such as Dix and Grosz, it was no less critical. Some of the artists were called the Verists and could be aggressive and cynical, while others, less abrasive, were described as Magic Realists. Dix was a Verist and, with a critical spirit, he turned his portrait skills on the decadence and debauchery of Weimar society, with works like &lt;i&gt;Metropolis&lt;/i&gt; (1927-28). Other notable canvases from this period include his triptych &lt;i&gt;The War&lt;/i&gt; (1929-32). </p>
          <p type="p">In 1931, Dix was appointed a member of the Prussian Academy of Arts in Berlin. The same year he showed work in exhibitions all over Germany and at the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-museum_of_modern_art"&gt;Museum of Modern Art&lt;/span&gt; in New York. This renown was relatively short-lived, however, as the Nazis began to target him, regarding his art as immoral. As such, he was forbidden to exhibit in Germany, but he traveled to Switzerland several times during the mid 1930s and participated in several exhibitions there. </p>
          <p type="p">Forced to join the Nazi government's Reich Chamber of Fine Arts in 1934, Dix still managed to express himself. &lt;i&gt;Seven Deadly Sins&lt;/i&gt; (1933) parodies Adolf Hitler as the embodiment of Envy. He was sent to a rural outpost and portrayed the surrounding landscapes in his work. In 1939, Dix was arrested on charges of plotting to kill Hitler, but the charges were dropped. He was captured by the French at the end of the war and held prisoner until 1946. Not wasting time, he painted a triptych for the prison camp chapel. After returning to Germany, Dix picked up where the war had interrupted his career. He resumed showing works and began making lithographs and documenting his war experiences and its effects in his work. </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Years and Death">
          <p type="img" alt="Otto Dix Portrait" show="0">/images20/photo/dix_otto_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Much of Dix's later work focuses on post-war suffering, religious allegories, and Biblical scenes. Throughout the 1950s and '60s, he traveled a great deal and exhibited his work constantly. He was appointed to membership of many art academies in Florence, Berlin, and Dresden.</p>
          <p type="p">He continued making prints and participated in a short documentary film in 1965. In 1967, after traveling to Greece, he suffered a stroke, which paralyzed his left hand. He died in 1969. </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">Dix is most remembered for the portraits he produced during the years of the Weimar Republic, pictures that have contributed to the enduring popular image of that famously decadent time in German history. They have also powerfully influenced portrait painters throughout the 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century. Although the rise of abstraction in the 1940s and 1950s continued to erode the importance of figurative portraiture, the tradition of portrait painting has continued throughout the West, and many leading artists continue to speak of Otto Dix with reverence.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="beckmann_max">Self Portrait in Tuxedo (1927)</artwork>
    <artwork from="movement" page="expressionism">Hans Tietze and Erica Tietze-Conrat (1909)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="grosz_george">Germany: A Winter's Tale (c. 1917)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>bosch_hieronymus</entity>
        <entity>goya_francisco</entity>
        <entity>baldung_grien_hans</entity>
        <entity>kokoschka_oskar</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>einstein_carl</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>renaissance</entity>
        <entity>dada</entity>
        <entity>post_impressionism</entity>
        <entity>cubism</entity>
        <entity>realism</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>beckmann_max</entity>
        <entity>schlichter_rudolph</entity>
        <entity>grosz_george</entity>
        <entity>balthus</entity>
        <entity>dali_salvador</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>ey_johanna</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>new_objectivity</entity>
        <entity>expressionism</entity>
        <entity>neo_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>social_realism</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Skat Players (Card-Playing War Cripples)</title>
      <year>1920</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas with photomontage and collage</materials>
      <desc>Showing both his Dadaist and Cubist influences, Dix makes a clear social statement using his bold technique in this painting. The skat players are war veterans horribly disfigured and crippled by their service, yet they are still able to play cards. Skat was a card game favored by Krupps, the German manufacturers of weapons. Dix uses the repetition of the cards, the chair legs, and the stumped limbs of the men to build a composition that is disturbing in form as well as content.</desc>
      <collection>Staatliche Museen zu Berlin, Nationalgalerie</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Portrait of the Lawyer Dr. Fritz Glaser</title>
      <year>1921</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>This picture of the lawyer Dr. Fritz Glaser is typical of Dix's portraiture from the early 1920s, in which he depicted his friends from the professional classes - doctors, lawyers and other notables who were also interested in the arts. Dr. Glaser assembled an extensive collection of art including works by artists such as Wassily Kandinsky, Paul Klee, and Emil Nolde. Dix shows him in front of the snow-covered facade of a typically ornate Dresden building, which appears to have been shattered during the war. Typical of his inclination toward caricature, the artist emphasizes the prominent features in Glaser's face, in this case his Semitic nose. The picture is also typical of the contradictions in Dix's life and work - contradictions between the good relations he had with many of Dresden's bourgeoisie, and the icy, critical tone with which his art remembered them.</desc>
      <collection>Pompidou Centre, Paris</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Portrait of the Journalist Sylvia von Harden</title>
      <year>1926</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>As a character of her time just as the woman herself, this image of Sylvia von Harden became iconic of the era. This portrait is perhaps Dix's most recognized. It was even referenced in the 1972 film &lt;i&gt;Cabaret&lt;/i&gt;, set in Weimar-era Berlin. It is said that Dix painted this portrait after seeing von Harden in the street and exclaiming, "I must paint you, I simply must! You represent an entire epoch." She was amused. "So you want to paint my lackluster eyes, my ornate ears, my long nose, my thin lips. You want to paint my short legs, my big feet -- things that can only frighten people and delight no one?" Dix claimed that she was a perfect image for a society that was less concerned about a woman's outward appearance than her psychological state.</desc>
      <collection>Pompidou Centre, Paris</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>The War</title>
      <year>1929-32</year>
      <materials>Oil and tempera on wood</materials>
      <desc>Dix was extremely affected by his war experiences and returned to them often for inspiration. &lt;i&gt;The War&lt;/i&gt; shows men going into battle, it shows the aftermath of conflict, and it shows them returning from the field. Dix studied the Old Masters in both their subject matter and painting methods. This triptych is immediately reminiscent of grand history paintings as well as German Renaissance artist Matthias Gruenwald's Isenheim altarpiece (1506-15). Andrea Mantegna's &lt;i&gt;Dead Christ&lt;/i&gt; (1480) is evoked in the lower panel showing the dead soldiers. Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, Friedrich Nietzsche, and the Bible also influenced Dix, thus associations of sacrifice and apocalypse with war imagery are common in his works.</desc>
      <collection>Staatliche Kunstsammlungen, Dresden</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Seven Deadly Sins</title>
      <year>1933</year>
      <materials>Oil and egg tempera on wood</materials>
      <desc>In response to the Nazis' dismissing him from his teaching post at the Berlin Academy, Dix created this surreal satire on German politics. The figure of Sloth, depicted in the center, is a skeleton whose outstretched arms and scythe form a sort of swastika. Dix felt that this sloth or lack of concern and unwillingness to take early action by the German people had allowed Hitler's rise to power. The most poignant aspect of this picture is the representation of Envy, riding on the back of Avarice: he wears a Hitler mask. However, it wasn't until after the war that Dix painted in the telltale mustache.</desc>
      <collection>State Gallery, Stuttgart</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Self Portrait with Palette before Red Curtain</title>
      <year>1942</year>
      <materials>Mixed media on wood</materials>
      <desc>Dix created many self-portraits throughout his lifetime. His maturity as an artist and a man can be chronicled in these reflective and intense studies of his own image. In this scene, he is fully facing the viewer, while in other portraits he is in profile. He is engaged in the act of painting, presumably the portrait itself. The dark and ominous view of the Alps can be seen out the window in the distance.</desc>
      <collection>Private Collection</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" />
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Otto Dix</title>
          <link>379135020X</link>
          <info>By Olaf Peters</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Otto Dix: The Art of Life</title>
          <link>3775725814</link>
          <info>By Philipp Gutbrod</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by" />
      <subcategory name="paintings" class="artwork">
        <entry>
          <title>Otto Dix: Hommage a Martha (German Edition)</title>
          <link>3775716203</link>
          <info>By Karin Schick, Otto Dix</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Otto Dix: Zwischen Paradies und Untergang (German Edition)</title>
          <link>3777420212</link>
          <info>By Dieter Buchhart, Hartwig Knack</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Otto Dix</title>
          <link>http://www.otto-dix.de/start_html</link>
          <info>Official Site of the Artist</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Otto Dix House Museum</title>
          <link>http://www.kunstmuseum-stuttgart.de/index.php?site=Museum_Haus_Dix;The_House&amp;id=25</link>
          <info>Residence of the Artist is open as a museum</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Online Otto Dix Project</title>
          <link>http://www.ottodix.org/</link>
          <info>Informative Website on Dix with Many Images of His Work</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Otto Dix</title>
          <link>http://www.mess.net/galleria/dix/</link>
          <info>A Smaller Image Gallery of the Artist's Paintings</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Critical Dix</title>
          <link>http://www.artnet.com/magazineus/features/kuspit/otto-dix3-24-10.asp</link>
          <info>

						By Donald Kuspit 

						&lt;br&gt;

						ArtNet 

						&lt;br&gt;

						March 24, 2010 

					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Always Outrageous, Frequently Disturbing</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/12/arts/design/12dix.html</link>
          <info>

						By Roberta Smith 

						&lt;br&gt;

						The New York Times 

						&lt;br&gt;

						March 11, 2010 

					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Dix and Beckmann: Two Painters Convey The Horror of War</title>
          <link>http://observer.com/2005/08/29/dix-and-beckmann-two-painters-convey-the-horror-of-war/</link>
          <info>

						By Hilton Kramer 

						&lt;br&gt;

						The New York Observer 

						&lt;br&gt;

						August 28, 2005

					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="interviews" class="interviews" />
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips">
        <entry>
          <title>Otto Dix, Nocturnal Apparition, 1923</title>
          <link>http://www.moma.org/explore/multimedia/audios/261/3032</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry>
          <title>'The Skat Players' by Otto Dix</title>
          <link>http://vimeo.com/77827274</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>The German Expressionism Exhibit at MoMA: The War by Otto Dix</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fsyqEX-DlaA</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips" />
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop">
        <entry>
          <title>Degenerate Art</title>
          <link>http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0236147/</link>
          <info>1993</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Portrait of an Artist: Otto Dix - The Painter is the Eyes of the World</title>
          <link>http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/36727/Portrait-of-an-Artist-Otto-Dix-The-Painter-is-the-Eyes-of-the-World/overview</link>
          <info>1989</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item />
      <a_image />
      <a_name />
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>