<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>dubuffet_jean</id>
    <name>Jean Dubuffet</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1942 - 1985</years>
    <description>Dubuffet developed a radically new, graphic style and he remains famous for the thick textured and gritty surfaces of his post-war pictures.</description>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <highlight>3</highlight>
    <occupation>Painter, Printmaker, and Sculptor</occupation>
    <nationality>French</nationality>
    <birthDate>July 31, 1901</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Le Havre, France</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>May 12, 1985</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>Paris, France</deathPlace>
    <img_version>?1</img_version>
    <image_desc>true</image_desc>
    <pub_time>8/1/2012</pub_time>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>art_brut_and_outsider_art</include>
    <include>art_informel</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>art_brut_and_outsider_art</movement>
    <movement>art_informel</movement>
    <movement>abstract_expressionism</movement>
    <movement>primitivism</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>breton_andre</artist>
    <artist>masson_andre</artist>
    <artist>rousseau_henri</artist>
    <artist>jorn_asger</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"Personally, I believe very much in values of savagery; I mean: instinct, passion, mood, violence, madness."</q>
    <q>"Look at what lies at your feet! .. A crack in the ground, sparkling gravel, a tuft of grass, some crushed debris, offer equally worthy subjects for your applause and admiration."</q>
    <q>"For me, insanity is super sanity. The normal is psychotic. Normal means lack of imagination, lack of creativity."</q>
    <q>"Unless one says goodbye to what one loves, and unless one travels to completely new territories, one can expect merely a long wearing away of oneself and an eventual extinction."</q>
    <q>"In the name of what - except perhaps the coefficient of rarity - does man adorn himself with necklaces of shells and not spider's webs, with fox fur and not fox innards? In the name of what I don't know. Don't dirt, trash and filth, which are man's companions during his whole lifetime, deserve to be dearer to him and isn't it serving him well to remind him of their beauty?"</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="borteh">Larissa Borteh</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Jean Dubuffet disliked authority from a very early age. He left home at 17, failed to complete his art education, and wavered for many years between painting and working in his father's wine business. He would later be a successful propagandist, gaining notoriety for his attacks on conformism and mainstream culture, which he described as "asphyxiating." He was attracted to the art of children and the mentally ill, and did much to promote their work, collecting it and promulgating the notion of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-art_brut_and_outsider_art"&gt;Art Brut&lt;/span&gt;. His early work was influenced by that of outsiders, but it was also shaped by the interests in materiality that preoccupied many post-war French artists associated with the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-art_informel"&gt;Art Informel&lt;/span&gt; movement. In the early 1960s, he developed a radically new, graphic style, which he called "&lt;i&gt;Hourloupe&lt;/i&gt;," and would deploy it on many important public commissions, but he remains best known for the thick textured and gritty surfaces of his pictures from the 1940s and '50s.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Dubuffet was launched to success with a series of exhibitions that opposed the prevailing mood of post-war Paris and consequently sparked enormous scandal. While the public looked for a redemptive art and a restoration of old values, Dubuffet confronted them with childlike images that satirized the conventional genres of high art. And while the public looked for beauty, he gave them pictures with coarse textures and drab colors, which critics likened to dirt and excrement.</idea>
      <idea>The emphasis on texture and materiality in Dubuffet's paintings might be read as an insistence on the real. In the aftermath of the war, it represented an appeal to acknowledge humanity's failings and begin again from the ground - literally the soil - up.</idea>
      <idea>Dubuffet's &lt;i&gt;Hourloupe&lt;/i&gt; style developed from a chance doodle while he was on the telephone. The basis of it was a tangle of clean black lines that forms cells, which are sometimes filled with unmixed color. He believed the style evoked the manner in which objects appear in the mind. This contrast between physical and mental representation later encouraged him to use the approach to create sculpture.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Jean Dubuffet was born on July 31, 1901, in Le Havre, France, into a middle-class family that distributed wine. Although he was well-educated, he came to reject his studies, preferring to educate himself by reading the work of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-prinzhorn_hans"&gt;Dr. Hans Prinzhorn&lt;/span&gt;, who drew comparisons between the art of asylum inmates and the artwork of children. Based on these observations, Prinzhorn stated that it was savagery, or base animal instinct, that lead to universal harmony, arguing that it was the primal instinct, not intellectual theory or analysis, that connected all living things. This concept had a strong influence on Dubuffet's later career.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="p">In 1918, Dubuffet moved to Paris where he studied painting at the Académie Julian. Dubuffet thought of himself as savage in comparison to the intellectuals at the art academy. Rebelling against the institution, Dubuffet took a stance that was anti-art and anti-culture, for example, refusing to be constrained by categories like "Surrealist" and "Futurist." After attending classes for six months, he withdrew from the academy, deeming his studies useless. In 1924, Dubuffet took over his father's wine business and continued to study on his own. He found solace with the common, everyday people of the country and believed there was meaning in living a simple life with a focus on music and poetry. It was not until 1942 that Dubuffet decided to return to painting where he could explore this fondness for quotidian life and the interiority of human emotion.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Jean Dubuffet working in his studio (1960). Photo by Paolo Monti" show="1">/images20/photo/dubuffet_jean_1a.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Frustrated by intellectual approaches to art, Dubuffet continued to admire the artwork of asylum inmates and children. In attempting to recreate what he saw as their uninhibited style, he chose to paint in seclusion where he could experiment with new methods and concepts, unfettered by theory or popular trends.
		  
		  Heavily influenced by the paintings of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-fautrier_jean"&gt;Jean Fautrier&lt;/span&gt;, Dubuffet began to take a similar approach to the texture of his paint, combining sand, gravel, tar, and straw to his paintings to create a thick emulsion. The mixtures created a highly textured surface, providing the ideal ground for his raw, primal figures. As Dubuffet became increasingly obsessed with texture, he began to drastically limit his palette, focusing on dark, monochromatic surfaces and figures.</p>
          <p type="p">Dubuffet's subject matter featured the surrounding countryside, including childlike depictions of cows and milkmaids, but shifted to focus on urban landscapes and city dwellers. Although he created many portraits based on urban individuals, he chose to depersonalize them, exaggerating features and proportions to create grotesque caricatures, challenging cultural standards of beauty, traditional academic notions of realism, and the more contemporary obsession with non-objective art. What is most striking about his work from this period is his deliberate evocation of ugliness. Dubuffet did not believe in the separation of the beautiful and the ugly, and, as such, declared that ugliness did not exist. He expressed this in many of his paintings, including the series of portraits &lt;i&gt;Hautes Pates&lt;/i&gt; (c. 1945), which was exhibited in 1946 at the Galerie Rene Drouin.</p>
          <p type="p">In 1948, Jean Dubuffet joined with Surrealists &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-breton_andre"&gt;André Breton&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-ratton_charles"&gt;Charles Ratton&lt;/span&gt; to establish Art Brut, or outsider art, a style of image-making modeled after the art collection of Dr. Prinzhorn. The primitive, childlike approach to art was an alternative to the conventional art world aesthetic, and the return to figuration was a deliberate about-face from the abstract, non-objective canvases of his contemporaries.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Period">
          <p type="p">Dubuffet continued to challenge aesthetic boundaries through experiments with materials and through style. In his later career, he created some of his most important work, gravitating toward the tools used by the "common man," such as ballpoint and felt tip pens. Dubuffet's style began to accommodate Surrealist notions of automatic drawing, seeking to tap directly into his subconscious. He would begin with simple scribbles on paper and finalize the work with flashes of red, blue, white, and black. This approach allowed Dubuffet to break away from objectivity and, he believed, to arrive at art in the purest form. In 1962, Dubuffet titled these paintings the &lt;i&gt;Hourloupe&lt;/i&gt; series.</p>
          <p type="p">From 1966 to his death, Jean Dubuffet would use the &lt;i&gt;Hourloupe&lt;/i&gt; series as inspiration for several large-scale sculptures. These sculptures are comprised of papier-mache and polystyrene, many of which are large enough to walk through.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="img" alt="The outdoor sculpture &lt;i&gt;Group of Four Trees&lt;/i&gt; installed in The Chase Manhattan Bank Plaza, New York City." show="1">/images20/photo/dubuffet_jean_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Until his death in 1985, Dubuffet was exhibited in retrospectives and exhibitions around the world. Rebelling against art, culture, and intellectualism, Dubuffet was instrumental in establishing the style of Art Brut, an aesthetic of his own that was devoid of the traditional standards of its time, both in style and subject matter. His primitive approach to art making, with its simple, childlike figures and bold, visually dramatic palette, has universal appeal and is instrumental in modern psychology and studies of mental development.</p>
          <p type="p">The artwork by Jean Dubuffet continues to be exhibited and collected by The Dubuffet Foundation, and is shown by the Pace Gallery in New York City.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="munch_edvard">The Scream (1893)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="picasso_pablo">Bowl of Fruit, Violin and Bottle (1914)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="soutine_chaim">Carcass of Beef (1925)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>fautrier_jean</entity>
        <entity>munch_edvard</entity>
        <entity>picasso_pablo</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>prinzhorn_hans</entity>
        <entity>jacob_max</entity>
        <entity>paulhan_jean</entity>
        <entity>breton_andre</entity>
        <entity>masson_andre</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>cubism</entity>
        <entity>abstract_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>expressionism</entity>
        <entity>surrealism</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>basquiat_jean_michel</entity>
        <entity>schnabel_julian</entity>
        <entity>baselitz_georg</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>masson_andre</entity>
        <entity>breton_andre</entity>
        <entity>artaud_antonin</entity>
        <entity>paulhan_jean</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>art_brut_and_outsider_art</entity>
        <entity>neo_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>pop_art</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Apartment Houses, Paris</title>
      <year>1946</year>
      <materials>Oil with sand and charcoal on canvas</materials>
      <desc>The painting &lt;i&gt;Apartment Houses, Paris&lt;/i&gt; focuses on urban life. The buildings are tilted, playfully defying architectural integrity. The flattening of the space between the sky, buildings, and civilians seems spontaneous and unprocessed - childlike. Here Dubuffet satirizes conventional, sentimental images of Paris, suggesting instead that the jollity of the city's inhabitants is forced and false.</desc>
      <collection>Private Collection</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Grand Maitre of the Outsider</title>
      <year>1947</year>
      <materials>Oil and emulsion on canvas</materials>
      <desc>This picture is typical of the &lt;i&gt;Hautes Pates&lt;/i&gt; series that Dubuffet exhibited to huge controversy in 1946. A thick, monochromatic surface serves as the ground for the crudely depicted figure, which is a parody of portraiture. Although Dubuffet undoubtedly intended the series to offend and his graphic style and thick, coarse impasto certainly did offend conventional tastes, it is worth noting that the color palette is not as jarring as it might be. Dubuffet was at least cautiously mindful of the need for success.</desc>
      <collection>Private Collection</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>The Cow With The Subtle Nose</title>
      <year>1954</year>
      <materials>Oil and enamel on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Dubuffet's heady experience in the country and rejection of art education is evident in this painting. The heavily textured surface depicts a cow, rendered in the childlike innocence of patients held in psychological facilities. The uninhibited, savage approach to the canvas exemplifies the concepts of what Dubuffet termed Art Brut - the image seems entirely unschooled in the traditions of landscape. The image is thus at odds with the notions of "high art," and approaches art making from the direction of artistic purity uninfluenced by cultural advancement. Going a step further, Dubuffet suggests how "cultural" and "savage" approaches to art together work to reaffirm civilization as a whole.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum Of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Soul of the Underground</title>
      <year>1959</year>
      <materials>Oil and aluminum foil on composition board</materials>
      <desc>
				&lt;i&gt;Soul of the Underground&lt;/i&gt; exemplifies Dubuffet's fascination with texture and his departure from representational painting. Inspired by the surface quality of Jean Fautrier's paintings, Dubuffet's use of aluminum foil and oil paint creates a coarse, uneven surface resembling mineral deposits. Here Dubuffet completely abandons pictorial representation in order to evoke sheer matter and sheer unprocessed material. It is part of a series of &lt;i&gt;Texturologies&lt;/i&gt; that he worked on throughout the 1950s as he became more interested in evoking different sorts of texture. 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				After the horrible destruction of World War II, mud and dirt is what remained in plentitude. Rather than proclaiming that civilization had ceased, Dubuffet wanted to use the rubble to build anew and to purify for the future. In addition, the dirt is thought of as a material that has a natural structure that can be discovered, explored, and put to new uses.
			</desc>
      <collection>The Museum Of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>L'Hourloupe</title>
      <year>1966</year>
      <materials>Ink on paper</materials>
      <desc>Dubuffet's &lt;i&gt;L'Hourloupe&lt;/i&gt; series began in 1962 and would preoccupy the artist for many decades. The inspiration came from a doodle he created while on the telephone, in which the fluid movement of line combines with limited fields of color to create movement. He believed the style evoked the manner in which objects appear in the mind. This contrast between physical and mental representation later encouraged him to use the approach to create sculpture.</desc>
      <collection>Galerie Jeanne Bucher, Paris</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Monument with Standing Beast</title>
      <year>1984</year>
      <materials>Fiberglass</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Monument with Standing Beast&lt;/i&gt; is another sculpture based on Dubuffet's &lt;i&gt;Hourloupe&lt;/i&gt; series. The piece is one of his three monumental sculptures based in the United States. The sculpture is an abstract representation of a tree, a standing animal, and an architectural structure. The work evokes graffiti and cartoons, though it also plays on the contrast between mental images and real objects. The visitor is invited to wander and contemplate within the black and white walls of the sculpture.</desc>
      <collection>James R. Thompson Center, Chicago, IL</collection>
      <use_big_image>true</use_big_image>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" />
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry>
          <title>Jean Dubuffet: Works, Writings, Interviews</title>
          <link>8434309491</link>
          <info>By Valerie Da Costa, Fabrice Hergott, Jean Dubuffet</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>The Work of Jean Dubuffet, with texts by the artist</title>
          <link>B000WD3X2C</link>
          <info>By Peter Selz, Jean Dubuffet</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Jean Dubuffet: Towards an Alternative Reality</title>
          <link>0896597822</link>
          <info>By Jean Dubuffet, Mildred Glimcher</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Dubuffet Prints from the Museum of Modern Art</title>
          <link>0929865022</link>
          <info>By the Museum of Modern Art, New York</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Asphyxiating Culture and Other Writings</title>
          <link>0941423093</link>
          <info>By Jean Dubuffet, Carol Volk</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Jean Dubuffet: Writings on Sculpture</title>
          <link>3941263188</link>
          <info>By Jean Dubuffet</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="paintings" class="artwork">
        <entry>
          <title>Jean Dubuffet: A Retrospective</title>
          <link>B0006C9OF4</link>
          <info>By Jean Dubuffet, Margit Rowell, Thomas M. Messer</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Dubuffet Foundation</title>
          <link>http://www.dubuffetfondation.com/home.php?lang=en</link>
          <info>Features an In-Depth Biography, Images of Works</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>MoMA: Jean Dubuffet</title>
          <link>http://www.moma.org/collection/artist.php?artist_id=1633</link>
          <info>Includes Images and Analyses of Dubuffet's Works from the MoMA Collection</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>Jean Dubuffet</title>
          <link>https://frieze.com/article/jean-dubuffet</link>
          <info>
						By Sophie Berrebi
						&lt;br&gt;
						Frieze Magazine
						&lt;br&gt;
						January - February 2002
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>The French Establishment Salutes a Dedicated Rebel</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/23/arts/arts-abroad-the-french-establishment-salutes-a-dedicated-rebel.html?src=pm&amp;gwh=DA940D50C02E9F659A21F2819545F83B</link>
          <info>
						By Alan Riding
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br&gt;
						October 23, 2001
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Jean Dubuffet, Giving Pleasure Despite Himself</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/1993/07/04/arts/art-view-jean-dubuffet-giving-pleasure-despite-himself.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm</link>
          <info>
						By Michael Kimmelman
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br&gt;
						July 4, 1993
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="interviews" class="interviews" />
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips">
        <entry>
          <title>UbuWeb Sound - Jean Dubuffet</title>
          <link>http://www.ubu.com/sound/dubuffet.html</link>
          <info>Provides Audio Files of Coucou Bazar Turin, Musique Brut, and Musical Experiments by Dubuffet</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>The Artists Studio Jean Dubuffet</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eAloe0EMBqw</link>
          <info>Trailer. Directed by Michael Blackwood</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>TateShots: Mark Haddon on Jean Dubuffet</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cp21LTdvd0k</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips" />
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop" />
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item />
      <a_image />
      <a_name />
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>