<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>giacometti_alberto</id>
    <name>Alberto Giacometti</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1920 - 1966</years>
    <description>Giacometti created art that summed up Existentialism's interests in alienation and anxiety, making the suffering human figure a symbol of post-war trauma.</description>
    <barnebys_item>156</barnebys_item>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <highlight>4</highlight>
    <occupation>Sculptor and Painter</occupation>
    <nationality>Swiss</nationality>
    <birthDate>October 10, 1901</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Stampa, Graubunden, Switzerland</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>January 11, 1966</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>Chur, Graubunden, Switzerland</deathPlace>
    <img_version>?1</img_version>
    <art_type>Sculptures+</art_type>
    <mptv_banner>true</mptv_banner>
    <pub_time>6/1/2011</pub_time>
    <big_bio_box_img>Alberto Giacometti in Paris (April 22, 1952)</big_bio_box_img>
    <bio_highlight>Calling it “a complete transformation of reality,” Giacometti was struck by a vision after leaving a cinema in Paris. Trembling with fear, he entered a familiar café and was met by a waiter, “his eyes fixed in an absolute immobility.” Subsequently, he began sculpting the tall emaciated figures with prominent heads that evoked the existential angst of the post World War II era.</bio_highlight>
    <custom_logo>true</custom_logo>
    <hero>true</hero>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>surrealism</include>
    <include>existentialism</include>
    <include>surrealist_sculpture</include>
    <include>modern_sculptors</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>surrealism</movement>
    <movement>existentialism</movement>
    <movement>surrealist_sculpture</movement>
    <movement>modern_sculptors</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>brancusi_constantin</artist>
    <artist>ernst_max</artist>
    <artist>calder_alexander</artist>
    <artist>oppenheim_meret</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"All the art of the past rises up before me, the art of all ages and all civilizations, everything becomes simultaneous, as if space had replaced time. Memories of works of art blend with affective memories, with my work, with my whole life."</q>
    <q>"Let me know how to make only one and I will be able to make a thousand."</q>
    <q>"Just the same, if I begin my statue, as they do, with the tip of the nose, then an infinity of time will not be too much before I get to the nostrils."</q>
    <q>"When I make my drawings ... the path traced by my pencil on the sheet of paper is, to some extend, analogous to the gesture of a man groping his way in the darkness."</q>
    <q>"All the art of the past rises up before me, the art of all ages and all civilizations, everything becomes simultaneous, as if space had replaced time. Memories of works of art blend with affective memories, with my work, with my whole life."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="wolf">Justin Wolf</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Alberto Giacometti's remarkable career traces the shifting enthusiasms of European art before and after the Second World War. As a &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealist&lt;/span&gt; in the 1930s, he devised innovative sculptural forms, sometimes reminiscent of toys and games. And as an &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-existentialism"&gt;Existentialist&lt;/span&gt; after the war, he led the way in creating a style that summed up the philosophy's interests in perception, alienation and anxiety. Although his output extends into painting and drawing, the Swiss-born and Paris-based artist is most famous for his sculpture. And he is perhaps best remembered for his figurative work, which helped make the motif of the suffering human figure a popular symbol of post-war trauma.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Giacometti's work of the 1930s represents probably the most important contribution to Surrealist sculpture. In an effort to explore themes derived from &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-freud_sigmund"&gt;Freudian&lt;/span&gt; psychoanalysis, like sexuality, obsession and trauma, he developed a variety of different sculptural objects. Some were influenced by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-primitivism"&gt;primitive art&lt;/span&gt;, but perhaps most striking were those that resemble games, toys, and architectural models. They almost encourage the viewer to physically interact with them, an idea which was very radical at the time.</idea>
      <idea>In the late 1930s, Giacometti abandoned &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_art"&gt;abstraction&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealism&lt;/span&gt;, becoming more interested in how to represent the human figure in a convincing illusion of real space. He wanted to depict figures in such a way as to capture a palpable sense of spatial distance, so that we, as viewers, might share in the artist's own sense of distance from his model, or from the encounter that inspired the work. The solution he arrived at involved whittling the figures down to the slenderest proportions.</idea>
      <idea>Giacometti's post-war achievement - finding a language through which to represent the figure in real space - impressed the many writers of the period who were interested in Phenomenology and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-existentialism"&gt;Existentialism&lt;/span&gt;. Both of these philosophies contained ideas about self-consciousness and how we relate to other human beings, and Giacometti's art was thought to powerfully capture the tone of melancholy, alienation and loneliness that these ideas suggested.</idea>
      <idea>Although the 1950s art world of both Europe and the United States was dominated by abstract painting, Giacometti's figurative sculpture came to be a hugely influential model of how the human figure might return to art. His figures represented human beings alone in the world, turned in on themselves and failing to communicate with their fellows, despite their overwhelming desire to reach out.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Alberto Giacometti was born in 1901 in the mountain hamlet of Borgonovo, in eastern Switzerland. He was the first of four children born to Giovanni Giacometti, a &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-post_impressionism"&gt;Post-Impressionist&lt;/span&gt; painter, and Annetta Giacometti-Stampa, whose family was among the area's prominent land owners. In addition to his father, several members of Giacometti's extended family were artists, including Augusto Giacometti (second cousin to both Giovanni and Annetta), who was a &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-symbolism"&gt;Symbolist&lt;/span&gt; painter, and Cuno Amiet, Alberto's godfather and a close family friend, who was a &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-fauvism"&gt;Fauvist&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
          <p type="p">When Giacometti was no older than ten, he began to send pencil and crayon drawings to his godfather Amiet, most of which he saved and survive today. And in the years that followed, he began to experiment with oils and still lifes, often using his siblings as models. He produced his first painting at age twelve.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
		  <p type="img" alt="A 1935 bronze sculpture by Giacometti’s sculpture instructor, Maurice Sarkissoff." show="1">/images20/photo/photo_giacometti_alberto_1.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">In 1915, Giacometti enrolled at the Evangelical School in the town of Schiers, where he continued to work in a small private studio. Later he enrolled at the École des Arts Industriels in Geneva, and studied painting, drawing and sculpture under the tutelage of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pointillism"&gt;Pointillist&lt;/span&gt; painter David Estoppey and sculptor Maurice Sarkissoff.</p>
          <p type="p">In May 1920, Giacometti traveled to Italy with his father, where he viewed paintings by Jacopo Tintoretto at the Venice Biennale, Giotto's frescoes in Padua, and ancient Egyptian art at the Archeological Museum in Florence. Soon after, he moved to Paris, where he enrolled in several art classes, and later he began to be attracted to &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-cubism"&gt;Cubism&lt;/span&gt; and primitive art. In 1926 he exhibited his very first major bronze sculpture work, the idol-like &lt;i&gt;Spoon Woman&lt;/i&gt; (1926-27), at the Salon des Tuileries.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Alberto Giacometti Biography" show="0">/images20/photo/giacometti_alberto_3.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">By the 1930s, Giacometti had been warmly welcomed into Surrealist circles, and he became close to figures such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-ray_man"&gt;Man Ray&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-miro_joan"&gt;Joan Miró&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-masson_andre"&gt;André Masson&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-ernst_max"&gt;Max Ernst&lt;/span&gt;, as well as the movement's founders &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-breton_andre"&gt;André Breton&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-aragon_louis"&gt;Louis Aragon&lt;/span&gt;. But he also published work in &lt;i&gt;Documents&lt;/i&gt;, the periodical produced by writer Georges Bataille, who was then putting forward a version of Surrealism in opposition to Breton's. Critics now believe that Bataille's ideas may have been important in inspiring several of Giacometti's Surrealist works, such as &lt;i&gt;Suspended Ball&lt;/i&gt; (1930-1).</p>
          <p type="p">In June 1940 Giacometti and his brother Diego fled Paris by bicycle, narrowly missing an encounter with the invading German Wehrmacht (the next day they witnessed the city's bombardment from afar). Giacometti remained in France during this time, and forged friendships with Jean-Paul Sartre and Simone de Beauvoir, thinkers who would later influence his figurative work.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Giacometti in his Montparnasse (Paris) studio, photographed by his wife Annette." show="1">/images20/photo/photo_giacometti_alberto_2.jpg</p>
		  <p type="p">In 1946, following the liberation of Paris, and Giacometti's own three-year hiatus in Geneva, he returned to the French capital. That same year his former lover, Annette Arm, joined him, and the two were married in 1949. Arm modeled for him on several occasions, including for the oil painting &lt;i&gt;Annette with Chariot&lt;/i&gt; (1950). It was while living in Paris during these years that Giacometti arrived at his mature style of elongated figures, reportedly after spending time sketching passersby in the city streets.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Alberto Giacometti Photo" show="0">/images20/photo/giacometti_alberto_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">As Giacometti's style continued to mature into the 1950s and 60s, his bronze figures grew larger and more complex, ranging from his &lt;i&gt;Woman of Venice II&lt;/i&gt; (1956) at nearly four feet tall, to &lt;i&gt;Tall Woman II&lt;/i&gt; (1960), towering at close to nine feet. He also devoted more time to portraiture, in both painting and sculpture. His regular models included Diego and Annette, as well as Isaku Yanaihara, a Japanese philosophy professor and writer whom he befriended in 1955.</p>
          <p type="p">By the 1960s, Giacometti was internationally famous, but his health declined. He was plagued by heart and circulatory problems. Nevertheless he continued to work, and in his final weeks he was working on a bust and painting of Elie Lotar, a French photographer and close friend. On the evening of January 11, 1966, he died of complications of pericarditis.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
		  <p type="img" alt="Works by Giacometti at the Kunsthaus Zürich in 2020." show="1">/images20/photo/photo_giacometti_alberto_3.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Both of the important phases of Giacometti's career yielded innovations that influenced a wide range of artists. His Surrealist sculpture of the 1930s, for instance, influenced &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-moore_henry"&gt;Henry Moore&lt;/span&gt;, partly inspiring the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealism&lt;/span&gt; that would be such an important component of Moore's practice throughout his life. It is certainly hard to imagine Moore's own innovative experiments in the 1930s without Giacometti's example. And Giacometti's figurative work was vital in re-establishing the figure as a viable motif in the post-war period, at a time when abstract art dominated. His spindly bronze figures, which appear punctured and fragile, compressed in space, are in many respects visual manifestations of Existentialist thought, emblems of the condition of modern humanity ravaged by doubt.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="brancusi_constantin">Sleeping Muse I (1909-10)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="picasso_pablo">Guernica (1937)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="ernst_max">The King Playing with the Queen (1944)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>derain_andre</entity>
        <entity>brancusi_constantin</entity>
        <entity>arp_hans</entity>
        <entity>miro_joan</entity>
        <entity>picasso_pablo</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>masson_andre</entity>
        <entity>aragon_louis</entity>
        <entity>balthus</entity>
        <entity>ernst_max</entity>
        <entity>bataille_georges</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>post_impressionism</entity>
        <entity>cubism</entity>
        <entity>surrealism</entity>
        <entity>constructivism</entity>
        <entity>divisionism</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>noguchi_isamu</entity>
        <entity>dali_salvador</entity>
        <entity>moore_henry</entity>
        <entity>bell_leland</entity>
        <entity>bacon_francis</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>sartre_jean_paul</entity>
        <entity>genet_jean</entity>
        <entity>ponge_francis</entity>
        <entity>paolozzi_eduardo</entity>
        <entity>calder_alexander</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>existentialism</entity>
        <entity>art_nouveau</entity>
        <entity>realism</entity>
        <entity>neo_expressionism</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Gazing Head</title>
      <year>1928</year>
      <materials>Plaster</materials>
      <desc>In his early years, Giacometti often experienced difficulty in sculpting from life. In this despair, he began to work from memory. The early plaster bust &lt;i&gt;Gazing Head&lt;/i&gt;, arguably the artist's first truly original work, illustrates the culmination of this effort. The flatness of the head and face - Giacometti's economical placement of smooth divots for definition - result in a bust that is at once abstract and figurative. And yet the underlying theme of the work, the act of gazing, invites viewers to ponder whether what they are looking at is in fact a mirror. When &lt;i&gt;Gazing Head&lt;/i&gt; was first exhibited in Paris in 1929, it immediately grabbed the attention of the French Surrealists, beginning an association that would cement the early part of Giacometti's career.</desc>
      <collection>Alberto Giacometti-Stiftung, Zurich</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Suspended Ball</title>
      <year>1930-31</year>
      <materials>Metal, cord, plaster</materials>
      <desc>Although works like &lt;i&gt;Gazing Head&lt;/i&gt; caught the attention of the Surrealists, it was &lt;i&gt;Suspended Ball&lt;/i&gt;, first exhibited at Galerie Pierre in 1930, that prompted André Breton to invite Giacometti to join the group. The sculpture's white globular form - at once floating freely and trapped in a cage - and the enigmatic segment below it, all evinced the dream-like and erotic qualities that the Surrealists adored. In fact, following the 1930 group exhibition, Salvador Dalí contributed an article on Surrealist objects for Breton's periodical, inspired by &lt;i&gt;Suspended Ball&lt;/i&gt;. Despite this association with Breton's group, critics have also associated the sculpture with the ideas of Breton's rival, Georges Bataille. It has been argued that the elements in the sculpture are deliberately enigmatic, since while they seem to suggest a sexual act, it is unclear which element is male and which female. This confusion of categories has been said to encapsulate Bataille's notion of &lt;i&gt;informe&lt;/i&gt;, or formlessness.</desc>
      <collection>Fondation Giacometti, Paris</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Hands Holding the Void (Invisible Object)</title>
      <year>1934</year>
      <materials>Bronze</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Hands Holding the Void&lt;/i&gt; illustrates how Giacometti started to stray from the Surrealists after his brief association with the group. It was created as a monument to the artist's recently deceased father, embracing what the critic Carl Einstein called a "metaphysical realism." It incorporates certain primitive and Egyptian elements. The void the figure is holding is possibly the soul, or what the Egyptians called &lt;i&gt;kâ&lt;/i&gt;. While the Surrealists embraced this work, the figurative elements indicate that the artist was beginning to move beyond them.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>City Square</title>
      <year>1948</year>
      <materials>Painted bronze</materials>
      <desc>The multi-figured &lt;i&gt;City Square&lt;/i&gt;, while not Giacometti's first foray into the waif-like figures for which he is best known, is a stunning exercise in creating an impression of spacious landscape. Treading amidst an empty space, the figures - what Sartre called "moving outlines" - seem to rise out of nothing. In a 1960 review for &lt;i&gt;The Nation&lt;/i&gt;, Fairfield Porter observed, "Giacometti's concern is to place the relationship of man and landscape with the ground. And he further considers man and everything else as having a dual relationship to the environment as a link between the earth and infinity." By this time Giacometti was well acquainted with Existentialism, and &lt;i&gt;City Square&lt;/i&gt; could be interpreted along its lines, depicting as it does mankind as a mere shadow of itself, existing half-way between being and nothingness.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Annette with Chariot</title>
      <year>1950</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Although sculpture is the medium for which Giacometti is best known, he was also an accomplished painter and draughtsman. This 1950 oil work shows his skill at creating an impression of profound depth on a flat surface. The subject here is the artist's wife Annette, who is composed of the same lines and strokes used to depict the surrounding room, as if she herself were just another object. Nevertheless, like Giacometti's sculptural stick figures, Annette does subtly emerge from the composition, asserting her humanity amidst the otherwise bland order of the room. Much as some of the leading Existentialist thinkers of the time noted, Giacometti's mature work was an antidote to abstraction.</desc>
      <collection>Private Collection</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Woman of Venice II</title>
      <year>1956</year>
      <materials>Bronze</materials>
      <desc>Perhaps no other writer has better summed up Giacometti's bronze stick figures than Francis Ponge, who wrote in a 1951 article for &lt;i&gt;Cahiers d'Art&lt;/i&gt;, "Man - and man alone - reduced to a thread - in the dilapidation and misery of the world - who searches for himself - starting from nothing... Man on a pavement like burning iron; who cannot lift his heavy feet." Like other works in this vein, &lt;i&gt;Woman of Venice II&lt;/i&gt; shows a single figure, her body seemingly beaten almost to the point of disintegration, yet still standing tall and upright. At the heart of such works was the theme of human dignity and mankind's need to assert its existence in a vast universe that seems bent on its destruction.</desc>
      <collection>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website"/>
    <category name="where to see works"/>
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>A Giacometti Portrait</title>
          <link>0374515735</link>
          <info>By James Lord</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>In Giacometti's Studio</title>
          <link>0300093934</link>
          <info>By Michael Peppiatt</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Giacometti (2009)</title>
          <link>3775723498</link>
          <info>By Ulf Kuster, Pierre-Emanuel Martin-Vivier</info>
        </entry>
		<entry>
			<title>Alberto Giacometti: Face to Face</title>
			<link>3777436488</link>
			<info>By Christian Alandete</info>
		</entry>
		<entry recommended="true">
			<title>Alberto Giacometti: A Biography</title>
			<link>2080203797</link>
			<info>By Catherine Grenier</info>
		</entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="artworks" class="artwork">
        <entry>
          <title>Alberto Giacometti: Retrospective (2010)</title>
          <link>303764060X</link>
          <info>By Donat Rutiman, Thierry Dufrene, Nadia Schneider, Alberto Giacometti</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Alberto Giacometti: Works, Writings, Interviews (Essentials Poligrafa) (2007)</title>
          <link>8434309505</link>
          <info>By Angel Gonzalez, Alberto Giacometti</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Alberto Giacometti (2002)</title>
          <link>0870703390</link>
          <info>By Felix Baumann, Christian Klemm, Alberto Giacometti</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Alberto Giacometti</title>
          <link>2843233003</link>
          <info>By Yves Bonnefoy</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Alberto Giacometti: A Retrospective Exhibition (1974)</title>
          <link>B000V5TICK</link>
          <info>By Ulf Kuster, Pierre-Emanuel Martin-Vivier</info>
          <pdflink source="gugenheim">https://archive.org/stream/comett00giac#page/n0/mode/2up</pdflink>
        </entry>
		<entry recommended="true">
			<title>Giacometti</title>
			<link>0892075384</link>
			<info>By Karole Vail and Megan Fontanell</info>
		</entry>
		<entry recommended="true">
			<title>Alberto Giacometti: Sculptures, Paintings, Drawings</title>
			<link>3791313711</link>
			<info>By Angela Schneider</info>
		</entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
		<entry recommended="true">
			<title>Alberto Giacometti: One Of The Most Important Sculptors Of The 20th Century - Perspective</title>
			<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N05Ox0Lkkj0</link>
			<info/>
		</entry>
		<entry>
			<title>Alberto Giacometti: 'A New Way of Thinking About Humanity' - TateShots</title>
			<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M58oMKBO7S0</link>
			<info/>
		</entry>
		<entry recommended="true">
			<title>Giacometti: Walking Man II - Smarthistory</title>
			<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ps4wuBpAUCQ</link>
			<info/>
		</entry>
		<entry>
			<title>The Essence of Giacometti’s Existentialist Sculpture - Sotheby’s</title>
			<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yA1_iw4P5QI</link>
			<info/>
		</entry>
		<entry recommended="true">
			<title>Giacometti (1967) - British Film Institute</title>
			<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vRsejf8xdC0</link>
			<info/>
		</entry>
		<entry>
			<title>Alberto Giacometti’s 'Portrait of James Lord’ - Christie’s</title>
			<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I7Jpy4mAZXg</link>
			<info/>
		</entry>
		<entry>
			<title>Giacometti: The Palace at 4 a.m. - Smarthistory</title>
			<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hn39FYUiqkI</link>
			<info/>
		</entry>
		<entry>
			<title>Alberto Giacometti's Chariot - Sotheby’s</title>
			<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cpM7k604RLU</link>
			<info/>
		</entry>
		<entry recommended="true">
			<title>Giacometti: Icons of 20th Century Art - Sotheby’s</title>
			<link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JeBpRrLqdaY</link>
			<info/>
		</entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry>
          <title>Alberto Giacometti</title>
          <link>http://www.gagosian.com/artists/alberto-giacometti/</link>
          <info>Gagosian Gallery</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>"The Giacomettis' Decorative Works"</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/1987/05/24/arts/the-giacomettis-decorative-works.html?src=pm</link>
          <info>By Rita Reif&lt;br/&gt;The New York Times&lt;br/&gt;May 24, 1987</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>"Art in Review" - 'Alberto Giacometti: Sculpture' at Gagosian Gallery</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/1993/06/11/arts/art-in-review-575093.html?src=pm</link>
          <info>By Roberta Smith&lt;br/&gt;The New York Times&lt;br/&gt;June 11, 1993</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>"The human race, handled with care"</title>
          <link>http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2008/mar/23/art1</link>
          <info>By Laura Cumming&lt;br/&gt;The Observer&lt;br/&gt;March 23, 2008</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>"Alberto Giacometti: Drawings"</title>
          <link>http://www.brooklynrail.org/2009/06/artseen/alberto-giacometti-drawings</link>
          <info>
				By Alix Finkelstein
				&lt;br/&gt;
				The Brooklyn Rail
				&lt;br/&gt;
				June 2009
		  </info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>"At London Sale, a Giacometti Sets a Record"</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/04/arts/design/04giacometti.html?ref=albertogiacometti</link>
          <info>
			By Carol Vogel
			&lt;br/&gt;
			The New York Times
			&lt;br/&gt;
			February 3, 2010
		  </info>
        </entry>
		<entry recommended="true">
			<title>On the Edge of Madness: The Terrors and Genius of Alberto Giacometti</title>
			<link>https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2017/apr/21/the-terrors-genius-of-alberto-giacometti-artist-sculptor-tate-modern</link>
			<info>
				By Lara Feigel 
				&lt;br&gt;
				The Guardian  
				&lt;br&gt;
				April 21, 2017
			</info>
		</entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item/>
      <a_image/>
      <a_name/>
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>
