<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>kline_franz</id>
    <name>Franz Kline</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <is_influences>true</is_influences>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1930 - 1962</years>
    <description>Franz Kline's emphatic, abstract paintings set down with strident confidence exemplify the Action Painting achievements of the Abstract Expresionists.</description>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <highlight>3</highlight>
    <occupation>Painter</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>May 23, 1910</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>May 13, 1962</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>New York, New York</deathPlace>
    <pub_time>11/21/2011</pub_time>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>abstract_expressionism</include>
    <include>action_painting</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>abstract_expressionism</movement>
    <movement>action_painting</movement>
    <movement>nouveau_realisme</movement>
    <movement>post_painterly_abstraction</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>rothko_mark</artist>
    <artist>greenberg_clement</artist>
    <artist>rosenberg_harold</artist>
    <artist>barr_alfred</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"The final test of a painting, theirs, mine, any other, is: does the painter's emotion come across?"</q>
    <q>"I paint not the things I see but the feelings they arouse in me."</q>
    <q>"The nature of anguish is translated into different forms."</q>
    <q>"You instinctively like what you can't do."</q>
    <q>"It's a wonderful thing to be in love with The Square."</q>
    <q>"You paint the way you have to in order to give. That's life itself, and someone will look and say it is the product of knowing, but it has nothing to do with knowing, it has to do with giving."</q>
    <q>"I paint the white as well as the black, and the white is just as important."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="savvine">Ivan Savvine</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>American Abstract Expressionist Franz Kline is best known for large black and white paintings bearing abstract motifs set down with strident confidence. He started out as a realist with a fluent style that he perfected during an academic training that encouraged him to admire &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-old_masters"&gt;Old Masters&lt;/span&gt; such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rembrandt_van_rijn"&gt;Rembrandt&lt;/span&gt;. But after settling in New York and meeting &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-de_kooning_willem"&gt;Willem de Kooning&lt;/span&gt;, he began to evolve his signature abstract approach. By the end of his life he had achieved immense international recognition, and his unusual approach to gestural abstraction was beginning to influence the ideas of many &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalists&lt;/span&gt;.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Franz Kline is most famous for his black and white abstractions, which have been likened variously to New York's cityscape, the landscape of his childhood home in rural Pennsylvania, and Japanese calligraphy.</idea>
      <idea>The poet and curator &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-ohara_frank"&gt;Frank O'Hara&lt;/span&gt; saw Kline as the quintessential 'action painter', and Kline's black and white paintings certainly helped establish gestural abstraction as an important tendency within &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionism&lt;/span&gt;. Yet Kline saw his method less as a means to express himself than as a way to create a physical engagement with the viewer.</idea>
      <idea>The powerful forms of his motifs, and their impression of velocity, were intended to translate into an experience of structure and presence which the viewer could almost palpably feel.  Along with De Kooning and Pollock, Kline was one of the examplary artists heralded in &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rosenberg_harold"&gt;Harold Rosenberg's&lt;/span&gt; definition of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-action_painting"&gt;Action Painting&lt;/span&gt;.</idea>
      <idea>Kline's reluctance to attribute hidden meanings to his pictures was important in recommending his work to a later generation of Minimalist sculptors such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-judd_donald"&gt;Donald Judd&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-serra_richard"&gt;Richard Serra&lt;/span&gt;.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Franz Kline was born and raised in Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania, a small coal-mining community that offered few opportunities for artistic development. His childhood was marred by a complicated relationship with his parents. His father, a saloon keeper, committed suicide in 1917, when Kline was only seven years old. His mother later remarried and sent her son to an institution for fatherless boys, which the artist referred to as "the orphanage."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="p">Determined to make his own way, Kline worked as a cartoonist for his high school newspaper and managed to escape his small town to attend Boston University's School of Art, between 1931 and 1935. Boston offered him a wealth of opportunities: not only did his instructors help familiarize him with modern art, but he also learnt much from the city's private and public collections. After leaving, he studied briefly at the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-art_students_league"&gt;Art Students League&lt;/span&gt; in New York. He then went to England where he enrolled in the Heatherly's School of Art in London. It was there that he met his future wife, Elizabeth V. Parsons, a former ballet dancer who was working as an artist's model at the school. She returned with Kline to New York in 1938 but would later suffer a mental breakdown and spend time in mental institutions.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Franz Kline Biography" show="0">/images20/photo/kline_3.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">The first few years back in New York proved difficult for Kline. He was forced to take odd jobs: he painted murals in bars and sold illustrations to magazines. At this point, his work was shaped by his love of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-old_masters"&gt;Old Masters&lt;/span&gt; such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rembrandt_van_rijn"&gt;Rembrandt&lt;/span&gt;, but in 1943 he met &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-de_kooning_willem"&gt;Willem de Kooning&lt;/span&gt; and began to frequent the Cedar Bar, where he met &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pollock_jackson"&gt;Jackson Pollock&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-guston_philip"&gt;Philip Guston&lt;/span&gt;. Around 1947, under the influence of de Kooning, he also began to abandon figuration and experiment on a large scale with a gestural, abstract technique. He had already began to explore an austere black and white palette in a series of ink on paper sketches, but now he brought the technique to canvases and employed house-painting brushes to create broad strokes of black criss-crossing white canvases. In part he was inspired by de Kooning's black and white paintings of 1946-49, and - although the story is apocryphal - it is said that de Kooning also inspired him to scale up the work, after he encouraged him to examine it using an enlarger. "A four by five inch black drawing of a rocking chair," Kline recalled, "...loomed in gigantic black strokes which eradicated any image, the strokes expanding as entities in themselves, unrelated to any entity but that of their own existence." The pictures, which resulted from this revelation, were first exhibited at the Charles Egan Gallery in New York in 1950, a show that established Kline's reputation.</p>
          <p type="p">Critics have long debated whether Kline's black and white paintings were inspired by Japanese calligraphy. The suggestion first surfaced in reviews of his breakthrough show of 1950. However, the artist denied it, claiming that his inspirations came from unconscious sources. When asked to explain the meaning of his work, he refused, saying that he wanted the viewers to feel the effects of the composition unhindered by suggestion. Instead, he emphasized the non-symbolic character of the work, and what he called "painting experience." He was supported in this by critics such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-greenberg_clement"&gt;Clement Greenberg&lt;/span&gt;, who focused on the importance of abstract form in art, and sidelined discussions of sources or content. Kline also put a distance between himself and contemporaries such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rothko_mark"&gt;Mark Rothko&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-newman_barnett"&gt;Barnett Newman&lt;/span&gt;, whose art expressed an urge to transcendence. And, although his gestural approach might seem to place him close to de Kooning, Kline was less interested in wild expression than in the isolated gesture itself.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Period and Death">
          <p type="img" alt="Franz Kline Photo" show="0">/images20/photo/kline_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">By 1955 Kline was experimenting with color once again - using planes painted in different hues to evoke a more complex sense of space. His style also became looser, and by the early 1960s, in works such as &lt;i&gt;Red Painting&lt;/i&gt; (1961), some of his pictures were almost monochromatic. By this stage, Kline's reputation was secure as a leading &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionist&lt;/span&gt;. He was exhibiting continuously both in the U.S.A. and abroad, and was selected to show at the Venice Biennale in 1960, along with &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-hofmann_hans"&gt;Hans Hofmann&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-guston_philip"&gt;Philip Guston&lt;/span&gt; and Theodore Roszac. In 1961, his works were also included in "American Vanguard", an exhibition organized by the United States Information Agency, and which toured countries throughout Europe. Such exhibitions have since come to be seen as an important facet of the American government's efforts to advance itself as a guardian of free expression in the midst of the Cold War. He died unexpectedly of heart failure on May 13, 1962, aged only fifty-two.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">Although Kline's death received much attention in the press, his fame declined in subsequent years and his work was not seriously revisited until the art market boom of the late 1980s. However, a new generation of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalists&lt;/span&gt; found much of interest in his work. They rejected the heroics of his gestures, and their aura of lofty nobility, but they were attracted by the way the viewer could feel energized by the architectonic forms of his motifs. What to some critics seemed like references to architecture then became almost real built surfaces in the work of artists like &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-judd_donald"&gt;Donald Judd&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-serra_richard"&gt;Richard Serra&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="de_kooning_willem">Woman III (1951-53)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="pollock_jackson">Autumn Rhythm: Number 30 (1950)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="graham_john">Embrace (1932)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>de_kooning_willem</entity>
        <entity>pollock_jackson</entity>
        <entity>davis_stuart</entity>
        <entity>graham_john</entity>
        <entity>smith_david</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>greenberg_clement</entity>
        <entity>rosenberg_harold</entity>
        <entity>barr_alfred</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>expressionism</entity>
        <entity>japanese_calligraphy</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>twombly_cy</entity>
        <entity>judd_donald</entity>
        <entity>warhol_andy</entity>
        <entity>johns_jasper</entity>
        <entity>serra_richard</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>creeley_robert</entity>
        <entity>ginsberg_allen</entity>
        <entity>rothko_mark</entity>
        <entity>wyeth_andrew</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>abstract_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>minimalism</entity>
        <entity>pop_art</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Painting No. 7</title>
      <year>1952</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Unlike his friends Pollock and de Kooning, Kline never experimented with figurative elements in his mature work. &lt;/i&gt;Painting No.7&lt;/i&gt; is a fine example of his black and white pictures. The rigid geometry of broad black lines defines the composition, perhaps manifesting his reconsideration of the iconic paintings of squares by Kazimir Malevich.</desc>
      <collection>The Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Chief</title>
      <year>1950</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Critics' comments on the pictures included in Kline's breakthrough show of 1950 set the pattern for later reviews with their variety of analogies. &lt;i&gt;Chief&lt;/i&gt; was the name of a locomotive Kline remembered from his childhood, and it's possible to read the image as a sensory reminiscence of its power, sound and steaming engine. Some also believed that the artist's obsession with black was connected to his childhood spent in a coal-mining community dominated by heavy industry. Many have since noted, however, that the forms in these early abstractions seem to have evolved from Kline's drawings of his wife Elizabeth. He made numerous sketches of her sitting in a rocking chair in the years when she began to succumb to mental illness; the circular forms in &lt;i&gt;Chief&lt;/i&gt; bear comparison with the blank circles representing her face in the drawings.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
      <use_big_image>true</use_big_image>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Four Square</title>
      <year>1956</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Four Square&lt;/i&gt; is another example of Kline's experimentation with angular compositions. Although apparently structured in its compositional rigidness, &lt;i&gt;Four Square&lt;/i&gt; is a fine example of his gestural approach to painting. The viewer is led to ponder the canvas, seeing as either a close-up of a linguistic symbol or, perhaps, a set of open windows. In this work Kline is also attempting to construct a three-dimensional abstract composition, whereas most of the Abstract Expressionists preferred the two- dimensional treatment of the pictorial surface. Kline achieves the visual effect of depth through energetic juxtapositions of vertical and horizontal lines and their diagonal overlapping.</desc>
      <collection>The National Gallery of Art, Washington DC</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Meryon</title>
      <year>1960</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Meryon&lt;/i&gt; has a strong architectonic sense in its composition. The inspiration was possibly an engraving of a clock tower by the 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-century French artist Charles Meryon. Again, Kline represents not the object itself, but his vision of it. Seemingly spontaneous in its arrangement, this composition was conceived through a number of preliminary studies, shedding a new light on the nature of his gestural technique.</desc>
      <collection>Collection of the Tate, United Kingdom</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Black Reflection</title>
      <year>1956</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Black Reflection&lt;/i&gt; is an example of Kline's early attempts at introducing color back into his works. The treatment of color in this composition could be related to the contemporary paintings of Willem de Kooning and Hans Hofmann. The focal point of this picture is the black shape that Kline previously employed in the &lt;i&gt;Untitled&lt;/i&gt; composition of 1954. This fact further attests to the careful consideration the Action Painting artists devoted to the pictorial forms in their compositions.</desc>
      <collection>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York.</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Probst I</title>
      <year>1960</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Probst I&lt;/i&gt; refers to Jack Probst, a fellow artist who lived near Kline in Greenwich Village. At first glance, this composition is typical of his black and white work. However, more colors are present on this canvas. There are dabs of yellow and pale salmon that illuminate the massiveness of black twisted shapes, creating warm luminous effects. &lt;i&gt;Probst I&lt;/i&gt; is an example of Kline's late work where he returned to employing a wider palette.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" />
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Franz Kline</title>
          <link>1558597700</link>
          <info>By Harry F. Gaugh</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>An Emotional Memoir of Franz Kline</title>
          <link>B000OLV9Q4</link>
          <info>By Fielding Dawson</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="paintings" class="artwork">
        <entry>
          <title>Franz Kline (1910-1962)</title>
          <link>8884918669</link>
          <info>By David Anfam</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Franz Kline</title>
          <link>B001A5YSWK</link>
          <info>By Frank O'Hara</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry>
          <title>Franz Kline.org</title>
          <link>http://www.franzkline.org/</link>
          <info>Monograph and Comprehensive Catalogue Initiative</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Energy in Black and White</title>
          <link>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,960609-1,00.html</link>
          <info>
						By Robert Hughes
						&lt;br/&gt;
						TIME
						&lt;br/&gt;
						February 10, 1986
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Man Who Painted IMPACT</title>
          <link>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,982273,00.html</link>
          <info>
						By Robert Hughes
						&lt;br/&gt;
						TIME
						&lt;br/&gt;
						January 23, 1995
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Franz Kline at L&amp;M Arts Gallery</title>
          <link>http://i1.exhibit-e.com/lmarts/78516ee0.pdf</link>
          <info>
						By Joan Waltemath
						&lt;br/&gt;
						ARTnews
						&lt;br/&gt;
						May 2008
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry>
          <title>Kerouac and Franz Kline</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PMGjI6g05E8</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Strokes of Genius: Franz Kline</title>
          <link>http://www.amazon.com/Strokes-Genius-Franz-Dustin-Hoffman/dp/B0000DJE9S/ref=pd_bbs_sr_4?ie=UTF8&amp;s=video&amp;qid=1238899922&amp;sr=8-4</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item />
      <a_image />
      <a_name />
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>