<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>marca_relli_conrad</id>
    <name>Conrad Marca-Relli</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1933 - 2000</years>
    <description>Conrad Marca-Relli breakthrough collage paintings drew on human forms to create abstract compositions of interlocking curves and angles.</description>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <highlight>4</highlight>
    <occupation>Painter</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>June 5, 1913</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Boston, Massachusetts</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>August 29, 2000</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>Parma, Italy</deathPlace>
    <pub_time>12/5/2013</pub_time>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>abstract_expressionism</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>abstract_expressionism</movement>
    <movement>surrealism</movement>
    <movement>minimalism</movement>
    <movement>postmodernism</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>pollock_jackson</artist>
    <artist>kline_franz</artist>
    <artist>guston_philip</artist>
    <artist>rosenberg_harold</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"Collage forces you to think and clarify ideas, with regard to both space and volumes. This discipline obliges me to think in terms of forms, outlines, real and imagined spaces, so as not to fall into the temptation of thinking that nature is a reality."</q>
    <q>"Painting has nothing to do with imitating life. It has a life of its own life, in it reality is based on its own rules."</q>
    <q>"You get a linear quality from collage that is more rapid than the swiftest drawn line."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="top">The Art Story Contributors</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Conrad Marca-Relli was a Boston-born painter and sculptor who belonged to the early generation of New York School &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionist&lt;/span&gt; artists. Following a period of painting &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealist&lt;/span&gt; inspired imagery, Marca-Relli made a critical breakthrough with large-scale &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-collage"&gt;collage&lt;/span&gt; paintings that frequently drew inspiration from the human form to create abstract compositions of interlocking curves and angles. He is considered to be one of the first artists to raise the art of collage to a status comparable with monumental painting, which paved the way for the large "combine paintings" of the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-neo_dada"&gt;Neo-Dada&lt;/span&gt; artists of the 1960s.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Early in his career, Marca-Relli recognized that for abstraction to be emotionally moving, the use of psychologically affecting shapes and textures were necessary. Contours and shapes in his work were therefore based on imagined architectural themes or figure arrangements but were deliberately left ambiguous.</idea>
      <idea>Marca-Relli took a constructive approach to image making, building up surfaces by cutting out and applying shapes to canvas or metal supports. He did not seek gestural movement or uncontrolled spontaneity, but sought to create controlled, complex compositions of interlocking forms.</idea>
      <idea>Marca-Relli maintained strong links to Europe throughout his life and did not wish to break from the traditions of the "Old World" unlike many of his contemporaries. He lived and worked in France, Spain, and Italy and looked to European painters from the Renaissance, Cubism, and metaphysical movements for inspiration.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Conrad Marca-Relli was born Corrado di Marcarelli in Boston, Massachusetts to Italian immigrant parents. Marca-Relli's father was a news commentator and a journalist whose job required frequent travel, he therefore spent much of his childhood moving back and forth between the United States and Europe. He began to draw at an early age and was encouraged by his family to pursue his artistic interests, taking his first lessons during his many extended trips to Italy. There he developed a lasting feeling for the heritage of Italian art and culture and the atmosphere of European life. When he was thirteen, Marca-Relli and his parents permanently settled in New York, where Marca-Relli finished his last year of high school at night so he could dedicate his days to painting.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="p">With the exception of a year's study at the Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art in 1930, Marca-Relli was largely a self-taught painter. Following his year at Cooper Union, he established his own studio and managed to earn an income by teaching and producing occasional illustrations for the daily and weekly press. Like many of his contemporaries, Marca-Relli later supported himself by working for the Works Progress Administration, first as a teacher and then with the easel and mural painting divisions of the Federal Art Project. This period was vitally important as it not only enabled Marca-Relli to fully dedicate his time and energy to his art, but also introduced him to a community of artists, such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-de_kooning_willem"&gt;Willem de Kooning&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pollock_jackson"&gt;Jackson Pollock&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-kline_franz"&gt;Franz Kline&lt;/span&gt;, who exposed him to artistic concepts of modernism. After serving in the army during World War II, Marca-Relli returned to New York to paint. His work initially depicted stark imagined cityscapes and circus scenes influenced by the work of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-de_chirico_giorgio"&gt;Giorgio de Chirico&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rousseau_henri"&gt;Henri Rousseau&lt;/span&gt; before he turned to a form of colorful &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-biomorphism"&gt;biomorphic&lt;/span&gt; abstraction in the early 1950s.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Conrad Marca-Relli Biography">/images20/photo/marca-relli_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">In 1947 Marca-Relli moved to Paris, then to Rome, where he exhibited for two consecutive years and formed strong connections with Italian artists such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-afro"&gt;Afro&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-burri_alberto"&gt;Alberto Burri&lt;/span&gt;. He returned to New York in 1949 and immersed himself in the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-avant_garde"&gt;avant-garde art&lt;/span&gt; world in Greenwich Village, becoming a founding member of the exclusive "Eighth Street Club." The "Club" was a center for lectures and discussion and provided a supportive environment for the Abstract Expressionists. In the spring of 1951, the club organized an exhibition of its members, with Marca-Relli on the selecting committee. The groundbreaking Ninth Street Show was arguably the first comprehensive display of Abstract Expressionist work that garnered serious attention from art critics, dealers, and the public.</p>
          <p type="p">In 1953, Marca-Relli purchased a house near Jackson Pollock's home in The Springs, East Hampton, an area that was at the time developing as an artists' colony. It was at this time that Marca-Relli radically altered his painting practice. During a trip to Mexico in 1953, a lack of available painting materials compelled him to experiment with collage in order to capture his impressions of the particular light, forms, and textures of his surroundings. He developed a process wherein he intuitively combined oil painting and cutout shapes, using intense colors, layered surfaces, and expressionistic spattering to initially represent architectural forms and single figures that were inspired by de Kooning's depictions of women. As he cultivated this technique, he made more complex and dynamic abstract works with veiled references to landscape elements and figural imagery. These points of reference manifested themselves in shapes evocative of writhing bodies or in hues drawn from the natural environment.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Years and Death">
          <p type="p">Marca-Relli continued to investigate the formal possibilities of collage throughout his career. From the early 1960s, he gradually began to experiment with wood, aluminum, and vinyl on assemblage 'paintings.' The rigidity of these new materials led him to create carefully structured compositions of increasingly simplified forms and inspired a series of freestanding metal sculptures.</p>
          <p type="p">Marca-Relli's regular journeys to Europe formed an important bridge between art circles on both sides of the Atlantic. He lived and worked in London, Florida, New Jersey, Ibiza, Spain, and Paris whilst maintaining a particularly close, lifelong connection to Italy and its art world. In his final years, he lived in Parma with his wife, Anita Gibson (whom he married in 1951). Marca-Relli became an honorary Italian citizen the year before his death in 2000. That same year the Mathildenhohe Institute in Darmstadt presented a career retrospective of his work.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">Marca-Relli's nomadic lifestyle prevented close association with the New York School; indeed, much critical attention was focused on his closest friends rather than on his own work. Yet he is widely admired by artists and critics alike for the richness and variation of his uniquely constructed images. A revived interest in his contribution to the Abstract Expressionist movement has been expressed in the recent publication of a catalog raisonne by David Anfam.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="picasso_pablo">Still Life with Chair Caning (1912)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="de_chirico_giorgio">Gare Montparnasse (The Melancholy of Departure) (1914)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="pollock_jackson">Mural (1943)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>uccello_paolo</entity>
        <entity>rousseau_henri</entity>
        <entity>picasso_pablo</entity>
        <entity>braque_georges</entity>
        <entity>de_chirico_giorgio</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>pollock_jackson</entity>
        <entity>kline_franz</entity>
        <entity>ward_eleanor</entity>
        <entity>guston_philip</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>surrealism</entity>
        <entity>metaphysical_art</entity>
        <entity>constructivism</entity>
        <entity>cubism</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>afro</entity>
        <entity>burri_alberto</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>rosenberg_harold</entity>
        <entity>castelli_leo</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>abstract_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>art_informel</entity>
        <entity>neo_dada</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Untitled</title>
      <year>1940</year>
      <materials>Oil on board</materials>
      <desc>This untitled painting from 1940 reveals the influence of Giorgio di Chirico on Marca-Relli's early career as a painter. This strangely unpopulated square is strongly evocative of di Chirico's enigmatic imagery inspired by the architecture and melencholy atmosphere of Turin. The archway in the background indicate the scene is an imagined European city with its tilted perspective enhancing the flatness of the picture plane.</desc>
      <collection>Private Collection</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Seated Figure</title>
      <year>1953-54</year>
      <materials>Oil and canvas on linen</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Seated Figure&lt;/i&gt; won Marca-Relli the prestigious Logan Medal of the Art Institute of Chicago in 1954. The composition was produced during a period in which the artist focused almost exclusively on interpretations of single figures using layered planes of collaged canvas. In these works, Marca-Relli sought to explore abstract form using "the architecture of the human figure" as a starting point for interchanges between light and dark, positive and negative space.</desc>
      <collection>The Art Institute of Chicago</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Trial</title>
      <year>1956</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas and collage</materials>
      <desc>The interlocking biomorphic forms in &lt;i&gt;Trial&lt;/i&gt; represent the increasing complexity of Marca-Relli's collage technique during the 1950s. The artist has deliberately obliterated any recognizable sections of human anatomy, yet the work suggests a myriad of jostling figures. This vast composition combines an extraordinary variety of overlapping shapes, textures and contrasts to create a sense of movement that was inspired in part by Paolo Uccello's monumental battle scenes.</desc>
      <collection>The Minneapolis Institute of Arts</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>The Surge</title>
      <year>1958</year>
      <materials>Oil and collage on canvas</materials>
      <desc>In the late 1950s, Marca-Relli embarked on a series of works that were ambitious in their scale, complexity and color harmonies. With &lt;i&gt;Surge&lt;/i&gt;, Marca-Relli abandoned his formerly subdued palette of off-white and ochre to introduce bold zones of color as a new formal element in his paintings. The jostling blue, red and yellow shapes that expand outwards from a tight mass at the centre of the canvas convey a sense of intense energy and movement.</desc>
      <collection>The Cleveland Museum of Art</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Cristobal (L-12-62)</title>
      <year>1962</year>
      <materials>Oil and collage on board</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Cristobal&lt;/i&gt; displays Marca-Relli's developing interest in new materials such as vinyl and plastic. Created in 1962, this composition abandons painterly lyricism and any reference to naturalistic forms for bold geometric planes. The nails that hold the work together are deliberately left exposed to lend it an industrial appearance that is meant to suggest "the side of a freighter" in transit.</desc>
      <collection>Private Collection</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Untitled A</title>
      <year>1967</year>
      <materials>Aluminum, painted aluminum and screws</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Untitled A&lt;/i&gt; reveals Marca-Relli's continued desire to move beyond the gestures and materials traditionally associated with painting. This assemblage of planar, cut-out aluminum shapes reveals the artist's tendency towards formal reduction and simplicity in his later years. His experiments with metal came from his need to work with more resilient material than the canvas he had relied upon for previous collage work. This material introduced a new ambiguity regarding the artwork's definition as painting or sculpture.</desc>
      <collection>Hirshorn Museum and Sculpture Garden</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website"></category>
    <category name="where to see works"></category>
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="not_to_show" class=""></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="paintings" class="artwork">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Conrad Marca-Relli</title>
          <link>8890280425</link>
          <info>By David Anfam</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Conrad Marca-Relli</title>
          <link>0295978023</link>
          <info>By Conrad Marca-Relli</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Marca-Relli: John and Mable Ringling Museum of Art, November 6&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, 1979 through January 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;, 1980</title>
          <link>B0007AQMN2</link>
          <info>By Conrad Marca-Relli</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Conrad Marca-Relli: City to Town</title>
          <link>http://www.brooklynrail.org/2011/06/art/conrad-marca-relli-city-to-town</link>
          <info>
						By Phong Bui
						&lt;br&gt;
						The Brooklyn Rail 
						&lt;br&gt;
						June 3, 2011
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Celebrating a Few Fertile Years in the Hamptons</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/01/nyregion/a-fertile-period-for-marca-relli-in-the-hamptons.html?_r=0</link>
          <info>
						By Karin Lipson
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times 
						&lt;br&gt;
						April 30, 2011
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Conrad Marca-Relli: The New York Years, 1945-1967</title>
          <link>http://www.brooklynrail.org/2009/10/artseen/conrad-marca-relli-the-new-york-years-1945-1967</link>
          <info>
						By Craig Olson
						&lt;br&gt;
						The Brooklyn Rail 
						&lt;br&gt;
						October 5, 2009
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Conrad Marca-Relli, Collagist and Painter, Is Dead at 87</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/arts/conrad-marca-relli-collagist-and-painter-is-dead-at-87.html</link>
          <info>
						By Michael Kimmelman 
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times 
						&lt;br&gt;
						August 31, 2000
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="interviews" class="interviews"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>American Abstract Expressionist: Conrad Marca-Relli</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gGJergg0zvo</link>
          <info></info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>9&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; Street Show: Abstract Expressionist Artists Reminisce</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9R6cnawfnCI</link>
          <info></info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop"></subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item></a_item>
      <a_image></a_image>
      <a_name></a_name>
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>