<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>maurer_alfred</id>
    <name>Alfred Maurer</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1897 - 1932</years>
    <description>Alfred Maurer became an influential modernist who balanced abstraction with representation leading the new American art circles.</description>
    <use_big_images>true</use_big_images>
    <highlight>1</highlight>
    <mini>true</mini>
    <occupation>painter</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>April 21, 1868</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>New York</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>August 4, 1932</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>New York</deathPlace>
    <pub_time>6/19/2017</pub_time>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>fauvism</include>
    <include>synchromism</include>
    <include>early_american_modernism</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>fauvism</movement>
    <movement>synchromism</movement>
    <movement>post_impressionism</movement>
    <movement>early_american_modernism</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>stieglitz_alfred</artist>
    <artist>dove_arthur</artist>
    <artist>okeeffe_georgia</artist>
    <artist>de_zayas_marius</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q author="Hans Hoffman">"Maurer is a painter of enormous stature. His vision of the reality of painting drove him to leave behind the success that accompanied his earlier work."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="archino">Sarah Archino</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>
			The son of a prominent lithographer for the print firm of Currier &amp; Ives, Alfred Maurer began his career in a conventional manner; he attended the prestigious National Academy of Design in New York, finding success with a realist style akin to &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-whistler_james_abbott_mcneill"&gt;James McNeill Whistler&lt;/span&gt;, before moving to Paris in 1897. There, he became part of the expatriate circle of American artists in Montparnasse and his paintings were well received in both Paris and New York as part of the circle of artists around &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-henri_robert"&gt;Robert Henri&lt;/span&gt;. Yet, in 1906, Maurer abandoned this style to become one of the first Americans to adopt a riotous &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-fauvism"&gt;Fauve&lt;/span&gt; palette and "primitive" forms. Familiar with &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-avant_garde"&gt;avant-garde&lt;/span&gt; French painters from the salons of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-stein_gertrude"&gt;Gertrude&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-stein_leo"&gt;Leo Stein&lt;/span&gt;, he incorporated their brilliant colors and bold distortions into his work. His balance between abstraction and representation pioneered new terrain for his American audience. 
			&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
			At the outbreak of WWI, Maurer was forced to leave Paris and in the post-war years, the obvious influence of French modernism on his work conflicted with the growing nationalism of American art. Although his "howlers in color" were enthusiastically received by artists and the avant-garde (who continued to believe their forceful palette and energy blazed new artistic ground) Maurer struggled for mainstream recognition and sales. Maurer's artistic endeavors were compounded by the disapproval of his more traditional father; the reasons for the artist's suicide, which followed the death of his father by mere weeks, have been the subject of much speculation.
		</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Embracing the bold palette of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-fauvism"&gt;Fauvism&lt;/span&gt; and the abstracted forms of early Cubism, Maurer explored the potential for the expression of subjective emotions through representational forms. His understood his abstractions as manifestations of another level of reality and introduced these ideas to the avant-garde in New York, especially the circle around &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-stieglitz_alfred"&gt;Alfred Stieglitz&lt;/span&gt; that included &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-marin_john"&gt;John Marin&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-hartley_marsden"&gt;Marsden Hartley&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-okeeffe_georgia"&gt;Georgia O'Keeffe&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-dove_arthur"&gt;Arthur Dove&lt;/span&gt;. He believed that art had to convey a sense of experience, not just an observed subject.</idea>
      <idea>While Maurer abstracted his subjects in order to evoke emotional experiences for his viewer, his decisions about color and shape were also appreciated for their simultaneous sense of balance and energy. Later generations of abstractionists, who did not subscribe to his metaphysical beliefs about painting, still looked to his example of powerful color harmonies and dynamic forms. His experiments created a foundation for &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionism&lt;/span&gt; and other expressionist styles of painting.</idea>
      <idea>Moving away from his Fauve roots, Maurer's postwar figurative paintings were part of an international return to order and the development of a modern version of classicism. His &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-realism"&gt;realism&lt;/span&gt; provided an alternative to &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-american_regionalism"&gt;Regionalist&lt;/span&gt; painting, keeping a strain of American modernism that connected back to European art and tradition. His highly-simplified, icon-like paintings of women recast traditions of art history in a modernist palette with bold brushwork that flattens three-dimensional space.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections />
  </article>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>An Arrangement</title>
      <year>1901</year>
      <materials>Oil on cardboard</materials>
      <desc>Painted in a style heavily influenced by Whistler, this work was a critical success for Maurer, winning the gold medal at the juried Carnegie International exhibition in 1901. Even the title reflects the influence of Whistler and the Aesthetic movement, as it suggests a musical composition and the close tonality of a subdued palette. The subject of the painting, a young woman set in a fashionable &lt;i&gt;japoniste&lt;/i&gt; background, is less important than the abstract quality of the loose brushwork and harmonious shades of brown, gray, and black. The effect is a meditative mood that is created by the painterly qualities of line and color.</desc>
      <collection>Whitney Museum of American Art</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Tulips in a Green Vase,</title>
      <year>c. 1911</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>With bold compositions such as this, Maurer quickly became the most famous American Fauve artist, incorporating the bold colors, abstract forms, and flat space of that style. Rather than using color descriptively, he now embraced its suggestive and emotional potential, using unnatural tones to create a sense of energy or mood. He believed this mode of abstraction conveyed the true essence of his subject. Here, he skillfully balances the bold, gem-like, shades of blues, greens, reds, and yellows, to create flat planes of color that both describe the subject and create a flattened, decorative design. Sending his work back to America for exhibitions, he was an important influence, spreading the theories of Fauvism and the potential for abstract art to artists and audiences in the States.</desc>
      <collection>The Barnes Foundation</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>The Florentines</title>
      <year>c. 1929</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				Around 1919, Maurer began two series, &lt;i&gt;Girls&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Heads&lt;/i&gt;, to which he would return until the end of his life. He adopted a relatively standard format, positioning his sitters alone or in small groups, most often in a simple frontal pose and three-quarter length. The series progresses from fairly representational and naturalistic depictions to more stylized and abstractions renderings. Although they tend to have generic features, they were based on models. 
				&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
				Influenced by a general return-to-order in the postwar years, these paintings convey classicism in both their traditional subject and their calm approach to figuration. They reconnect to the realist paintings that had originally established Maurer's reputation, but break from his earlier illusionism to incorporate a range of primitive, Renaissance, and modernist influences. Critics considered them as "modern madonnas" and noted their Byzantine elongations of the female body; their deliberate awkwardness was celebrated as a powerful interpretation of non-Western masks and carvings.
			</desc>
      <collection>The Phillips Collection</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="whistler_james_abbott_mcneill">Arrangement in Grey and Black No. 1: Portrait of the Artist's Mother (1871)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="matisse_henri">The Woman with a Hat (1905)</artwork>
    <artwork from="movement" page="post_impressionism">The Dream (1910)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart />
  <sidebar />
</data>