<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>newman_barnett</id>
    <name>Barnett Newman</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1923 - 1970</years>
    <description>Barnett Newman's works of large fields of color and trademark 'zips' reflected his interests in myth and the primitive unconscious.</description>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <highlight>1</highlight>
    <occupation>Painter</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>January 29, 1905</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>New York, New York</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>July 4, 1970</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>New York, New York</deathPlace>
    <pub_time>7/1/2009</pub_time>
    <big_bio_box_img>Barnett Newman's &lt;i&gt;Vir Heroicus Sublimis&lt;/i&gt; at the Museum of Modern Art, New York City</big_bio_box_img>
    <bio_highlight>Saying "A painter is a choreographer of space," Barnett Newman invented what he called the "zip," a band of vertical color. Thus he led Abstract Expressionism and Color Field Painting, impacted related movements, while also being an inspiring art theorist.</bio_highlight>
    <custom_logo>true</custom_logo>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>abstract_expressionism</include>
    <include>color_field_painting</include>
    <include>action_painting</include>
    <include>the_sublime_in_art</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>abstract_expressionism</movement>
    <movement>color_field_painting</movement>
    <movement>action_painting</movement>
    <movement>the_sublime_in_art</movement>
    <movement></movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>rothko_mark</artist>
    <artist>gottlieb_adolph</artist>
    <artist>greenberg_clement</artist>
    <artist>rosenberg_harold</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"I hope that my painting has the impact of giving someone, as it did me, the feeling of his own totality, of his own separateness, of his own individuality."</q>
    <q>"The image we produce is the self-evident one of revelation, real and concrete."</q>
    <q>"It is our function as artists to make the spectator see the world our way not his way."</q>
    <q>"There is no such thing as a good painting about nothing."</q>
    <q>"I prefer to leave the paintings to speak for themselves."</q>
    <q>"I hope that my painting has the impact of giving someone, as it did me, the feeling of his own totality, of his own separateness, of his own individuality."</q>
    <q>"The problem of a painting is physical and metaphysical, the same as I think life is physical and metaphysical."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="gershman">Rachel Gershman</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Newman shared the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionists&lt;/span&gt;' interests in myth and the primitive unconscious, but the huge fields of color and trademark "zips" in his pictures set him apart from the gestural abstraction of many of his peers. The response to his mature work, even from friends, was muted when he first exhibited it. It was not until later in his career that he began to receive acclaim, and he would subsequently become a touchstone for both &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalists&lt;/span&gt; and a second generation of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-color_field_painting"&gt;Color Field painters&lt;/span&gt;. Commenting on one of Newman's exhibitions in 1959, critic &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-hess_thomas"&gt;Thomas B. Hess&lt;/span&gt; wrote, "he changed in about a year's time from an outcast or a crank into the father figure of two generations."</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Newman believed that the modern world had rendered traditional art subjects and styles invalid, especially in the post-World War II years shadowed by conflict, fear, and tragedy. Newman wrote: "old standards of beauty were irrelevant: the sublime was all that was appropriate - an experience of enormity which might lift modern humanity out of its torpor."</idea>
      <idea>Newman's pictures were a decisive break with the gestural abstraction of his peers. Instead, he devised an approach that avoided painting's conventional oppositions of figure and ground. He created a symbol, the "zip," which might reach out and invoke the viewer standing before it - the viewer fired with the spark of life.</idea>
      <idea>He thought that humans had a primal drive to create, and one could find expressions of the same instincts and yearnings locked in ancient art as one would find in modern art. He saw artists, and himself, as the creators of the world.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Barnett Newman was born in 1905 to Jewish parents who had immigrated to New York from Russian Poland five years earlier. Barney, as his family and friends called him, grew up in Manhattan and the Bronx with three younger siblings. He started drawing at the Art Students League during high school, continuing to take classes there while earning a philosophy degree from City College of New York. It was at the Art Students League that he would meet and befriend &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-gottlieb_adolph"&gt;Adolph Gottlieb&lt;/span&gt;, who would introduce him to important New York artists and gallery owners.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="img" alt="Barnett Newman Biography" show="0">/images20/photo/newman_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Following his college graduation, Newman worked for his father's clothing manufacturing business until it failed a few years after the 1929 stock market crash. During the next few years, his disparate pursuits included substitute art teaching (despite failing the art teacher qualification exam many times), running as a write-in candidate for mayor in 1933, and creating a short-lived magazine advocating civil service workers' rights. In 1936, he married Annalee Greenhouse, a teacher. During the early 1940s, he gave up painting entirely. Instead, he studied natural history, ornithology, and Pre-Columbian art, wrote museum catalogue essays and art reviews, and organized exhibitions. His interest in ornithology would later inform his famous quote, "Aesthetics is for the artist as ornithology is for the birds." During this time, he began a friendship with gallery owner Betty Parsons, for whom he organized several exhibitions. She soon began representing &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rothko_mark"&gt;Mark Rothko&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-still_clyfford"&gt;Clyfford Still&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pollock_jackson"&gt;Jackson Pollock&lt;/span&gt;, all close friends of Newman.</p>
          <p type="p">By 1944, Newman had returned to art practice, inspired in part by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealism&lt;/span&gt;. Dissatisfied with his earlier figurative work, he destroyed everything he had previously made, and he would continue to destroy work that failed to please him throughout his career. In 1946, the Betty Parsons Gallery began representing him.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="p">The year 1948 was a major turning point in Newman's career. He began developing a pictorial device he called a "zip," a vertical stripe of color running the length of the canvas, and this led to the painting &lt;i&gt;Onement I&lt;/i&gt;(1948). The device would become the trademark of all his work to come. With it, he suspended a painting's traditional opposition of figure and ground and created an enveloping experience of color in which the viewer herself, physically and emotionally, is invoked by the zip - gestured to as a being filled with the original spark of life, just like Newman's mythical "first man" (see "Writings and Ideas" below). He touched on some of these ideas in explaining how viewers should read his much larger 1950 canvas &lt;i&gt;Vir heroicus sublimis&lt;/i&gt;: "It's no different, really, from meeting another person. One has a reaction to the person physically. Also, there's a metaphysical thing, and if a meeting of people is meaningful, it affects both their lives."</p>
          <p type="p">The new work, including &lt;i&gt;Onement I&lt;/i&gt; (1948), was first shown at Betty Parsons Gallery in 1950. The response, however, was chiefly negative; one painting was even defaced, and Newman's works would continue to excite violent reactions from audiences, being slashed on several occasions in subsequent years. The following year, Parsons showed him again, yet the response was little better and it drove Newman to withdraw from the gallery scene. Throughout this time he continued writing, producing several philosophical essays about art. Most notably, he wrote "The Sublime Is Now," in which he stated, "I believe that here in America, some of us, free from the weight of European culture, are finding the answer, by completely denying that art has any concern with the problem of beauty and where to find it."</p>
          <p type="p">His work was not shown anywhere between 1951 and 1955; he even bought back a painting he no longer wanted on view. And throughout these early years, he sold very few paintings. It was not until the early 1960s - and following a heart attack in 1957 - that some of his most ardently negative critics began to shift their viewpoints.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Barnett Newman Photo" show="0">/images20/photo/newman_5.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">With the critical tide gradually changing, many began to consider Newman an important artist within Abstract Expressionism, particularly after &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-greenberg_clement"&gt;Clement Greenberg&lt;/span&gt; organized his 1959 solo show at French &amp; Company. In the 1960s, Newman expanded his work into lithographs and sculpture, which he had only delved into earlier in his career. His work appeared in several important museum exhibitions on Abstract Expressionism, securing his significant place within the movement. Despite this broader recognition, however, many still misinterpreted his work; Newman would repeatedly dispute such misunderstandings throughout his career. He would even do this at considerable cost to himself; at a time when few museums were interested in his work, he refused an offer to be in the 1962 Whitney exhibit on &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-geometric_abstraction"&gt;Geometric Abstraction&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
          <p type="p">In 1966, the Guggenheim gave Newman his first solo museum exhibition, displaying his &lt;i&gt;Stations of the Cross&lt;/i&gt;, a series of fourteen pictures executed between 1958 and 1966. Although this show also received many negative reviews, it expanded his recognition within the art world. Over the next few years, he continued creating some of his most important work. Among these included his largest painting, &lt;i&gt;Anna's Light&lt;/i&gt; (1968), the series &lt;i&gt;Who's Afraid of Red, Yellow and Blue&lt;/i&gt; (1966-68) and the monumental sculpture &lt;i&gt;Broken Obelisk&lt;/i&gt; (1963-69). On July 4, 1970, Newman died of a heart attack in New York.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">Although largely unappreciated during his life, Barnett Newman is now viewed as crucial to the Abstract Expressionist movement and as a precursor to Minimalism. Yet he never considered himself a part of any particular movement, nor a contrast to one. He rejected comparisons to geometric painters as well as comments that named him a progenitor of the Minimalist movement. Unlike those more stark canvases that focused on non-representational meaning of shapes and colors, Newman brought a more philosophical edge to his paintings, infusing them with his own self, and inviting the audience to experience them with both their bodies and their psyches.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section title="Writings and Ideas">
        <subsection title="Introduction">
          <p type="p">Newman stands out among artists of the New York School for the quantity of writing he produced, particularly in the early to mid 1940s. Discussion and ideas remained important to him, and he likened abstract thought to the non-objective forms of "primitive" art - both, he believed, were aimed at generalization and classification. However, as an artist, Newman claimed to have never approached any painting with a plan. "I am an intuitive painter," he wrote, one who is concerned with the "immediate and particular." In this respect, Newman's ideas about art were romantic. He believed that a maker of abstract art was harnessing the most basic human emotions, but wasn't bound by any mythology or ancient standard for making art, or even for viewing it.</p>
          <p type="p">In a 1962 interview Newman gave to &lt;i&gt;Art in America&lt;/i&gt; magazine, he remarked, "The central issue of painting is the subject matter... My subject is antianecdotal." An anecdotal painting, he believed, was like an episode or a piece in a longer sequence. Newman believed that if a painting is antianecdotal, then it somehow becomes more whole, self-sufficient and independent. He also believed that whatever a painting's meaning, it would come out in the viewing of the work, not through discussion.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="MOST IMPORTANT WRITINGS">
          <p type="p">
						'The First Man Was an Artist'
						&lt;br/&gt;
						&lt;i&gt;Tiger's Eye&lt;/i&gt;
						&lt;br/&gt;
						October 1947
						&lt;br/&gt;
						Newman worked as an associate editor for &lt;i&gt;Tiger's Eye&lt;/i&gt;, and 'The First Man Was an Artist' was published in the magazine's first year. In the essay, Newman asserted the priority of the aesthetic over the social: "The human in language is literature," he wrote, "not communication." Humans were artists before they were hunters, he claimed, and were storytellers before they were scientists. "Just as man's first speech was poetic before it became utilitarian, so man first built an idol of mud before he fashioned an axe." 
						&lt;br/&gt;
						Newman also questioned the benefits of scientific advancements on the mind of modern man. His position was not that science was particularly malevolent, but rather that it had become a strict form of theology that restricted the creative spirit. "The domination of science over the mind of modern man," he wrote, "has been accomplished by the simple tactic of ignoring the prime scientific quest; the concern with its original question &lt;i&gt;What&lt;/i&gt;?"
						&lt;br/&gt;
						&lt;br/&gt;
						According to Newman, once this question of "&lt;i&gt;what&lt;/i&gt;?" ceases to be at the forefront, advancements in the arts and sciences are no longer possible; they became merely the practice of reaffirming old and tried ideas.
					</p>
          <p type="p">
						'The Sublime is Now'
						&lt;br/&gt;
						&lt;i&gt;Tiger's Eye&lt;/i&gt;
						&lt;br/&gt;
						December 1948
						&lt;br/&gt;
						In this, perhaps Newman's most famous essay, he examined the work of several 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-century European artists who, he believed, destroyed old standards of beauty. He also briefly touched on the standards of beauty in art established by the ancient Greeks and examined the ways in which influential philosophers - particularly 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-century Germans - reconciled these ideas with the advent of new modern styles. The key struggle, according to Newman, was that which occurs between ideas of beauty and ideas of the sublime. Newman concluded that artists had finally succeeded in creating a new standard of beauty and the sublime. Not since the Renaissance, he claimed, had a melding of those two concepts occurred with such force. Before Abstract Expressionism, some of the greatest modern artists had only succeeded in challenging old ideas about beauty in the visual arts: "Picasso's effort may be sublime," he wrote, "but there is no doubt that his work is a preoccupation with the question of what is the nature of beauty." He believed his own generation was a new breed - artists who didn't simply question or even challenge old standards, but rather created entirely new and consequently sublime ideas about beauty.
					</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="On Abstract Art">
          <p type="img" alt="Barnett Newman Portrait" show="0">/images20/photo/newman_3.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Newman considered himself a pure artist, working with pure forms. For a 1947 exhibition at Betty Parsons Gallery, entitled &lt;i&gt;The Ideographic Picture&lt;/i&gt;, he wrote, "The basis of an aesthetic act is the pure idea. But the pure idea is, of necessity, an aesthetic act." Newman affirmed his belief that authentic, expressive abstract art was void of symbolism or illusion and that the purest living form in an abstract painting was its shape. "[A] shape [is] a living thing," he wrote, "a vehicle for an abstract thought-complex, a carrier of the awesome feelings [the artist] felt before the terror of the unknowable."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="On Art and Inquiry">
          <p type="p">For the first issue of &lt;i&gt;Tiger's Eye&lt;/i&gt;, in October 1947, Newman wrote one of his most famous essays, 'The First Man Was an Artist'. In it he sought to establish a rather unorthodox link between art and science; "For there is a difference between method and inquiry," he wrote. "Scientific inquiry, from its beginnings, has perpetually asked a single and specific question, &lt;i&gt;What&lt;/i&gt;? What is the rainbow, what is an atom, what is a star [sic]?" This basic and instinctive question of "what?" was what made all art into a science - not a science that set out to prove something, but rather a science that simply sought new knowledge and experience.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="On Beauty">
          <p type="p">According to Newman, all of modern art had been a quest to negate the classical standards of beauty established during the Renaissance. The early Modernists - artists such as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-manet_edouard"&gt;Édouard Manet&lt;/span&gt; and the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-impressionism"&gt;Impressionists&lt;/span&gt; - had failed to fully achieve this, and the task of completion was left to his own generation. "I believe that here in America," he wrote in 1948, "some of us, free from the weight of European culture, are finding the answer, by completely denying that art has any concern with the problem of beauty and where to find it... We are reasserting man's natural desire for the exalted, for a concern with our relationship to the absolute emotions."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Barnett Newman vs. Ad Reinhardt">
          <p type="p">In 1956, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-reinhardt_ad"&gt;Ad Reinhardt&lt;/span&gt; wrote an article in &lt;i&gt;College Art Journal&lt;/i&gt; entitled 'The Artist in Search of an Academy', in which he derided Barnett Newman as "the artist-professor and traveling-design-salesman, the &lt;i&gt;Art-Digest&lt;/i&gt;-philosopher-poet and Bauhaus-exerciser, the avant-garde-huckster-handicraftsman and educational-shop-keeper, the holy-roller-explainer-entertainer-in-residence."</p>
          <p type="p">Newman was enraged and sued Reinhardt for libel. When the case reached the New York Supreme Court, it was dismissed and subsequently rejected again upon appeal. But Newman was often similarly criticized by fellow artists for being overly romantic - Pollock reportedly called him a "horse's ass" at one gallery opening.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="In Discussion with Hess on &lt;i&gt;Stations of the Cross&lt;/i&gt;">
          <p type="p">In a public conversation between Thomas B. Hess and Newman, staged at the Guggenheim Museum on May 1, 1966, Newman was asked a series of questions regarding his &lt;i&gt;Stations of the Cross&lt;/i&gt; series (1958-66), which were exhibited at the museum in Newman's very first solo exhibition at a public gallery.</p>
          <p type="p">"When I call them &lt;i&gt;Stations of the Cross&lt;/i&gt;," he said, "I am saying that these paintings mean something beyond their formal extremes...What I'm saying is that my painting is physical and what I'm saying also is that my painting is metaphysical...that my life is physical and my life is also metaphysical." Hess later asked Newman about the absence of color in the pictures - something that was unusual in his work. Newman responded, "Tragedy demands black, white, and gray. I couldn't paint a green passion, but I did try to make raw canvas come into color. That was my color problem - to get the quality of color without the use of color. A painter should try to paint the impossible."</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="giacometti_alberto">Woman of Venice II (1956)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="mondrian_piet">Composition with Large Red Plane, Yellow, Black, Gray, and Blue (1921)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="malevich_kasimir">Black Square (c. 1915)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>giacometti_alberto</entity>
        <entity>mondrian_piet</entity>
        <entity>malevich_kasimir</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>kant_immanuel</entity>
        <entity>goethe_johann_wolfgang</entity>
        <entity>hegel_georg</entity>
        <entity>marx_karl</entity>
        <entity>greenberg_clement</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>pre_columbian_art</entity>
        <entity>abstract_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>color_field_painting</entity>
        <entity>surrealism</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>stella_frank</entity>
        <entity>andre_carl</entity>
        <entity>judd_donald</entity>
        <entity>flavin_dan</entity>
        <entity>noland_kenneth</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>greenberg_clement</entity>
        <entity>hess_thomas</entity>
        <entity>rosenberg_harold</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>minimalism</entity>
        <entity>color_field_painting</entity>
        <entity>pop_art</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Onement I</title>
      <year>1948</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas and oil on masking tape on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Newman saw &lt;i&gt;Onement I&lt;/i&gt; as a breakthrough in his work. It features the first full incarnation of what he later called a "zip," a vertical band of color. This motif would play a central role in many of his subsequent paintings. The painting's title is an archaic derivation of the word "atonement," meaning, "the state of being made into one." For Newman, this unevenly painted zip on a flat field of color does not divide the canvas; rather, it merges both sides, drawing in the audience to intensely experience the work both physically and emotionally. Some have compared the zips to Alberto Giacometti's slender figures, reinforcing Newman's own connections between his paintings and the viewer's body.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Vir heroicus sublimis</title>
      <year>1950-51</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Translated as "Man, heroic and sublime," &lt;i&gt;Vir heroicus sublimis&lt;/i&gt; was, at 95 by 213 inches, Newman's largest painting at the time it was completed, although he would go on to create even more expansive works. He intended his audiences to view this and other large paintings from a close vantage point, allowing the colors and zips to fully surround them. In this piece, which is more complex than it initially appears, Newman's zips are variously solid or wavering, creating a perfect square in the center and asymmetrical spaces on the perimeter. Mel Bochner, an artist associated with Conceptualism, remembered encountering it at the Museum of Modern Art in the late 1960s and realizing that its scale and color created a new kind of contact between the artwork and the viewer. "A woman standing there [looking at it]...was covered with red," he recalled. "I realized it was the light shining on the painting reflecting back, filling the space between the viewer and the artwork that created the space, the place. And that that reflection of the self of the painting, the painting as the subject reflected on the viewer, was a wholly new category of experience."</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
      <use_big_image>true</use_big_image>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>The Wild</title>
      <year>1950</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;The Wild&lt;/i&gt; is unique in Newman's &lt;i&gt;oeuvre&lt;/i&gt; by virtue of its unusual size; at eight feet tall by one and a half inches wide, it focuses on the zip alone. When first exhibited it was placed directly across from the vast &lt;i&gt;Vir heroicus sublimis&lt;/i&gt; (1950-51) and was said to be a response to the latter's sprawling size. It demonstrated Newman's belief that a painting need not be physically large to inspire an intense response from the viewer. &lt;i&gt;The Wild&lt;/i&gt; could also be regarded as one of the first of the shaped canvases that became popular over a decade later with the arrival of artists such as Frank Stella and Kenneth Noland.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Third Station</title>
      <year>1960</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Third Station&lt;/i&gt; is part of Newman's major fourteen-piece series, &lt;i&gt;The Stations of the Cross: Lema Sabachthani&lt;/i&gt; (1958-66). The title refers to Christ's cry on the cross, yet he also intended to evoke the cries of humanity throughout history. The series is characterized by a stark palette of black, white, and raw canvas - Newman wanted the unpainted canvas to become its own color - and the picture expands the artist's use of the zip, with some appearing starkly straight and others seeming feathered and about to explode. The series took eight years to complete because, as Newman said, he could never plan a picture; "I could not do them all at once, automatically, one after the other...When there was a spontaneous urge to do [each of the paintings] is when I did them."</desc>
      <collection>The National Gallery of Art, Washington DC</collection>
      <use_big_image>true</use_big_image>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Canto VII</title>
      <year>1963</year>
      <materials>Lithograph</materials>
      <desc>In addition to paintings, Newman also created etchings and lithographs, such as the series &lt;i&gt;18 Cantos&lt;/i&gt; (1963-64). The &lt;i&gt;Cantos&lt;/i&gt; are his only print series executed in color, and Newman spoke of them using musical analogies; "their symphonic mass lends additional clarity to each individual canto," he wrote in an introduction to the series, "and at the same time, each canto adds its song to the full chorus." In &lt;i&gt;18 Cantos&lt;/i&gt;, Newman employs a wide, offset band, a variation on the thinner zips, and allows the colors to bleed out into the margins, testing the idea of spatial boundaries. He has written that each canto has its own "personal margins."</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Broken Obelisk</title>
      <year>1963-69</year>
      <materials>Cor-Ten steel</materials>
      <desc>Newman made several sculptures, but &lt;i&gt;Broken Obelisk&lt;/i&gt; is his most monumental. Its use of heavy, rough-surfaced steel contrasts with the impression of lightness created by the inverted obelisk that almost floats above the stable pyramid. The two parts connect at a space of only two and a quarter inches, with an internal steel rod stabilizing the massive sculpture. Although ancient imagery of pyramids and obelisks are often associated with death, Newman reinvents them here to evoke life and transcendence. Several versions of &lt;i&gt;Broken Obelisk&lt;/i&gt; exist, with one in Houston, dedicated to the memory of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York</collection>
      <use_big_image>true</use_big_image>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <reviews>
    <review>
      <title>Les Sourciers</title>
      <artist>Yves Tanguy</artist>
      <year>1945</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Les Sourciers&lt;/i&gt; is typical of the work of the French Surrealist Yves Tanguy, who often used biomorphic forms to evoke dream images. Surrealism was important in the formation of Abstract Expressionism, providing a precedent for the movement's interest in myth and the unconscious. Yet not all were in agreement with its approaches. In his now celebrated 1945 essay 'The Plasmic Image' (never published in his lifetime), Newman discussed the key differences between Surrealism and abstraction; "Surrealism is interested in a dream world that will penetrate the human psyche," he wrote. "[But] the present painter is concerned not with his own feelings or with the mystery of his own personality but with the penetration into the world mystery. His imagination is therefore attempting to dig into metaphysical secrets." Newman disliked the Surrealists' delving into personal worlds, and he was anxious to insist that abstract painting was not similarly introverted; Newman believed his art was a quasi-religious endeavor filled with universal symbols.</desc>
      <collection>Private Collection</collection>
    </review>
    <review>
      <title>Composition A</title>
      <artist>Piet Mondrian</artist>
      <year>1923</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>According to Newman, Piet Mondrian was one of those modern artists who had tried to achieve a new standard of beauty and purity in art by making the painting itself the subject matter. He admired that ambition, yet he was doubtful that Mondrian had succeeded; in his 1948 essay 'The Sublime is Now', Newman cited him as an artist who, "in his attempt to destroy the Renaissance picture by his insistence on pure subject matter, succeeded only in raising the white plane and the right angle into a realm of sublimity, where the sublime paradoxically becomes an absolute of perfect sensations." Newman concluded that Mondrian's paintings as a whole could not be sublime or transcendent, because old standards of beauty - Renaissance standards - were still upheld. Only with the arrival of Abstract Expressionism had artists fully embraced new conceptions of beauty.</desc>
      <collection>Galleria Nazionale d'Arte Moderna e Contemporanea, Rome</collection>
    </review>
    <review>
      <title>Untitled</title>
      <artist>Mark Rothko</artist>
      <year>1955</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Barnett Newman and Mark Rothko were once close friends, and Newman was very interested in his friend's work, but in a letter addressed to Sidney Janis, dated April 9, 1955, Newman wrote, "I am frankly bored with the uninspired, or to put it more accurately, I am bored with the too easily inspired...This easy ability to be inspired not only reduces the concepts that form his [Rothko's] sources, not only distorts the act of painting itself, but it is so at variance with my own point of view that I can only reject everything it involves." Newman disliked the evocation of death and the macabre in Rothko's work. "Why should I look at his death image?" he continued. "I am involved in life, in the joy of the spirit."</desc>
      <collection>The National Gallery of Art, Washington DC</collection>
    </review>
  </reviews>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" />
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry>
          <title>Reconsidering Barnett Newman</title>
          <link>0300109334</link>
          <info>By Melissa Ho, Mel Bochner, Yve-Alain Bois, B.H. Friedman, Mark Godfrey, Ben Heller, Carol Mancusi-Ungaro, Robert Murray, Suzanne Penn, Sarah K. Rich, Nan Rosenthal, Pierre Schneider, Gabriele Schor, Richard Shiff, Allan Stone</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Barnett Newman</title>
          <link>0870705008</link>
          <info>By Thomas B. Hess</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Barnett Newman: Selected Writings and Interviews</title>
          <link>0520078179</link>
          <info>By Barnett Newman, John P. O'Neill, Richard Shiff</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Sublime Is Now: The Early Work of Barnett Newman</title>
          <link>1878283421</link>
          <info>By Jeremy Strick, Barnett Newman, Walker Art Center, St. Louis Art Museum, Pace Gallery</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="paintings" class="artwork">
        <entry>
          <title>Barnett Newman</title>
          <link>0300094299</link>
          <info>By Ann Temkin</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Barnett Newman: A Catalogue Raisonné</title>
          <link>0300101678</link>
          <info>By Richard Shiff, Carol Mancusi-Ungaro, Heidi Colsman-Freyberger</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Looking at Barnett Newman</title>
          <link>1902854209</link>
          <info>By Jeremy Lewison</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Barnett Newman Foundation</title>
          <link>http://www.barnettnewman.org/</link>
          <info>Features a Chronology and Bibliography for the Artist</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Philadelphia Museum of Art: Barnett Newman</title>
          <link>http://www.philamuseum.org/micro_sites/exhibitions/newman/index.html</link>
          <info>Includes Biographical Information and Images of Barnett Newman's Work</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Museum of Modern Art: Barnett Newman</title>
          <link>http://www.moma.org/collection/artist.php?artist_id=4285</link>
          <info>Provides an Image Gallery of Works by the Artist</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>Barnett Newman at Craig F. Starr Gallery</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/25/arts/design/barnett-newman-at-craig-f-starr-gallery-review.html</link>
          <info>
						By Roberta Smith
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times 
						&lt;br&gt;
						November 29, 2011
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>He Had to Draw the Line Somewhere</title>
          <link>http://www.guardian.co.uk/theobserver/2002/sep/22/features.review77</link>
          <info>
						By Tim Adams
						&lt;br&gt;
						The Observer
						&lt;br&gt;
						September 21, 2002
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Barnett Newman and the Heroic Sublime</title>
          <link>http://www.thenation.com/article/barnett-newman-and-heroic-sublime#</link>
          <info>
						By Arthur C. Danto
						&lt;br&gt;
						The Nation
						&lt;br&gt;
						June 17, 2002
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Lord Barney</title>
          <link>http://www.newyorker.com/archive/2002/04/15/020415craw_artworld</link>
          <info>
						By Peter Schjeldahl 
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New Yorker 
						&lt;br&gt;
						April 15, 2002 
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>A Giant Zip for Mankind</title>
          <link>http://www.artnews.com/2002/03/01/a-giant-zip-for-mankind/</link>
          <info>
						By Ann Temkin
						&lt;br&gt;
						ARTnews
						&lt;br&gt;
						March 1, 2002
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="interviews" class="interviews" />
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>NPR: All Things Considered: Barnett Newman</title>
          <link>http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=1145959</link>
          <info>October 28, 2002</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Smarthistory: Discussion of Barnett Newman's Onement I (1948)</title>
          <link>http://smarthistory.khanacademy.org/barnett-newman.html?q=barnett-newman.html</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Museum of Modern Art: The Painting Techniques of Barnett Newman: Vir Heroicus Sublimis</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GacKM9yxiw4</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips" />
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop">
        <entry>
          <title>Painters Painting (1973)</title>
          <link>http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0207645/</link>
          <info>Film with Newman Interview</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item />
      <a_image />
      <a_name />
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>