<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>pousette_dart_richard</id>
    <name>Richard Pousette-Dart</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1934 - 1991</years>
    <description>Pousette-Dart was the youngest of the first generation of Abstract Expressionists whose work maintained a more transcendent and positive quality.</description>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <highlight>4</highlight>
    <occupation>Draftsman, Painter, and Sculptor</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>June 8, 1916</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>St. Paul, Minnesota</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>October 25, 1992</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>Suffern, New York</deathPlace>
    <pub_time>12/5/2013</pub_time>
    <cname>Pousette-Dart</cname>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>abstract_expressionism</include>
    <include>action_painting</include>
    <include>color_field_painting</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>abstract_expressionism</movement>
    <movement>action_painting</movement>
    <movement>post_painterly_abstraction</movement>
    <movement>color_field_painting</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>olitski_jules</artist>
    <artist>frankenthaler_helen</artist>
    <artist>mitchell_joan</artist>
    <artist>diebenkorn_richard</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"I strive to express the spiritual nature of the Universe. Painting for me is a dynamic balance and wholeness of life; it is mysterious and transcending, yet solid and real."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="top">The Art Story Contributors</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>The painter Richard Pousette-Dart was the youngest member of the first generation of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionists&lt;/span&gt;. His early work, marked by thick black contour lines and primitive themes, gave way to a freer abstract style in the 1940s, and to light-infused, pointillist paintings in the 1950s and 1960s. Although initially associated with the classic Abstract Expressionist angst, his work maintained a more transcendent and positive quality to it, increasingly focused on the expression of spiritual ideals in paint and color.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Pousette-Dart's paintings are imbued with a sense of the spiritual and the mythic, evoking primordial forms and scenes.</idea>
      <idea>The artist's experiments with abstraction began with abstracted animal shapes, but soon evolved into formal explorations of textural handling, built-up surfaces, and intense color.</idea>
      <idea>Despite being present for the iconic &lt;i&gt;Irascibles&lt;/i&gt; photo by Nina Leen in &lt;i&gt;Life&lt;/i&gt; magazine, Pousette-Dart was one of the more independent artists within Abstract Expressionism, leaving New York City at the height of the movement and pursuing an optimistic, life-affirming art style to the end.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Richard Pousette-Dart was born on June 8, 1916 to educated, artistically-inclined parents in St. Paul, Minnesota. The family soon moved to Valhalla, New York, where Pousette-Dart spent most of his childhood. His father, Nathaniel Pousette, was an artist, collector, and writer, and his mother, Flora Dart, a musician, pianist, and poet. His early interests in art and music were strongly encouraged by his parents.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="p">Before turning to painting, Pousette-Dart worked with bronze sculpture, and his earliest works are in that medium. He spent a year at Bard College in the 1930s before moving to New York City, where he worked with the sculptor &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-manship_paul"&gt;Paul Manship&lt;/span&gt; as an assistant. In Manhattan, his ideas about art were influenced by visits to the Museum of Modern Art and the American Museum of Natural History. He was particularly impressed by the Byzantine period and the work of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-van_gogh_vincent"&gt;Vincent van Gogh&lt;/span&gt;. In addition, an early job as a secretary in a photography studio, where he completed color retouchings, is often cited as an influence on the dotted, pointillist style he developed later in his paintings.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="p">Pousette-Dart's paintings in the late 1930s and early 1940s share in the primitive, mythic quality evoked in the early work of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pollock_jackson"&gt;Jackson Pollock&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rothko_mark"&gt;Mark Rothko&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-still_clyfford"&gt;Clyfford Still&lt;/span&gt;, and other New York painters. Pousette-Dart mined a variety of sources, from Eastern philosophy and Jungian psychology to the totemic forms of Oceanic and Native Art, to develop these themes. The resulting paintings feature birds, bull heads, egg shapes, and other animal forms, often rimmed with the artist's distinctive black contour line, and suggesting sacrifice, ancient rite, or primitive spirituality. Like many of his Abstract Expressionist peers, his early work shows a great debt to &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-picasso_pablo"&gt;Pablo Picasso&lt;/span&gt;, with its animal imagery and its tension between recognizable forms and abstracted motifs.</p>
          <p type="p">Between 1941 and 1942, Pousette-Dart painted what many consider to be the first grand-scale work in Abstract Expressionism, &lt;i&gt;Symphony No.1, The Transcendental&lt;/i&gt;. Several of his large-scale works from this period have a dark tenor, as in &lt;i&gt;Crucifixion, Comprehension of the Atom&lt;/i&gt; (1944), where he grapples with the themes of nuclear war and human suffering. Extremely attuned to formal issues, Pousette-Dart developed his pantheon of animal forms into an extensive array of squiggles, triangles, ovaloids, and cell-like shapes, a vocabulary that would come to characterize his organic, gestural dynamism for years to come. During this generative period in New York, Pousette-Dart showed at &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-guggenheim_peggy"&gt;Peggy Guggenheim's&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-gallery_art_of_this_century"&gt;Art of This Century Gallery&lt;/span&gt; and at the Betty Parsons Gallery.</p>
          <p type="p">Pousette-Dart's work became increasingly painterly in the 1940s and 1950s, assuming a rougher, heavier mark. In 1951, despite his growing success and the newly recognized cache of the New York art scene, Pousette-Dart left Manhattan with his wife Evelyn Gracey for Sloatsburg and then Suffern, both in Rockland County, New York. In his studio upstate, he continued on his artistic journey, producing work that was increasingly spiritual in nature. Many of the abstracted figural motifs began to give way to designs in pure color, texture, and form. His brightly colored works from the period have been likened to mosaics and stained-glass windows, with their vertical streams of jewel-like color. In the 1960s, Pousette-Dart turned increasingly to a pointillist approach, layering dabs or dots of paint over one another to create spreading, pulsing fields of color.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Years and Death">
          <p type="img" alt="Richard Pousette-Dart Biography">/images20/photo/pousette_dart_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Pousette-Dart painted into his seventies, utilizing and modifying approaches from his stylistic arsenal of pointillism, geometry, gesture, and inscribed text. In his journal writings, Pousette-Dart attached particular thematic meanings to the 'square of matter' and the 'circle of spirit,' notions that become especially apparent in his work of the 1980s and 1990s. Here, the angst and dynamism of some of his earlier work has settled into a more static harmony, with circles, ovals, and meanders arranged as balanced meditations on matter, spirit, and universal form. Pousette-Dart died in Suffern, NY, at the age of 76.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">While famous in his day, Pousette-Dart's legacy has faded more than that of some of his Abstract Expressionist peers. This is explained in part by the independent quality of his work, being neither 'expressionist' nor fully 'abstract,' it tends to be left out of canonical accounts of the New York School. Pousette-Dart also lacked the notoriety and brooding mien of other contemporaries. He was a vegetarian and spiritualist who avoided alcohol and depression, and thus does not fit the stereotype of the suffering New York painter that others embodied.</p>
          <p type="p">There is no doubt, however, that his work influenced other developing artists of his day, especially in his abstraction of primitive scenes and the figures and the color-centric approach of his pointillist works. In recent years, Pousette-Dart's posthumous reputation has grown, with retrospectives at The Peggy Guggenheim Collection in Venice and the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum in New York. Pousette-Dart's daughter, Joanna Pousette-Dart, and a grandson, Chris Pousette-Dart, are both contemporary abstract artists.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="gorky_arshile">Aviation: Evolution of Forms under Aerodynamic Limitations (1937)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="gottlieb_adolph">Pictograph (1946)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="miro_joan">Maternity (1924)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>picasso_pablo</entity>
        <entity>gorky_arshile</entity>
        <entity>gottlieb_adolph</entity>
        <entity>miro_joan</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>graham_john</entity>
        <entity>freud_sigmund</entity>
        <entity>jung_carl</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>primitivism</entity>
        <entity>african_art</entity>
        <entity>byzantine_art</entity>
        <entity>cubism</entity>
        <entity>surrealism</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>pollock_jackson</entity>
        <entity>gottlieb_adolph</entity>
        <entity>still_clyfford</entity>
        <entity>rothko_mark</entity>
      </column>
      <column></column>
      <column>
        <entity>abstract_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>color_field_painting</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Animal Head</title>
      <year>c. 1936-8</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>This work, an abstracted study of an animal head, shows Pousette-Dart's interest in tribal and Jungian themes of confrontation and sacrifice. These themes are the main focus of his work in the 1930s and early 40s. The oval shape is repeated and modified to suggest eye, horn, egg, yolk, and fetus, all surrounded by his characteristic black contour line.</desc>
      <collection>Hollis Taggart Galleries, New York, NY</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Symphony No. 1, The Transcendental</title>
      <year>1941-2</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Symphony No. 1, The Transcendental&lt;/i&gt; is a large painting, considered by many to be the first mural-scale work of Abstract Expressionism. Evoking at once musical notes, cell-like squiggles, and the orbits of a planetary system, the work suggests the universal forms that inhere in the world at large. While the spiritual theme and many of the shapes are familiar from his 1930s work, Pousette-Dart's style has become more painterly and textured.</desc>
      <collection>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Chavade</title>
      <year>1951</year>
      <materials>Oil and pencil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Pousette-Dart created a number of works in the early 1950s like this one, using pencil and white paint on canvas or board. Originally prompted by a tight budget, the approach shows Pousette-Dart exploring an ethereal side to the abstract grids of Picasso and his New York School heirs. One can discern the characteristic ovals, eye-shapes, and arcs, but rendered in a softer and more --- manner.</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York, NY</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Illumination Gothic</title>
      <year>1958</year>
      <materials>Oil on linen</materials>
      <desc>Pousette-Dart developed his pantheon of diamonds, circles, and organic shapes into vertical compositions in the 1950s and 60s. The thickly layered forms in this work suggest an underwater seabed, a stained glass window, or the streaming refractions of filtered light. Where in earlier paintings there are still some distinct, quasi-representational forms, the elements here are abstract and fluid, diffused across the colored ground.</desc>
      <collection>Estate of Richard Pousette-Dart</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Golden Presence</title>
      <year>1961</year>
      <materials>Oil on linen</materials>
      <desc>With its allover style of colored dots, &lt;i&gt;Golden Presence&lt;/i&gt; exemplifies Pousette-Dart's pointillist approach. Up close, one can see the highly textured surface daubs and marks. From far away, the densely layered surface suggests a landscape, garden, or other spatial presence. Pousette-Dart here evokes the spiritual element not through suggestive subject matter but through color, texture, and the veil-like, shimmering surface of the work.</desc>
      <collection>Valerie Carberry Gallery, Chicago IL</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Now a Turning Orb</title>
      <year>1987-90</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on linen</materials>
      <desc>In &lt;i&gt;Now a Turning Orb&lt;/i&gt;, Pousette-Dart employs familiar forms from his career, like nested circles, pointillist dots, and curved arcs and lines. Here, as in many of his late works, Pousette-Dart balances a sense of structure and harmony (in the even weave of the gridded forms and the central circle) with dynamism and energy (in the vibrating brushstrokes and the sense of whirring motion).</desc>
      <collection>Private Collection, Munich</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website"></category>
    <category name="where to see works"></category>
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="not_to_show" class=""></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="paintings" class="artwork">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Richard Pousette-Dart: The New York School and Beyond</title>
          <link>8876241558</link>
          <info>By Robert Mattison, Martica Sawin, John Yau Pepe Karmel, Sam Hunter, and Joanne Kuebler</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Richard Pousette-Dart</title>
          <link>0300086555</link>
          <info>By Lowery Stokes Sims and Stephen Polcari</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>The Estate of Richard Pousette-Dart</title>
          <link>http://www.richardpousette-dart.com</link>
          <info></info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Richard Pousette-Dart at the Metropolitan Museum of Art</title>
          <link>http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/works-of-art/1996.367</link>
          <info></info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>Richard Pousette-Dart</title>
          <link>http://artforum.com/inprint/issue=201203&amp;id=30351</link>
          <info>

						By David Rimanelli

						&lt;br&gt;

						Artforum 

						&lt;br&gt;

						March 2012

					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Scenes of the East River by Richard Pousette-Dart</title>
          <link>http://www.examiner.com/article/scenes-of-the-east-river-by-richard-pousette-dart</link>
          <info>

						The Examiner

						&lt;br&gt;

						December 5, 2011

					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>A Little Abstract, a Little Eccentric, and More</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/17/arts/17dart.html</link>
          <info>

						By Roberta Smith 

						&lt;br&gt;

						The New York Times 

						&lt;br&gt;

						August 17, 2007 

					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Richard Pousette-Dart</title>
          <link>http://www.brooklynrail.org/2005/12/artseen/richard-pousette-dart</link>
          <info>

						By Jim Long

						&lt;br&gt;

						The Brooklyn Rail 

						&lt;br&gt;

						December 10, 2005 

					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="interviews" class="interviews"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry>
          <title>Richard Pousette-Dart at the Guggenheim Museum</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AN3h7m00LNI</link>
          <info>Amateur Video by James Kalm</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Pousette-Dart: Predominantly White Paintings</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5IPoc1_tToA</link>
          <info></info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips"></subcategory>
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop">
        <entry>
          <title>The Pousette-Dart Band</title>
          <link>http://www.pousette-dart.com/</link>
          <info>Richard Pousette-Dart's son Jon founded the Pousette-Dart Band with friends in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1973. Playing throughout the 1970s and 1980s, the group used paintings by Richard Pousette-Dart as cover art for some of their albums.</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item></a_item>
      <a_image></a_image>
      <a_name></a_name>
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>