<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>rothko_mark</id>
    <name>Mark Rothko</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1923 - 1970</years>
    <description>Mark Rothko painted soft, rectangular forms floating in saturated color that made him a leader of New York Abstract Expressionism.</description>
    <use_big_images>false</use_big_images>
    <show_posters>true</show_posters>
    <highlight>6</highlight>
    <occupation>Painter</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>September 25, 1903</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Dvinsk, Russian Empire</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>February 25, 1970</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>New York, New York</deathPlace>
    <pub_time>7/1/2009</pub_time>
    <big_bio_box_img>Mark Rothko in Yorktown Heights (c. 1949)</big_bio_box_img>
    <bio_highlight>“We start with color," Rothko famously stated in 1936 when he was writing a book comparing children’s art to modern paintings. He went on to employ that early sense of color with his inherent belief: “the exhilarated tragic experience is for me the only source of art,” as he created his Color Field paintings, celebrated for their spiritual and psychological presence.</bio_highlight>
    <hero>true</hero>
    <custom_logo>true</custom_logo>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>abstract_expressionism</include>
    <include>surrealism</include>
    <include>color_field_painting</include>
    <include>the_sublime_in_art</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>abstract_expressionism</movement>
    <movement>surrealism</movement>
    <movement>color_field_painting</movement>
    <movement>the_sublime_in_art</movement>
    <movement></movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>de_kooning_willem</artist>
    <artist>newman_barnett</artist>
    <artist>gottlieb_adolph</artist>
    <artist>avery_milton</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"If you are only moved by color relationships, you are missing the point. I am interested in expressing the big emotions - tragedy, ecstasy, doom."</q>
    <q>"I think of my pictures as dramas; the shapes in the pictures are the performers. They have been created from the need for a group of actors who are able to move dramatically without embarrassment and execute gestures without shame."</q>
    <q>"Ideas and plans that existed in the mind at the start were simply the doorway through which one left the world in which they occur."</q>
    <q>"Since my pictures are large, colorful, and unframed, and since museum walls are usually immense and formidable, there is the danger that the pictures relate themselves as decorative areas to the walls."</q>
    <q>"The fact that people break down and cry when confronted with my pictures shows that I can communicate those basic human emotions.. the people who weep before my pictures are having the same religious experience I had when painting them. And if you say you are moved only by their color relationships then you miss the point."</q>
    <q>"The most important tool the artist fashions through constant practice is faith in his ability to produce miracles when they are needed. Pictures must be miraculous: The instant one is completed, the intimacy between the creation and the creator is ended. He is an outsider, the picture must be for him, as for anyone experiencing it later, a revelation, an unexpected and unprecedented resolution of an eternally familiar need."</q>
    <q>"The progression of a painter's work, as it travels in time from point to point, will be toward clarity; toward the eliminiation of all obstacles between the painter and the idea, and between the idea and the observer."</q>
    <q>"Art to me is an anecdote of the spirit, and the only means of making concrete the purpose of its varied quickness and stillness."</q>
    <q>"I am not an abstractionist, I have never lost the sense of the need for concreteness. That is why I do not understand an aesthetic built on the perception of relationships. The image for me must always be concrete and indivisible and understandable in terms of real life"</q>
    <q author="Mark Rothko and Adolph Gottlieb">"We favor the simple expression of the complex thought. We are for the large shape because it has the impact of the unequivocal. We wish to reassert the picture plane. We are for flat forms because they destroy illusion and reveal truth."</q>
    <q>"I do not believe that there was ever a question of being abstract or representational. It is really a matter of ending this silence and solitude, of breathing, and stretching one’s arms again transcendental experiences became possible."</q>
    <q>"Like the Cubists before them, the abstractionists felt a beautiful thing in perceiving how the medium can, of its own accord, carry one into the unknown, that is to the discovery of new structures. What an inspiration the medium is.."</q>
    <q>"While the authority of the doctor or plumber is never questioned, everyone deems himself a good judge and an adequate arbiter of what a work of art should be and how it should be done."</q>
    <q>"In matters of art our society has substituted taste for truth, which she finds more amusing and less of a responsibility, and changes her tastes as frequently as she changes her hats and shoes."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="top">The Art Story Contributors</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>A prominent figure among the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;New York School&lt;/span&gt; painters, Mark Rothko moved through many artistic styles until reaching his signature 1950s motif of soft, rectangular forms floating on a stained field of color. Heavily influenced by mythology and philosophy, he was insistent that his art was filled with content, and brimming with ideas. A fierce champion of social revolutionary thought, and the right to self-expression, Rothko also expounded his views in numerous essays and critical reviews.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Highly informed by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-nietzsche_friedrich"&gt;Nietzsche&lt;/span&gt;, Greek mythology, and his Russian-Jewish heritage, Rothko's art was profoundly imbued with emotional content that he articulated through a range of styles that evolved from figurative to abstract.</idea>
      <idea>Rothko's early figurative work - including landscapes, still lifes, figure studies, and portraits - demonstrated an ability to blend &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-expressionism"&gt;Expressionism&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealism&lt;/span&gt;. His search for new forms of expression led to his Color Field paintings, which employed shimmering color to convey a sense of spirituality.</idea>
      <idea>Rothko maintained the social revolutionary ideas of his youth throughout his life. In particular he supported artists' total freedom of expression, which he felt was compromised by the market. This belief often put him at odds with the art world establishment, leading him to publicly respond to critics, and occasionally refuse commissions, sales and exhibitions.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Born in Dvinsk, Russia (in what is now Latvia), Marcus Rothkovich was the fourth child born to Jacob and Anna Rothkovich. As Russia was a hostile environment for Zionist Jews, Jacob immigrated to the United States with his two older sons in 1910, finally sending for the rest of his family in 1913. They settled in Portland, Oregon, though Jacob died only a few months after the family's arrival, requiring them to earn a living in their new country though they only spoke Hebrew and Russian. Rothko was forced to learn English and go to work when he was very young, resulting in a lingering sense of bitterness over his lost childhood. He graduated early from Lincoln High School, showing more interest in music than visual art. He was awarded a scholarship to Yale University, but soon found the environment at Yale conservative and exclusionary; he left without graduating in 1923.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="img" alt="Mark Rothko Biography" show="0">/images20/photo/rothko_3.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">After leaving Yale, Rothko made his way to New York City, as he put it, "to bum about and starve a bit." Over the next few years, he took odd jobs while enrolled in &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-weber_max"&gt;Max Weber's&lt;/span&gt; still life and figure drawing classes at the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-art_students_league"&gt;Art Students League&lt;/span&gt;, which constituted his only artistic training. Rothko's early paintings were mostly portraits, nudes, and urban scenes. After a brief stint in the theatre on a return visit to Portland, Rothko was chosen to participate in a 1928 group show with Lou Harris and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-avery_milton"&gt;Milton Avery&lt;/span&gt; at the Opportunity Gallery. This was a coup for a young immigrant who had dropped out of college and had only begun painting three years earlier.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="p">By the mid-1930s, the effects of the Great Depression were being felt throughout American society, and Rothko had become concerned with the social and political implications of mass unemployment. This encouraged him to attend meetings of the leftist Artists' Union. Here, amongst other issues, he and many other artists fought for a municipal gallery, which was eventually granted. Working in the Easel Division of the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-federal_art_project_of_the_works_progress_administration"&gt;Works Progress Administration&lt;/span&gt;, Rothko met many other artists, yet he felt most at ease with a group that consisted mainly of other Russian Jewish painters. This group, which included such figures as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-gottlieb_adolph"&gt;Adolph Gottlieb&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-solman_joseph"&gt;Joseph Solman&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-graham_john"&gt;John Graham&lt;/span&gt;, showed together at Gallery Secession in 1934, and became known as "The Ten". In 1936, &lt;i&gt;The Ten: Whitney Dissenters&lt;/i&gt; showed at the Mercury Galleries, opening just three days after the Whitney show they were protesting.</p>
          <p type="p">His painting in the 1930s, influenced by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-expressionism"&gt;Expressionism&lt;/span&gt;, was typified by claustrophobic, urban scenes rendered often in acidic colors (such as Entrance to Subway (1938)). However, in the 1940s, he began to be influenced by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealism&lt;/span&gt;, and abandoned Expressionism for more abstract imagery which spliced human, plant and animal forms. These he likened to archaic symbols, which he felt might transmit the emotions locked in ancient myths. Rothko came to see mankind as locked in a mythic struggle with his free will and nature. In 1939, he briefly stopped painting altogether to read mythology and philosophy, finding particular resonance in &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-nietzsche_friedrich"&gt;Nietzsche's&lt;/span&gt; &lt;i&gt;Birth of Tragedy&lt;/i&gt;. He ceased to be interested in representational likeness and became fascinated with the articulation of interior expression.</p>
          <p type="p">Throughout this time Rothko's personal life was shadowed by his severe depression, and likely an undiagnosed bipolar disorder. In 1932, he married jewelery designer Edith Sachar, but divorced her in 1945 to marry Mary Alice Beistel, with whom he would have two children.</p>
          <p type="p">While Rothko tends to be grouped with &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-newman_barnett"&gt;Newman&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-still_clyfford"&gt;Still&lt;/span&gt; as one of the three chief inspirers of Color Field Painting, Rothko's works saw many abrupt and clearly defined stylistic shifts. The decisive shift came in the late 1940s, when he began creating the prototypes for his best-known works. They have since come to be called his "multi-forms": figures are banished entirely, and the compositions are dominated by multiple soft-edged blocks of colors which seem to float in space. Rothko wanted to remove all obstacles between the painter, the painting and the viewer. The method he settled on used shimmering color to swamp the viewer's visual field. His paintings were meant to entirely envelope the viewer and raise the viewer up and out of the mechanized, commercial society over which artists like Rothko despaired. In 1949, Rothko radically reduced the number of forms in his pictures, and grew them such that they filled out the canvas, hovering on fields of stained color that are only visible at their borders. These, his best known works, have come to be called his "sectionals", and Rothko felt they better met his desire to create universal symbols of human yearning. His paintings were not self-expressions, he claimed, but statements about the condition of man.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Mark Rothko Painting" show="0">/images20/photo/rothko_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Rothko would continue to work on the "sectionals" until the end of his life. They are considered to be rather enigmatic, as they are formally at odds with their intent. Rothko himself stated that his style changes were motivated by the growing clarification of his content. The all-over compositions, the blurred boundaries, the continuousness of color, and the wholeness of form were all elements of his development towards a transcendental experience of the sublime, Rothko's goal. "The progression of a painter's work, as it travels in time from point to point, will be toward clarity," he stated, "toward the elimination of all obstacles between the painter and the idea, and between the idea and the observer."</p>
          <p type="p">Rothko garnered many honors in the course of his career, including being invited to be one of the U.S. representatives at the Venice Biennale in 1958. Yet acclaim never seemed to sooth Rothko's embattled spirit, and he came to be known as an abrasive and combative character. When he was given an award by the Guggenheim Foundation, he refused it as a protest against the idea that art should be competitive. He was always confident and forthright in his beliefs: "I am not an Abstractionist," he once said. He distanced himself from the classification of his work as "non-objective color-filled painting." Instead he stressed that his paintings were based on human emotions of "tragedy, ecstasy, doom." He claimed that art was not about the perception of formal relationships, but was understandable in terms of human life. He also denied being a colorist - despite the fact that color was of primary importance to his paintings.</p>
          <p type="p">Rothko often stood up for his beliefs, even if it cost him dearly. In what was surely a self-defeating act of retaliation, he refused a 1953 offer by the Whitney to purchase two of his paintings because of, "a deep sense of responsibility for the life my pictures will lead out in the world." Another pivotal project which would end unhappily was the series of murals he completed for the Seagram Building in 1958. Initially, the idea of incorporating his work within an architectural environment appealed to him, since he had great admiration for the chapels of Michelangelo and Vasari. He spent two years making three series of paintings for this building, but was not pleased with the first two sets; then he became dissatisfied with the idea that his paintings were to be hung in the opulent Four Seasons restaurant. Characteristically, Rothko's social ideals led him to quit the commission, as he could not reconcile his personal vision or his integrity as an artist with the ostentatious environment.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Period">
          <p type="img" alt="Mark Rothko Portrait" show="0">/images20/photo/rothko_6.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">In 1964, Rothko received a large commission from major Houston art collectors and philanthropists, John and Dominique de Menil. He was to create large wall murals for a non-denominational chapel they were sponsoring on the campus of St. Thomas Catholic University where Dominique was the head of the Art Department. He generated fourteen paintings while working closely with a series of architects to construct a meditative environment with a dark palette. The Rothko Chapel has since been the setting for international meetings of some of the world's great religious leaders, like the Dalai Lama.</p>
          <p type="p">In 1968, Rothko suffered an aortic aneurysm and spent three weeks in a hospital. This brush with death would shadow him for the rest of his life. He became resentful that his work was not being paid the proper respect and reverence he felt it deserved. He also began to worry that his art would have no major legacy, and this led him to work on his last major series, &lt;i&gt;Black on Grays&lt;/i&gt; , which included twenty-five canvases and marked a clear deviation from his previous work.</p>
          <p type="p">However, work failed to buoy up his spirits, and at the age of 66, Rothko committed suicide by taking an overdose of anti-depressants and slashing his arms with a razor blade. On the morning of February 25, 1970, his assistant, Oliver Steindecker, arrived at the East 69&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; Street studio to find him on the floor of the bathroom, covered in blood. Many of his friends were not entirely surprised that he took his own life, saying that he had lost his passion and inspiration. Some suggested that like others who had died before of an internal struggle, such as Arshile Gorky, Rothko had submitted to the tortured artist's ritual of self-annihilation.</p>
          <p type="p">In the aftermath of his death, three of his best friends were appointed trustees of his estate, and they secretly transferred control of some eight-hundred paintings to the Marlborough Gallery, which had been representing Rothko for several years, at a fraction of their market value. Rothko's daughter, Kate, took the men and the gallery to court in what became a notoriously messy and protracted dispute. During the lengthy court battle, the sometimes illegal and unethical dealings of the art world were publicly exposed for the first time. &lt;i&gt;Time&lt;/i&gt; critic &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-hughes_robert"&gt;Robert Hughes&lt;/span&gt; cited the "Rothko case" as what essentially brought about what he called the "death of Abstract Expressionism". Ultimately, the Rothko children won the case and received half of the estate. The Rothko Foundation then donated the rest of the works to museums in the United States and abroad.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="img" alt="Mark Rothko Photo with Cigarette" show="0">/images20/photo/rothko_10.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Painting consumed Rothko's life, and although he did not receive the attention he felt his work deserved in his own lifetime, his fame has increased dramatically in the years following his death. At odds with the more formally rigorous artists among the Abstract Expressionists, Rothko nevertheless explored the compositional potential of color and form on the human psyche. To stand in front of a Rothko is to be in the presence of the pulsing vibrancy of his enormous canvases; it is to feel, if only momentarily, something of the sublime spirituality he relentlessly sought to evoke. Rigidly uncompromising, Rothko refused to bend to the more distasteful aspects of the art world, a position upheld by his children who did nothing less than alter the entire state of the art market in their fierce protection of his life and work.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section title="Writings and Ideas">
        <subsection title="Introduction">
          <p type="p">Nietzsche, myth, and Jewish and social revolutionary thought were all important influences on Rothko's life and art. He once wrote to &lt;i&gt;The New York Times&lt;/i&gt; saying he would not defend his pictures, "because they defend themselves." Yet he was always a vocal advocate for artists, writing many reviews as well as essays on the complexities of the art world. Around 1941, probably during his yearlong hiatus from painting, Rothko wrote the manuscript for a book which was to be called &lt;i&gt;The Artist's Reality&lt;/i&gt;. However, it was never published in his lifetime, being hidden away in a manila folder labeled "miscellaneous papers" for over fifty years. It was discovered by his children in a warehouse and has since been edited by his son, Christopher, and was published by Yale University Press in 2006. These writings discuss Rothko's ideas about Modern art, myth, beauty, the nature of American art, and the challenges of being an artist in his society. The book is most unique in that it never references Rothko's own work, but speaks from the point of view of the artist in general. While his political leanings were clearly Leftist, he maintained a highly subjective approach to theory.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="On Being an Artist">
          <p type="p">In &lt;i&gt;The Artist's Reality&lt;/i&gt;, Rothko described the perception of artists in society and how they have fostered myths of creativity into reality based on their own personal fantasy lives. He discussed the ways in which authority in its various forms had made the rules that artists must live by and that the market was the latest dictator of these rules. At the time of this writing, WWII was beginning in Europe and anxieties over conformity and tyranny gave Rothko's writing a constant sense of disquiet.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="On Freedom">
          <p type="img" alt="Self-portrait, 1936" show="0">/images20/photo/rothko_9.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Above all, Rothko championed the freedom of the artist. The politics and poetics of Rothko's life were inseparable and his art constitutes the strongest evidence of this. As he declared in the year of his suicide, "I am still an anarchist!" Critic &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-ashton_dore"&gt;Dore Ashton&lt;/span&gt; wrote that Rothko did not sit easily with the world, that he was always searching for an escape. Viewed in the light of his suicide, many have read his paintings as windows through which Rothko sought to transcend a world in which he could not find comfort.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="On Interpretation of his Work">
          <p type="p">Throughout his writings, Rothko insisted that his work was meant to be viewed closely and intimately, not observed from a safe, sterile distance. For those who find Rothko's paintings overwhelming, it is perhaps comforting to know that he intended to communicate with his audience, not to intimidate. "I realize that historically the function of painting large pictures is something very grandiose and pompous," he wrote in 1951. "The reason I paint them however. . . is precisely because I want to be intimate and human."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="On Critics">
          <p type="p">Most critics interpreted Rothko's work in formalist terms, in direct opposition to the intention of the artist to convey grand spiritual drama. Consequently, perhaps, he had little patience for most professional writers on his work, saying, "I hate and distrust all art historians, experts and critics. They are all parasites, feeding on the body of art. Their work is not only useless but misleading. They can say nothing worth listening to about art or the artist."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Greenberg on Rothko">
          <p type="p">&lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-greenberg_clement"&gt;Clement Greenberg&lt;/span&gt; wrote little about Rothko's work. They met in 1943, and Greenberg was not greatly impressed by him. "We talked," Greenberg recalled, "and I found Rothko sympathetic, but I also found him very square. Later he got pompous. But he always stayed a little square." Greenberg's &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-formalism"&gt;formalism&lt;/span&gt; encouraged him to talk of Rothko's work in terms of "the rectilinear," "dividing lines," and, above all, "color" (see his essay "'American-Type' Painting" (1955)).</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Rosenberg on Rothko">
          <p type="p">&lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-rosenberg_harold"&gt;Harold Rosenberg&lt;/span&gt;, whose criticism had been shaped more by Existentialism than Greenberg's formalism, was in rare agreement with his rival concerning Rothko. Writing in March 1978 in his column "The Art World," for the &lt;i&gt;New Yorker&lt;/i&gt;, Rosenberg said, "Rothko had reduced painting to volume, tone, and color, with color as the vital element." The "three or four horizontal blocks of color" that Rothko sustained for twenty years comprised, he wrote, "the substance of his emotional life.. the exhilarated tragic experience.. the only source book of art."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Porter on Rothko">
          <p type="p">In his letter to the &lt;i&gt;Parisian Review&lt;/i&gt; in 1955, artist and critic &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-porter_fairfield"&gt;Fairfield Porter&lt;/span&gt; responded to Greenberg's assessment of Rothko in "'American-Type' Painting." Greenberg had asserted that Rothko's "opposition of pure color" was reminiscent of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-matisse_henri"&gt;Matisse&lt;/span&gt;, but Porter disagreed, noting that Rothko's work was not as balanced as Matisse's in terms of proportion and composition, and that his use of symbolic color was not as sensitive.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Letter to the Editor by Rothko and Gottlieb">
          <p type="p">There are several drafts of this letter to the editor, published June 13, 1943, in which Rothko and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-gottlieb_adolph"&gt;Gottlieb&lt;/span&gt; respond to the &lt;i&gt;Times&lt;/i&gt; art review by Edward Alden Jewell of their work at an exhibition at the Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors. Significantly, in drafts five and six, they list their beliefs about modern art: "We believe our pictures demonstrate our aesthetic beliefs.. to us, art is an adventure into a world unknown, which can only be explored by those willing to take risks.. this world is fancy-free and violently opposed to common sense.. it is our function as artists to make the spectator see the world our way- not his way.. We favor the simple expression of complex thought.. We are for flat forms because they destroy illusion and reveal truth.. it is a widely accepted notion among painters that it does not matter what one paints as long as it is well painted.. There is no such thing as a good painting about nothing. We assert that subject is crucial and only that subject matter is valid if it is tragic and timeless."</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Rothko and Gottlieb in Conversation">
          <p type="p">In 1943, Rothko and Adolph Gottlieb took part in a radio broadcast in which they answered questions put to them in a letter; their responses covered their ideas about portraiture, mythology, abstraction, and subject matter. During the discussion, Rothko also talked about his belief in a collective psychology, based in antiquity and mythology. Myths explored the fundamentals of human experience, he believed, "If [the] titles [of my paintings] recall the known myths of antiquity.. [I] have used them because they are the eternal symbols upon which we must fall back to express basic psychological ideas. They are the symbols of man's primitive fears and motivations, no matter in which land or what time, changing only in detail but never in substance.. and modern psychology finds them persisting still in our dreams, our vernacular, and our art, for all the changes in the outward conditions of life."</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="miro_joan">The Beautiful Bird Revealing the Unknown to a Pair of Lovers (1941)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="de_kooning_willem">July 4th (1957)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="gottlieb_adolph">Blues (1962)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>picasso_pablo</entity>
        <entity>cezanne_paul</entity>
        <entity>chagall_marc</entity>
        <entity>miro_joan</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>de_kooning_willem</entity>
        <entity>gottlieb_adolph</entity>
        <entity>
					solman_joseph
				</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>impressionism</entity>
        <entity>fauvism</entity>
        <entity>expressionism</entity>
        <entity>cubism</entity>
        <entity>surrealism</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>newman_barnett</entity>
        <entity>still_clyfford</entity>
        <entity>louis_morris</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>ashton_dore</entity>
        <entity>antonioni_michelangelo</entity>
        <entity>avery_milton</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>abstract_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>color_field_painting</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Crucifixion</title>
      <year>1935</year>
      <materials>Oil on Canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				Rothko was among several artists invited by Joseph Brummer to exhibit in
				Paris at the Galerie Bonaparte in November 1936; &lt;i&gt;Crucifixion&lt;/i&gt; was one of the paintings included. French critic Waldemar George noted that Rothko's paintings revealed nostalgia for 14&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-century Italian art, and that they displayed "an authentic coloristic value." This painting has thematic ties to Renaissance religious painting, but it also carries references to Rembrandt's &lt;i&gt;Lamentation of
				the Dead Christ&lt;/i&gt; (1637): the two crosses in the extreme foreground; the third isolated in the back; and the figure groupings, all echo Rembrandt's picture. This work is signed Rothkowitz, as he did not
				officially become Rothko until 1940.
			</desc>
      <collection>Location Unknown</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Entrance to Subway</title>
      <year>1938</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				This early figurative work demonstrates Rothko's interest in contemporary urban life. The architectural features of the station are sketchily
				recreated, including the turnstiles and the "N" on the wall. Although the mood of the pictures is softened somewhat by the influence of Impressionism, it reflects many of the artist's feelings towards the modern
				city. New York City was thought to be soulless and inhuman, and something of that is conveyed here in the anonymous, barely rendered features of the figures.
			</desc>
      <collection>
				Kate Rothko Prizel
				Collection
			</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Oedipus</title>
      <year>1944</year>
      <materials>Oil on linen</materials>
      <desc>
				Greek mythology was an
				important theme of Rothko's work in the early 1940s. Oedipus, who is said to have solved of the riddle of the Sphinx, was his father's murderer and his mother's lover. His tale has inspired artists and psychologists
				alike. For Rothko, he embodied the victim of pride and passion, which the artist believed were at the center of man's destructive nature. As in other representational works of this time, Rothko has dismembered and
				then recombined his figures so intricately that they became a single mass of human conglomeration. In this way, Rothko sought to suggest how mankind is bound together by tragedy. The figures appear oddly huddled in
				the corner of a room with strange architecture. The blue and green zigzag pattern recurs in several of his mythological pictures. As Rothko said: "If our titles recall the known myths of antiquity, we have used them again because they are the eternal symbols upon which we must fall back to express basic psychological ideas.. …(they) express something real and existing in ourselves."
			</desc>
      <collection>Unknown</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Slow Swirl at the Edge of the Sea</title>
      <year>
				1944
			</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				&lt;i&gt;Slow Swirl at the Edge of the Sea&lt;/i&gt; is a representative example of Rothko's Surrealist period. The influence of Miro is
				particularly apparent, specifically in Miro's &lt;i&gt;The Family&lt;/i&gt;(1924). Rothko's all-over composition of muted colors, strange translucent figures, horizontal lines, angles, and swirls create a vibrant
				yet veiled picture of an obscure primeval landscape. Painted while courting Mary Beistel, who would become his second wife, this whimsical scene can also be interpreted as a romance within a mythical and magical
				world, where the figures are enjoying the ocean as a rose colored dawn is breaking on the horizon.
			</desc>
      <collection>The Museum of Modern Art, New York City</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>No. 9</title>
      <year>1947</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				Rothko showed eleven paintings at Betty Parsons Gallery in the spring of 1949; &lt;i&gt;No. 9&lt;/i&gt; was among
				them. Having left behind the figures and landscapes of his earlier work, the "multiforms", of which this is a typical example, featured blurred shapes created from layered washes of paint. The work anticipates
				Rothko's 1949 breakthrough to the so-called "sectionals". The warm reds, oranges and yellows of &lt;i&gt;No. 9&lt;/i&gt; are disrupted by the strange black mass coming in from the left as well as the brushy swirls
				of blue in the lower section. The blurred edges, separated color blocks, and beginnings of rectangular registers can be seen, as well as some experiment with size and scale. Far from being merely abstract forms,
				however, Rothko believed these motifs were objects imbued with his life force - "organisms..with the passion for self-expression."
			</desc>
      <collection>Dr. and Mrs. Jerome Dersh Collection</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Four Darks in Red</title>
      <year>1958</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				In 1969, Rothko exhibited ten
				paintings at the Sidney Janis Gallery; &lt;i&gt;Four Darks in Red&lt;/i&gt; were among those shown. With its dark, restricted palette, the picture exemplifies Rothko's late-period gravitation towards reds and
				browns. It established a prototype for the dark red/brown/black palette and horizontal composition that he would later use in the uninstalled Seagram Building paintings. Although the imagery of pictures like &lt;i
				&gt;Four Darks in Red&lt;/i&gt; seems far distant from that of &lt;i&gt;Slow Swirl at the Edge of the Sea&lt;/i&gt; (1944), Rothko believed that the rectangles merely offered a new way of representing the presences
				or spirits that he tried to capture in those earlier works. "It was not that the figure had been removed," he once said, "..but the symbols for the figures... These new shapes say.. what the figures said." In this
				way, Rothko imagined a kind of direct communion between himself and the viewer, one which might touch the viewer with a higher spirituality.
			</desc>
      <collection>Whitney Museum of American Art</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>The Rothko Chapel</title>
      <year>1965</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				Set on the campus of St. Thomas
				Catholic University, the Rothko chapel was funded by John and Dominique de Menil and contains fourteen Rothko mural paintings. There are three triptychs and five individual works. All of these paintings are in
				hues of dark purple, maroon and black and are of extremely large scale. Rothko worked closely with the architects, having almost complete control over the shape of the building and its meditative environment
				within. The darkness of the works can be seen as melancholic and expressive of Rothko's mood of his last years. He did not live to see the official opening of the Chapel.
			</desc>
      <collection>
				Houston, TX
			</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Untitled, Black on Gray</title>
      <year>1969</year>
      <materials>Acrylic on canvas</materials>
      <desc>
				Rothko
				invited many of the New York art world elite to his studio to view his latest, and what would be his last, series of paintings, the &lt;i&gt;Black on Grays&lt;/i&gt;. While the event was mainly shrouded in silence,
				it was thought by some that these were premonitions of his death. Others thought that with the prevalence of lunar images in popular culture that they were interpretations of moon landscapes, while others thought
				they were paintings of photographs taken at night. In general, they were not taken very seriously, which was devastating to Rothko, but also affirming, as he often felt that the interior world of his paintings were
				comprehensible to him alone. The &lt;i&gt;Black on Grays&lt;/i&gt; were painted directly on white canvas and lacked the usual underpainting which Rothko liked to "paint against." Working in two registers only, he
				severely restricted the colors and scaled down the canvas to a more approachable and intimate size. The extreme contrast of light and dark evokes a sadness that played out like a psychological drama, both mythic and
				tragic.
			</desc>
      <collection>Estate of Mark Rothko</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" is_recommended="false">
      <subcategory name="artist features" class="features">
        <entry>
          <title>Mark Rothko Achievement Overview</title>
          <link>/comparison-rothko-mark.htm</link>
          <info>Themes explained via The Art Story Image Comparison Tool</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Mark Rothko Jewish Art Overview</title>
          <link>/jewish-artist-rothko-mark.htm</link>
          <info>Overview of Rothko's achievements in Jewish Modern Art</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography and exhibitions" class="biography">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>About Rothko</title>
          <link>0306812649</link>
          <info>By Dore Ashton</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>
						Mark
						Rothko: A Biography
					</title>
          <link>0226074064</link>
          <info>By James E. B. Breslin</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Legacy Of Mark Rothko</title>
          <link>
						0306807254
					</link>
          <info>By Lee Seldes</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Mark Rothko, 1903-1970 : A Retrospective (1978)</title>
          <link>0810915871</link>
          <info>Guggenheim Exhibition Catalogue &lt;br/&gt;By Diane Waldman and Thomas M. Messer</info>
          <pdflink source="gugenheim">https://archive.org/stream/markrothko19031900roth#page/n0/mode/2up</pdflink>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by">
        <entry>
          <title>The Artist's Reality: Philosophies of Art</title>
          <link>
						0300115857
					</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Writings on Art</title>
          <link>0300114400</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="Paintings" class="artwork">
        <entry>
          <title>The Rothko Book: Tate Essential Artists Series</title>
          <link>
						1854375733
					</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>
						Mark Rothko: The
						Works
						on Paper
					</title>
          <link>0933920539</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Mark Rothko: The Works on Canvas</title>
          <link>
						0300074891
					</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Mark Rothko</title>
          <link>
						3775710272
					</link>
          <info>
						Edited by Jeffrey Weiss, Marjorie B. Cohn, Franz Meyer, Eliza E.
						Rathbone, Oliver Wick
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry>
          <title>National Gallery of Art, Washington DC</title>
          <link>https://www.nga.gov/collection/artist-info.1839.html</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Rothko Chapel</title>
          <link>http://www.rothkochapel.org/</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>
						Feeding Fury: How Rothko's Seagram Murals Found
						Their Way to London
					</title>
          <link>http://www.guardian.co.uk/culture/2002/dec/07/artsfeatures</link>
          <info>By Jonathin Jones&lt;br/&gt;The Guardian&lt;br/&gt;December, 2002</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Review of Mark Rothko Exhibition</title>
          <link>http://www.thecityreview.com/rothko.html</link>
          <info>
						By Carter B. Horsley
						&lt;br/&gt;
						The City Review
						&lt;br/&gt;
						1998
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips" />
      <subcategory name="videoclips" class="clips">
        <entry>
          <title>Mark Rothko at Tate Modern</title>
          <link>http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/video/2008/sep/26/rothko.tate</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>What Mark Rothko Thinks about Modern Art &amp; People</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EI29ye41gYs</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop">
        <entry>
          <title>
						Il
						deserto
						roso (1964)
					</title>
          <link>http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0058003</link>
          <info>
						Film directed by Michelangelo Antonioni, whose aesthetics were heavily influenced by Rothko's work
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Mark Rothko Song by Dar Williams</title>
          <link>http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01LYA7CHJ/</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item>305643</a_item>
      <a_image>http://imagecache6.allposters.com/LRG/7/783/DV9I000Z.jpg</a_image>
      <a_name>Orange and Yellow</a_name>
    </poster>
    <poster>
      <a_item>2107776</a_item>
      <a_image>http://imagecache6.allposters.com/SML/20/2056/9XR4D00Z.jpg</a_image>
      <a_name>No. 37 / No. 19 (Slate Blue and Brown on Plum), 1958</a_name>
    </poster>
    <poster>
      <a_item>1115561</a_item>
      <a_image>http://imagecache6.allposters.com/SML/11/1157/Y3BU000Z.jpg</a_image>
      <a_name>Blue, Green, and Brown</a_name>
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>