<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>seurat_georges</id>
    <name>Georges Seurat</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1874 - 1891</years>
    <description>Georges Seurat is the pioneer of technique of painting in softly flickering, small dots or strokes of color, called Pointillism.</description>
    <use_big_images>true</use_big_images>
    <highlight>2</highlight>
    <occupation>Draftsman and Painter</occupation>
    <nationality>French</nationality>
    <birthDate>December 2, 1859</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Paris, France</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>March 29, 1891</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>Paris, France</deathPlace>
    <big_bio_box_img>Detail of &lt;i&gt;Le Chahut&lt;/i&gt; (1889-90) by Georges Seurat</big_bio_box_img>
    <bio_highlight>“Some say they see poetry in my paintings; I see only science” was what Seurat said and his development as an artist was a similar progression away from the scenic and emotional, and into the calculated and analyzed.</bio_highlight>
    <pub_time>1/22/2012</pub_time>
    <hero>true</hero>
	<custom_logo>true</custom_logo>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>neo_impressionism</include>
    <include>post_impressionism</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>neo_impressionism</movement>
    <movement>post_impressionism</movement>
    <movement>realism</movement>
    <movement>les_nabis</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>pissarro_camille</artist>
    <artist>monet_claude</artist>
    <artist>degas_edgar</artist>
    <artist>signac_paul</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"Great things are done by a series of small things brought together."</q>
    <q>"Some say they see poetry in my paintings; I see only science."</q>
    <q>"Originality depends only on the character of the drawing and the vision peculiar to each artist."</q>
    <q>"Painting is the art of hollowing a surface."</q>
    <q>"Harmony is the analogy of contrary and similar elements of tone, of color, and of line, conditioned by the dominant key, and under the influence of a particular light, in gay, calm, or sad combinations."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="top">The Art Story Contributors</author>
  </authors>
  <editors>
    <editor link="duncan">Alexandra Duncan</editor>
  </editors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Georges Seurat is chiefly remembered as the pioneer of the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-neo_impressionism"&gt;Neo-Impressionist&lt;/span&gt; technique commonly known as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pointillism"&gt;Pointillism&lt;/span&gt;, or &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-divisionism"&gt;Divisionism&lt;/span&gt;, an approach associated with a softly flickering surface of small dots or strokes of color. His innovations derived from new quasi-scientific theories about color and expression, yet the graceful beauty of his work is explained by the influence of very different sources. Initially, he believed that great modern art would show contemporary life in ways similar to classical art, except that it would use technologically informed techniques. Later he grew more interested in Gothic art and popular posters, and the influence of these on his work make it some of the first modern art to make use of such unconventional sources for expression. His success quickly propelled him to the forefront of the Parisian &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-avant_garde"&gt;avant-garde&lt;/span&gt;. His triumph was short-lived, as after barely a decade of mature work he died at the age of only 31. But his innovations would be highly influential, shaping the work of artists as diverse as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-van_gogh_vincent"&gt;Vincent Van Gogh&lt;/span&gt; and the Italian &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-futurism"&gt;Futurists&lt;/span&gt;, while pictures like &lt;i&gt;Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grand Jatte&lt;/i&gt; (1884) have since become widely popular icons.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Seurat was inspired by a desire to abandon &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-impressionism"&gt;Impressionism's&lt;/span&gt; preoccupation with the fleeting moment, and instead to render what he regarded as the essential and unchanging in life. Nevertheless, he borrowed many of his approaches from Impressionism, from his love of modern subject matter and scenes of urban leisure, to his desire to avoid depicting only the 'local', or apparent, color of depicted objects, and instead to try to capture all the colors that interacted to produce their appearance.</idea>
      <idea>Seurat was fascinated by a range of scientific ideas about color, form and expression. He believed that lines tending in certain directions, and colors of a particular warmth or coolness, could have particular expressive effects. He also pursued the discovery that contrasting or complementary colors can optically mix to yield far more vivid tones that can be achieved by mixing paint alone. He called the technique he developed 'chromo-luminism', though it is better known as &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-divisionism"&gt;Divisionism&lt;/span&gt; (after the method of separating local color into separate dots), or &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pointillism"&gt;Pointillism&lt;/span&gt; (after the tiny strokes of paint that were crucial to achieve the flickering effects of his surfaces).</idea>
      <idea>Although radical in his techniques, Seurat's initial instincts were conservative and classical when it came to style. He saw himself in the tradition of great &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-the_salon"&gt;Salon&lt;/span&gt; painters, and thought of the figures in his major pictures almost as if they were figures in monumental classical reliefs, though the subject matter - the different urban leisure pursuits of the bourgeois and the working class - was fully modern, and typically Impressionist.</idea>
      <idea>In Seurat's later work he left behind the calm, stately classicism of early pictures like &lt;i&gt;Bathers at Asnières&lt;/i&gt;, and pioneered a more dynamic and stylized approach that was influenced by sources such as caricatures and popular posters. These brought a powerful new expressiveness to his work, and, much later, led him to be acclaimed by the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-surrealism"&gt;Surrealists&lt;/span&gt; as an eccentric and a maverick.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Georges Seurat was born in Paris December 2, 1859, the youngest of three children. His father, Chrysostome-Antoine Seurat, was a bailiff; his mother, Ernestine Faivre, came from a prosperous family that had produced several sculptors. Seurat's eccentric father had already retired with a small fortune by the time Seurat was born, and he spent most of his time in Le Raincy, some 12 kilometers from the comfortable family home in Paris. The young Seurat lived with his mother, his brother Émile, and his sister Marie-Berthe.</p>
          <p type="p">In 1870 the family temporarily relocated to Fontainebleau, where they stayed during the Franco-Prussian War and the subsequent Paris Commune rebellion. Seurat began to take a serious interest in art as a boy and was encouraged by informal lessons from his maternal uncle, Paul Haumonté, a textile dealer and amateur painter.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="p">Seurat's formal training began around 1875, when he entered the local municipal art school under the sculptor Justin Lequien. There, he made a friend of Edmond Aman-Jean (1858-1935) and together they entered the École des Beaux-Arts run by Henri Lehmann, a disciple of the Neo-Classical painter &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-ingres_jean_auguste_dominique"&gt;Jean-Auguste-Dominique Ingres&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
          <p type="p">Seurat attended the Academy from February 1878 until November 1879. The curriculum placed particular emphasis on drawing and composition, and most of Seurat's time was spent sketching from plaster casts and live models.</p>
          <p type="p">Seurat spent his free time conducting his own artistic studies and frequently visited museums and libraries throughout Paris. He also sought instruction from the painter &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-puvis_de_chavannes_pierre"&gt;Pierre Puvis de Chavannes&lt;/span&gt;, whose specialty was large-scale classical, allegorical scenes. Seurat's sketches dating to 1874 include copies of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-holbein_hans_the_younger"&gt;Holbein's&lt;/span&gt; drawings, a sketch of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-poussin_nicolas"&gt;Nicolas Poussin's&lt;/span&gt; hand from the acclaimed self-portrait in the Louvre, and figures from drawings by &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-raphael"&gt;Raphael&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
          <p type="p">Charles Blanc's &lt;i&gt;The Grammar of Painting and Engraving&lt;/i&gt; (1867) and Michel-Eugène Chevreul's &lt;i&gt;The Principles of Harmony and Contrast of Colors&lt;/i&gt; (1839) introduced Seurat to color theories and the science of optics that became central to his thinking and practice as a painter. Chevreul's discovery that by juxtaposing complementary colors one could produce the impression of another color became one of the bases for Seurat's &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-divisionism"&gt;Divisionist&lt;/span&gt; technique.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Georges Seurat Biography" show="1">/images20/photo/seurat_georges_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">In April 1879, Seurat visited the Fourth Impressionist exhibition. This was the first time he had seen their paintings and the work of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-monet_claude"&gt;Claude Monet&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pissarro_camille"&gt;Camille Pissarro&lt;/span&gt;, artists liberated from the rigidities of academic rules, greatly influenced his later experimentation. But in November his military service started in Brest, where he devoted all his spare time to reading and filling sketchbooks with studies of fellow recruits, seascapes, and street scenes.</p>
          <p type="p">In the following years, Seurat extended his understanding of color theory and the effects of color on the human eye. He also studied the brushwork of Romantic painter &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-delacroix_eugene"&gt;Eugène Delacroix&lt;/span&gt; and read Ogden N. Rood's &lt;i&gt;Modern Chromatics&lt;/i&gt; (1879), which proposed that artists should experiment with color contrast by juxtaposing small colored dots to see how they are blended by the eye.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="img" alt="An 1883 portrait of Seurat by French Ernest Laurent." show="1">/images20/photo/photo_seurat_georges_1.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Seurat began to apply his theoretical research to compositions executed between 1881 and 1884, culminating in his first major painting project, the &lt;i&gt;Bathers at Asnières&lt;/i&gt; (1884). This monumental canvas depicted a group of workers relaxing by the Seine and was based on numerous small oil sketches and figure studies. The final composition is an accomplished rendition of the light and atmosphere of high summer. It is largely rendered in a criss-cross brushstroke technique known as &lt;i&gt;balayé&lt;/i&gt; and was later re-touched by Seurat with dots of contrasting color in certain areas.</p>
          <p type="p">Seurat submitted &lt;i&gt;Bathers&lt;/i&gt; to the state-sponsored Salon in 1883, but the jury rejected it. Subsequently, Seurat and several other artists founded the Société des Artistes Indépendants, enabling him to exhibit &lt;i&gt;Bathers&lt;/i&gt; in June of 1884. There he met and befriended fellow artist &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-signac_paul"&gt;Paul Signac&lt;/span&gt; who was greatly influenced by Seurat's techniques.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Georges Seurat Photo" show="1">/images20/photo/seurat_georges_3.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">After the &lt;i&gt;Bathers&lt;/i&gt; Seurat began work on &lt;i&gt;Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grand Jatte&lt;/i&gt;, a mural-sized painting that took him two years to complete. Many times the artist visited La Grande Jatte, an island in the Seine located in the Parisian suburb of Neuilly, making drawings and more than thirty oil sketches to prepare for the final work. In the winter of 1885-86 he reworked the painting in the technique that he called "chromo-luminarism", also known as Divisionism or Pointillism. This technique uses dots of contrasting color that, when viewed at a distance, interact to create a luminous, shimmering effect. He also repainted sections of the &lt;i&gt;Bathers&lt;/i&gt; in the same style around 1887.</p>
          <p type="p">Seurat exhibited &lt;i&gt;La Grande Jatte&lt;/i&gt; at the Eighth Impressionist Exhibition in May 1886. Its visual effects of light and color, as well as its complex representation of different social classes established Seurat as the leader of a new &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-avant_garde"&gt;avant-garde&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Period">
          <p type="p">The exhibition of &lt;i&gt;La Grande Jatte&lt;/i&gt; in 1886 unexpectedly aroused interest in Seurat's work internationally. Soon after the exhibition, Seurat was mentioned in an avant-garde review and some of his paintings were shown by the renowned art dealer Paul Durant-Ruel in both Paris and New York City.</p>
          <p type="p">During this time he began associating with a very enclosed group of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-symbolism"&gt;Symbolist&lt;/span&gt; artists and writers based in Paris. His new associations troubled his friends Pissarro and Signac, who believed he was forsaking the pure study of color and light in favor of idealized subjects. Seurat's last major works depict Paris nightlife and all share a similar muted palette that differs greatly from the vibrancy of his earlier paintings.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="In the mid-1880s, Seurat’s divisionist/pointillist technique began to employ broader and more spaced-outs strokes and spots of color, lending the works a greater sense of lightness, as in L'échouage à Grandcamp (1885)." show="1">/images20/photo/photo_seurat_georges_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">Apart from a brief period of renewed military service in summer 1887, Seurat spent his summers on the Normandy coast, painting seaside scenes of Honfleur in 1886, Port-en-Bessin in 1888, Le Crotoy in 1889 and Gravelines in 1890. In winter he finished these paintings and produced large figure compositions. Although executed in his Pointillist style, the dots tended to be finer and more spaced out, giving the paintings a more spontaneous appearance.</p>
          <p type="p">In 1889, Seurat traveled to Belgium, where he exhibited at the Salon des Vingt (XX) in Brussels. After returning from this trip, he met Madeleine Knobloch, a 20-year-old model, and started secretly living with her. Knobloch gave birth to a son in February 1890, unbeknownst to his friends and family.</p>
          <p type="p">At his exhibition in the Salon des Indépendants the same year, Seurat showed his only known portrait of Madeleine Knobloch: &lt;i&gt;Young Woman Powdering Herself&lt;/i&gt;.</p>
          <p type="p">Madeleine Knobloch was pregnant again at the beginning of 1891, while Seurat was at work painting &lt;i&gt;The Circus&lt;/i&gt;. This painting would remain unfinished. On March 26, Seurat fell suddenly ill with a fever and died three days later. His son died of a similar illness in 2 weeks, and was buried alongside Seurat at the Père-Lachaise cemetery in Paris.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">Seurat was only 31 when he died, yet he left behind an influential body of work, comprising seven monumental paintings, hundreds of drawings and sketches, and around 40 smaller-scale paintings and sketches. Although his &lt;i&gt;oeuvre&lt;/i&gt; is relatively small in quantity, it had a lasting impact. He was among the first artists to make a systematic and devoted use of color theory, and his technical innovations influenced many of his peers. When the term Neo-Impressionism was coined by art critic Félix Fénéon in 1886, it was to describe Seurat, Signac, and Pissarro's new style of painting and their rejection of the spontaneity of Impressionism.</p>
          <p type="p">Poised between &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-impressionism"&gt;Impressionism&lt;/span&gt; in the 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-fauvism"&gt;Fauvism&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-cubism"&gt;Cubism&lt;/span&gt; in the early-20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-neo_impressionism"&gt;Neo-Impressionism&lt;/span&gt; brought with it a new awareness of the surface qualities of painting, and of decorative effects, thereby contributing to the development of abstraction.</p>
          <p type="p">Seurat is often cited by artists with an interest in the visual effects of color, form, and light. Painter &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-riley_bridget"&gt;Bridget Riley&lt;/span&gt; has credited him with influencing her particular brand of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-op_art"&gt;Op art&lt;/span&gt;.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="pissarro_camille">Hay Harvest at Eragny (1887)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="monet_claude">Boulevard des Capucines (1873)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="manet_edouard">A Bar at the Folies-Bergere (1881-82)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>puvis_de_chavannes_pierre</entity>
        <entity>ingres_jean_auguste_dominique</entity>
        <entity>poussin_nicolas</entity>
        <entity>delacroix_eugene</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>feneon_felix</entity>
        <entity>pissarro_camille</entity>
        <entity>monet_claude</entity>
        <entity>manet_edouard</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>impressionism</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>toulouse_lautrec_henri</entity>
        <entity>van_gogh_vincent</entity>
        <entity>gauguin_paul</entity>
        <entity>riley_bridget</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>degas_edgar</entity>
        <entity>signac_paul</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>post_impressionism</entity>
        <entity>pointillism</entity>
        <entity>op_art</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Bathers at Asnières</title>
      <year>1884</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Seurat's first important canvas, the &lt;i&gt;Bathers&lt;/i&gt; is his initial attempt at reconciling classicism with modern, quasi-scientific approaches to color and form. It depicts an area on the Seine near Paris, close to the factories of Clichy that one can see in the distance. Seurat's palette is somewhat Impressionist in its brightness, yet his meticulous approach is far removed from that style's love of expressing the momentary. The scene's intermingling of shades also demonstrates Seurat's interest in Eugene Delacroix's handling of shades of a single hue. And the working-class figures that populate this scene mark a sharp contrast with the leisured bourgeois types depicted by artists such as Monet and Renoir in the 1870s.</desc>
      <collection>The Art Institute of Chicago</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grand Jatte</title>
      <year>1884-86</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Seurat's &lt;i&gt;Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grand Jatte&lt;/i&gt; was one of the stand-out works in the eighth and last Impressionist exhibition, in 1884, and after it was shown later that year, at the Sociéte des Artistes Indépendents, it encouraged critic Félix Fénéon to invent the name 'Neo-Impressionism.' The picture took Seurat two years to complete and he spent much of this time sketching in the park in preparation. It was to become the most famous picture of the 1880s. Once again, as in &lt;i&gt;Bathers&lt;/i&gt;, the scale of the picture is equal to the dimensions and ambition of major Salon pictures. The site - again situated on the Seine in northwest Paris - is also close by. And Seurat's technique was similar, employing tiny juxtaposed dots of multi-colored paint that allow the viewer's eye to blend colors optically, rather than having the colors blended on the canvas or pre-blended as a material pigment. The artist said that his ambition was to "make modern people in their essential traits move about as they do on [ancient Greek] friezes and place them on canvases organized by harmonies." But the classicism of the &lt;i&gt;Bathers&lt;/i&gt; is gone from &lt;i&gt;La Grand Jatte&lt;/i&gt;; instead the scene has a busy energy, and, as critics have often noted, some of the figures are depicted at discordant scales. It marked the beginning of a new primitivism in Seurat's work that was inspired in part by popular art.</desc>
      <collection>The Art Institute of Chicago</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>La Seine à la Grande-Jatte</title>
      <year>1888</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;La Seine à la Grande-Jatte&lt;/i&gt; of 1888 shows the artist returning to the site of his most famous painting - &lt;i&gt;A Sunday on La Grande Jatte&lt;/i&gt; painted two years prior. This later composition demonstrates Seurat's continued interest in form and perspective, but reveals a much softer and more relaxed technique than &lt;i&gt;La Grande Jatte&lt;/i&gt;. The soft atmosphere is made up of a myriad of colored dots that mix optically to mimic the effects of a luminous summer day.</desc>
      <collection>Royal Museums of Fine Arts of Belgium, Brussels</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Young Woman Powdering Herself</title>
      <year>1888-90</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Young Woman Powdering Herself&lt;/i&gt; is a portrait of Seurat's mistress Madeleine Knobloch. It is an adoring likeness that jokingly contrasts the classical monumentality of the figure against the flimsy Rococo frivolity of the setting. It is also strongly marked by Seurat's increasing interest in caricature and popular art, sources which lent a new expressiveness to his work which accorded with the growing contemporary interest in Symbolism. Knobloch was a working-class woman with whom Seurat maintained a long-term secret relationship, keeping her separate not only from his bourgeois family but also from his bohemian friends. When the painting was shown in 1890, her identity remained concealed. Knobloch was given some of Seurat's paintings as an inheritance but she cut off all communication with his family after his death.</desc>
      <collection>The Courtauld Gallery, London</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Circus Sideshow</title>
      <year>1887-88</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Circus Sideshow&lt;/i&gt; is considered one of Seurat's major figure paintings. Yet it is much more condensed than his other mural-size paintings. This was Seurat's first nocturnal painting and it debuted at the 1888 Salon des Indépendants in Paris. It depicts a ringmaster and musicians under twinkling gaslight who are attracting a crowd of potential ticket buyers. The composition was drawn from on-site sketches he made in the spring of 1887, when Frenand Corvi's traveling circus performed in Paris (it appeared regularly in Paris between the 1870s and the First World War). Though Seurat frequently attended circus-like events in his leisure time, this painting was the first important picture Seurat dedicated to a scene of popular entertainment. The pattern of circles, ovals, and rectangles in the background has attracted much notice from critics, as many of the forms are hard to explain in terms of the structure of the setting. It has been argued that they derive from Seurat's understanding of various contemporary theories of expression, which advocated the use of particular forms and colors to convey particular types of emotion.</desc>
      <collection>The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>The Circus</title>
      <year>1890-91</year>
      <materials>Oil on canvas</materials>
      <desc>Seurat's early paintings often feature a remarkable stillness, even with complex figure compositions, but &lt;i&gt;The Circus&lt;/i&gt; features a scene of dynamic movement, and is typical of his late style. The scene is borrowed from an anonymous poster for the Nouveau Cirque, printed in 1888, although the horse and bareback rider have been reversed. The figure in the first row of seats, with a silk hat and a lock of hair visible under it, is the painter Charles Angrand, a friend of Seurat's. This painting was Seurat's last, and was left unfinished when he died suddenly in March of 1891. It was sold shortly thereafter to his friend Paul Signac.</desc>
      <collection>Musée d'Orsay, Paris</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" />
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry>
          <title>Seurat: A Biography</title>
          <link>0810981246</link>
          <info>By John Rewald</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Georges Seurat, 1859-1891: The Master of Pointillism (Basic Art)</title>
          <link>3822858633</link>
          <info>By Hajo Duchting</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Seurat (World of Art)</title>
          <link>0500200327</link>
          <info>By John Russell</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="written by artist" class="written-by" />
      <subcategory name="artworks" class="artwork">
        <entry>
          <title>Georges Seurat (Rizzoli Art Series)</title>
          <link>084781520X</link>
          <info>By Norma Broude</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Seurat and the Making of 'La Grande Jatte'</title>
          <link>0520242114</link>
          <info>By Robert L. Herbert, Neil Harris</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Georges Seurat 1859-1891</title>
          <link>0810964104</link>
          <info>By Robert L. Herbert</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Georges Seurat: The Drawings</title>
          <link>0870707175</link>
          <info>By Jodi Hauptman, Karl Buchberg, Hubert Damisch, Bridget Riley, Richard Shiff, and Richard Thomson</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Georges Seurat: The Art of Vision</title>
          <link>0300208359</link>
          <info>By Michelle Foa</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Masters of Art: Seurat</title>
          <link>0810915197</link>
          <info>By Pierre Courthion</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Seurat's Circus Sideshow</title>
          <link>1588396150</link>
          <info>By Richard Thomson</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Ways of Pointillism: Seurat, Signac, Van Gogh</title>
          <link>3777426342</link>
          <info>By Klaus Albrecht Schröder </info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Science of Art: Optical Themes in Western Art from Brunelleschi to Seurat</title>
          <link>0300052413</link>
          <info>By Martin Kemp</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Metropolitan Museum of Art (thematic section)</title>
          <link>http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/seni/hd_seni.htm</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Art Institute of Chicago (interpretative resources)</title>
          <link>http://www.artic.edu/aic/collections/artwork/27992</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Georges Seurat: The Complete Works</title>
          <link>http://www.georgesseurat.org/</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>Seurat, Drawing His Way to the Grande Jatte</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2007/10/26/arts/design/26seur.html</link>
          <info>
						By Roberta Smith
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br&gt;
						October 26, 2007
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>How Seurat Worked Up To Sunday</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/20/arts/art-review-how-seurat-worked-up-to-sunday.html?ref=georges_seurat</link>
          <info>
						By Holland Carter
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br&gt;
						August 20, 2004
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>The Death of Georges Seurat: Neo-Impressionism and the Fate of the Avant-Garde in 1891</title>
          <link>https://journals.ub.uni-heidelberg.de/index.php/rihajournal/article/view/69907</link>
          <info>
				By Marnin Young 
				&lt;br&gt;
				Journal of the International Association of Research Institutes in the History of Art 
				&lt;br&gt;
				2012
			</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Story Behind Seurat’s Pointillist Masterpiece, ‘A Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte’</title>
          <link>https://mymodernmet.com/georges-seurat-a-sunday-afternoon-on-the-island-of-la-grande-jatte/</link>
          <info>
				By Kelly Richman-Abdou
				&lt;br&gt;
				MyModernMet 
				&lt;br&gt;
				July 21, 2019
			</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips" />
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>The Story behind Great Paintings: Georges Seurat, Sunday on the Grande Jatte - Art History School</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=omHaPvcse-s</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Seurat: Courtauld's Impressionists - National Gallery</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jKNpN3F36ag</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Seurat Biography from Goodbye-Art Academy - PhilInTheCircle</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BOdmp7_BUhY</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Seurat, A Sunday on La Grande Jatte - Smarthistory</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wNB9Vm6MoDQ</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Seurat, Bathers at Asnières</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9bs1iQ14LJY</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Art Talk on Georges Seurat’s Models - Barnes Foundation</title>
          <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yVJahS23rBM</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips">
        <entry>
          <title>Georges Seurat: Point Counterpoint</title>
          <link>http://www.amazon.com/Georges-Seurat-Point-Counterpoint-VHS/dp/6303833373</link>
          <info>A historical/biographical film on Seurat and his study of Pointillism</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Sunday in the Park with George - 1984</title>
          <link>http://www.amazon.com/Sunday-Park-George-Mandy-Patinkin/dp/630530209X</link>
          <info> Musical by Steven Sondheim&lt;br&gt;Inspired by the life of the artist</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
  </sidebar>
</data>