<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<data>
  <main>
    <id>smithson_robert</id>
    <name>Robert Smithson</name>
    <type>artist</type>
    <active_section>artists</active_section>
    <years>1959 - 1973</years>
    <description>Robert Smithson art often dealt with the purpose art might have in the landscape, and ultimately, the eventual exhaustion and collapse of any given system.</description>
    <use_big_images>copyrighted</use_big_images>
    <highlight>5</highlight>
    <occupation>Sculptor and Writer</occupation>
    <nationality>American</nationality>
    <birthDate>January 2, 1938</birthDate>
    <birthPlace>Passaic, New Jersey</birthPlace>
    <deathDate>July 20, 1973</deathDate>
    <deathPlace>Amarillo, Texas</deathPlace>
    <art_type>Earth Art</art_type>
    <pub_time>8/1/2012</pub_time>
  </main>
  <includes>
    <include>earth_art</include>
    <include>post_minimalism</include>
    <include>conceptual_art</include>
  </includes>
  <similar_movements>
    <movement>earth_art</movement>
    <movement>post_minimalism</movement>
    <movement>conceptual_art</movement>
    <movement>postmodernism</movement>
  </similar_movements>
  <similar_artists>
    <artist>oldenburg_claes</artist>
    <artist>morris_robert</artist>
    <artist>holt_nancy</artist>
    <artist>serra_richard</artist>
  </similar_artists>
  <quotes>
    <q main="true">"I am for an art that takes into account the direct effect of the elements as they exist from day to day apart from representation."</q>
    <q>"By excluding technological processes from the making of art, we begin to discover other processes of a more fundamental order."</q>
    <q>"Deliverance from the confines of the studio frees the artist to a degree from the snares of craft and the bondage of creativity. Such a     <q>"Painting, sculpture and architecture are finished, but the art habit continues."</q>
condition exists without any appeal to 'nature.'"</q>
    <q>"The strata of the Earth is a jumbled museum. Embedded in the sediment is a text that contains limits and boundaries which evade the rational order, and social structures which confine art."</q>
    <q>"For too long the artist has been estranged from his own 'time.' Critics, by focusing on the 'art object,' deprive the artist of any existence in the world of both mind and matter."</q>
    <q>"Nobody wants to go on a vacation to a garbage dump."</q>
  </quotes>
  <authors>
    <author link="wolf">Justin Wolf</author>
  </authors>
  <article>
    <synopsys>Although Robert Smithson died at the age of only 35, his short career has inspired more young artists than most among the generation that emerged in the 1960s. A formidable writer and critic as well as an artist, his interests ranged from Catholicism to mineralogy to science fiction. His earliest pieces were paintings and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-collage"&gt;collages&lt;/span&gt;, but he soon came to focus on sculpture; he responded to the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalism&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-conceptual_art"&gt;Conceptualism&lt;/span&gt; of the early 1960s and he started to expand his work out of galleries and into the landscape. In 1970, he produced the Earthwork, or &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-land_art"&gt;Land art&lt;/span&gt;, for which he is best known, &lt;i&gt;Spiral Jetty&lt;/i&gt;, a remarkable coil of rock composed in the colored waters of the shore of the Great Salt Lake in Utah. In 1973, he died in an aircraft accident when he was surveying the site for another Earthwork in Texas.</synopsys>
    <key_ideas>
      <idea>Smithson is one of the most influential artists of the diverse generation that emerged in the wake of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionism&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalism&lt;/span&gt;, known as the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-post_minimalism"&gt;Post-Minimalists&lt;/span&gt;. Although inspired by Minimalism's use of industrial materials and interest in the viewer's experience of the space around the art object (as much as the object itself), the Post-Minimalists sought to abandon even more aspects of traditional sculpture. Smithson's approaches are typical of this group; he constructed sculptures from scattered materials, he found ways to confuse the viewer's understanding of sculpture (often by using mirrors or confusing scales), and his work sometimes referred to sites and objects outside of the gallery, leading the viewer to question where the art object really resided.</idea>
      <idea>Much of Smithson's output was shaped by his interest in the concept of entropy, the second law of thermodynamics that predicts the eventual exhaustion and collapse of any given system. His interest in geology and mineralogy confirmed this law to him, since in rocks and rubble he saw evidence of how the earth slows and cools. But the idea also informed his outlook on culture and civilization more generally; his famous essay &lt;i&gt;Entropy and the New Monuments&lt;/i&gt; (1969) draws analogies between the quarries and the strip malls and tract housing of New Jersey, suggesting that ultimately the later will also perish and return to rubble.</idea>
      <idea>Smithson's concepts of &lt;i&gt;Site&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Nonsite&lt;/i&gt; - the former being a location outside the gallery, the latter being a body of objects and documentation inside the gallery - were important contributions to the body of ideas surrounding Land art in the 1960s. His discussion of monuments and ruins in his writing also helped many to think about the purpose art might have in the landscape, after the demise of the tradition of commemorative public sculpture.</idea>
    </key_ideas>
    <sections>
      <section title="Biography">
        <subsection title="Childhood">
          <p type="p">Robert Smithson expressed a profound interest in the arts from an early age. While still attending high school in Clifton, New Jersey, during the mid 1950s, he attended art classes on the side in New York City. For two years, he was enrolled at The Art Students League in New York and, for a briefer period, at The Brooklyn Museum School.</p>
          <p type="p">Through his studies and training, Smithson became fascinated with the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-abstract_expressionism"&gt;Abstract Expressionists&lt;/span&gt;, in particular with &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-smith_david"&gt;David Smith&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-smith_tony"&gt;Tony Smith&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-pollock_jackson"&gt;Jackson Pollock&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-louis_morris"&gt;Morris Louis&lt;/span&gt;. Later in his career, Smithson said that he found David Smith's sculpture particularly captivating for its use of unnatural materials (i.e. steel) that were altered by time and natural elements (i.e. rust, decay, and discoloring). Several years before Smithson expressed any interest in Minimalism, Conceptual art, and working with the natural environment, the young artist was drawing, painting, and making collages.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Early Training">
          <p type="p">In the late 1950s, Smithson was noticed by art dealer Virginia Dwan and granted his first solo show at the Artists' Gallery in 1959. At this time, Smithson's paintings, drawings, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-collage"&gt;collages&lt;/span&gt; (he had yet to begin sculpting) drew in part on Abstract Expressionism; his works were multimedia, but were still two-dimensional artworks made using gouache, crayon, pencil, and photography.</p>
          <p type="p">Through his connection with Dwan, Smithson was introduced to several key artists and sculptors who were pioneering the Minimalist art movement of the early-1960s, including &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-andre_carl"&gt;Carl Andre&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-judd_donald"&gt;Donald Judd&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-morris_robert"&gt;Robert Morris&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-oldenburg_claes"&gt;Claes Oldenburg&lt;/span&gt;, and Smithson's soon-to-be wife, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-holt_nancy"&gt;Nancy Holt&lt;/span&gt;. Holt and Smithson married in 1963. The formation of these friendships would mark a significant turning point in Smithson's career.</p>
          <p type="p">The collages he produced in the early-1960s, including &lt;i&gt;Untitled (Tear)&lt;/i&gt; (1961-63), &lt;i&gt;Untitled (Conch Shell, Spaceship and World Land Mass)&lt;/i&gt; (1961-63), and &lt;i&gt;Algae&lt;/i&gt; (c. 1962), were still very much in keeping with an abstract and expressionist aesthetic, but they clearly suggest the artist's growing fascination with the earth as an inspirational resource and his concern with themes of permanence, natural and unnatural materials, and site-specific art.</p>
          <p type="p">By 1964, Smithson had taken up sculpture, inspired in large part by the Minimalism that was coming into vogue. It was clear from the beginning, however, that Smithson was not entirely comfortable confining himself and his work to the studio. Throughout the mid-1960s, he made several trips to New Jersey to visit quarries and industrial wastelands. He also paid several visits to the American West and Southwest, sparking in him an interest in deserts and sprawling tracts of land that appear unblemished by human intervention.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Mature Period">
          <p type="p">Smithson's sculptures of the mid 1960s maintain a strong resemblance to the &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-minimalism"&gt;Minimalist&lt;/span&gt; installations of &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-judd_donald"&gt;Donald Judd&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-andre_carl"&gt;Carl Andre&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-lewitt_sol"&gt;Sol LeWitt&lt;/span&gt;, and &lt;span class="marked_text chart-tooltip-target-top tooltip_id-morris_robert"&gt;Robert Morris&lt;/span&gt;. Painted steel works such as &lt;i&gt;Plunge&lt;/i&gt; (1966), &lt;i&gt;Alogon #2&lt;/i&gt; (1966), and &lt;i&gt;Terminal&lt;/i&gt; (1966), employed industrial materials, geometric forms, and a restricted palette. They were built indoors and intended for indoor display.</p>
          <p type="img" alt="Robert Smithson Biography" show="0">/images20/photo/smithson_robert_2.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">By 1967, Smithson was focused on two peculiar forms of sculpture, &lt;i&gt;Sites&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Non-sites&lt;/i&gt;, using mirrors and natural materials to create a new form of three-dimensional work. For his &lt;i&gt;Sites&lt;/i&gt; projects, Smithson made several trips to New Jersey, Mexico, England, and West Germany, among other places, often accompanied by his wife Nancy Holt and dealer Virginia Dwan. While at these chosen sites (barren wastelands, salt flats, and wooded areas), Smithson placed a series of mirrors in natural settings and photographed the newly altered landscapes. The results created an effect of beauty and unease at having inserted such blatantly unnatural materials into an untouched setting.</p>
          <p type="p">For his &lt;i&gt;Non-sites&lt;/i&gt;, Smithson situated mirrored surfaces into the corner or center of a room, in effect creating virtual doorways. Contrasting with these mirrors were the natural materials Smithson had scavenged from his trips, including mica, essen soil, red sandstone, limestone, sand, gravel, and other materials. Many of these &lt;i&gt;Non-site&lt;/i&gt; projects would directly mirror his &lt;i&gt;Sites&lt;/i&gt;, as in the case of &lt;i&gt;Chalk Mirror Displacement&lt;/i&gt; (1969), a single work located in two different locales: its original quarry site in Oxted, England (&lt;i&gt;Site&lt;/i&gt;), and later in the gallery space (&lt;i&gt;Non-site&lt;/i&gt;). What made the &lt;i&gt;Sites/Non-sites&lt;/i&gt; such a unique artistic endeavor was that Smithson was first altering the landscape, and then bringing the exhibition materials from the site in the gallery.</p>
          <p type="p">Simultaneous with Smithson's production of &lt;i&gt;Sites/Non-sites&lt;/i&gt;, the artist was also creating a series of works called &lt;i&gt;Photo-Markers&lt;/i&gt; (1968), which were in many ways the direct opposite of &lt;i&gt;Sites/Non-sites&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Photo-Markers&lt;/i&gt; also explored the effects of human intervention into the natural landscape, but applied a very different methodology. Smithson would photograph specific sites, enlarge the images, and place these enlargements into the physical landscapes they depicted. He then re-photographed the landscapes, creating an odd juxtaposition of the natural and the reproduced in the same shot - as if nature were referencing itself.</p>
          <p type="p">Smithson's first fully-fledged Earthworks were little more than preliminary sketches: site-specific proposals that existed only on paper. Throughout 1969 and 1970, he created a large number of drawings depicting projects that would soon come to fruition - and a few that would not. Early Earthworks, such as &lt;i&gt;Asphalt Rundown&lt;/i&gt; (1969) and &lt;i&gt;Glue Pour&lt;/i&gt; (1969), were inspired in part by his interest in entropy and abstraction, since the dumped and cooled materials created hardened abstract forms that resulted from their loss of heat. They were also demonstrations of Smithson's growing fascination with industrial areas and human neglect of wastelands.</p>
          <p type="p">His grandest achievement and most famous work was &lt;i&gt;Spiral Jetty&lt;/i&gt; (1970). After much searching, Smithson purchased a plot of land on the northern shore of the Great Salt Lake, Utah, and inserted into the violet-red water a massive spiral constructed of some 6650 tons of earth. The &lt;i&gt;Jetty&lt;/i&gt;, unlike previous Earthworks, maintained a harmony with its natural environment; it is an unnatural extension of the natural landscape, albeit one that, according to Smithson "[had been] disrupted by industry, reckless urbanization, or nature's own devastation." In subsequent years, Smithson embarked on other Earthworks projects that were in keeping with this artistic philosophy. In 1971, he completed &lt;i&gt;Broken Circle/Spiral Hill&lt;/i&gt;, located in a quarry near Emmen, Holland, after which he returned to the United States to undertake what would be his last project, one Smithson himself would never realize.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Late Years and Death">
          <p type="img" alt="Robert Smithson Photo" show="0">/images20/photo/smithson_robert_4.jpg</p>
          <p type="p">In the summer of 1973 Smithson was traveling in a small airplane to survey the site for his newest project, called &lt;i&gt;Amarillo Ramp&lt;/i&gt;. The plane crashed, killing him, the pilot, and the photographer who was accompanying them. Even though Smithson was robbed of the opportunity to build &lt;i&gt;Amarillo Ramp&lt;/i&gt;, the project was completed shortly after his death by his widow Nancy Holt, Richard Serra, and others.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Writings">
          <p type="p">In addition to being an artist, Smithson was also an accomplished critic, essayist, and theoretician. Writing for the publications &lt;i&gt;Artforum&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Arts Magazine&lt;/i&gt;, mostly between the years 1967 and 1970, he developed intriguing theories involving the convergence of earth, language, and art. In a September 1968 &lt;i&gt;Artforum&lt;/i&gt; piece entitled &lt;i&gt;A Sedimentation of the Mind: Earth Projects&lt;/i&gt; he wrote, "Embedded in the sediment is a text that contains limits and boundaries which evade the rational order, and social structures which confine art. In order to read the rocks we must become conscious of geologic time, and of the layers of prehistorical material that is entombed in the Earth's crust."</p>
          <p type="p">The above text is indicative of a constant theme in Smithson's writings and art: time. Throughout his career, he became increasingly fascinated with the element of time and with humankind's repeated attempts to control it. These attempts, according to Smithson, were foolish. He viewed any attempt to control time as tantamount to devaluing it altogether and defrauding the earth of its essential right to exist. He also presented this theme in his 1970 Earthwork &lt;i&gt;Partially Buried Woodshed&lt;/i&gt;, located in Kent, Ohio, which consisted of a woodshed partially buried under 20 truckloads of earth. This piece was "built" to illustrate the effects of geologic time and its eventual consumption of all man-made endeavors. Incidentally, other major works, such as &lt;i&gt;Spiral Jetty&lt;/i&gt;, would eventually be consumed (temporarily) by the waters that surrounded them.</p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection title="Legacy">
          <p type="p">Robert Smithson not only coined the term "Land art," he gave birth to the movement itself. Interestingly, Smithson's death could be said to have accelerated the Land art movement. Inspiring a new generation of artists to leave the studio altogether and create art out in the open, the movement represented a unique convergence of installation, Conceptual art, and environmental awareness. Adding a strange twist to the world of popular art, most of Smithson's works were designed to be consumed by time and nature; thus they were constructed to have a finite life span. Predating Smithson's arrival into the art world, artists hoped to immortalize themselves by creating works that would easily outlast the span of human life. Smithson, in a sense, sought the opposite. His incursions into wastelands and no-man's lands were dialectical attempts to show nature's fragility in the industrial world and its powerful ability to defend itself against such incursions.</p>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </sections>
  </article>
  <similar_artworks>
    <artwork from="artist" page="kaprow_allan">Rearrangeable Panels (1957-9)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="judd_donald">Untitled (1984)</artwork>
    <artwork from="artist" page="andre_carl">Stone Field Sculpture (1977)</artwork>
  </similar_artworks>
  <chart>
    <top>
      <column>
        <entity>kaprow_allan</entity>
        <entity>judd_donald</entity>
        <entity>burroughs_william_s</entity>
        <entity>ballard_jg</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>dwan_virginia</entity>
        <entity>andre_carl</entity>
        <entity>oldenburg_claes</entity>
        <entity>morris_robert</entity>
        <entity>holt_nancy</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>abstract_expressionism</entity>
        <entity>minimalism</entity>
        <entity>conceptual_art</entity>
        <entity>happenings</entity>
        <entity>landscape_architecture</entity>
      </column>
    </top>
    <bottom>
      <column>
        <entity>de_maria_walter</entity>
        <entity>long_richard</entity>
        <entity>haacke_hans</entity>
        <entity>heizer_michael</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>andre_carl</entity>
        <entity>oldenburg_claes</entity>
        <entity>morris_robert</entity>
        <entity>serra_richard</entity>
        <entity>holt_nancy</entity>
      </column>
      <column>
        <entity>land_art</entity>
        <entity>landscape_architecture</entity>
        <entity>conceptual_art</entity>
        <entity>installation_art</entity>
      </column>
    </bottom>
  </chart>
  <artworks>
    <artwork>
      <title>Blind in the Valley of the Suicides</title>
      <year>1962</year>
      <materials>Ink on paper</materials>
      <desc>&lt;i&gt;Blind in the Valley of the Suicides&lt;/i&gt; depicts a human transforming into a tree and may have been inspired by Dante's &lt;i&gt;Divine Comedy&lt;/i&gt;. It is one of a series of early drawings from 1960 to 1962 that explores the themes of vision and blindness. Smithson would continue to explore the theme of vision throughout his later work - particularly in pieces involving mirrors - but he soon abandoned figurative drawing. Works such as this belong to a part of his career in which he was preoccupied with imagery drawn from the repertoire of science fiction and Catholicism (his mother's religion).</desc>
      <collection>Estate of Robert Smithson, James Cohan Gallery, New York</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Plunge</title>
      <year>1966</year>
      <materials>Steel; 10 units with square surfaces</materials>
      <desc>Constructed when Smithson was still mostly confining himself to the studio, &lt;i&gt;Plunge&lt;/i&gt; is in keeping with Minimalism's preoccupation with geometry, repetition, and industrial materials. And many critics who saw this work in Smithson's first solo show at the Dwan Gallery in 1966 identified him as a leading Minimalist. However, there is much in &lt;i&gt;Plunge&lt;/i&gt; that departs from the aesthetic of mainstream Minimalists such as Donald Judd. In particular, the work is made of a series of stepped units that are positioned such that they slowly increase (or decrease) in size; this sense of progression is quite different from the kind of straightforward repetition employed by Judd's sculpture. While Judd's work is often quite frank about its scale and dimensions, the changing scale in Smithson's &lt;i&gt;Plunge&lt;/i&gt; makes it strangely difficult to gauge the scale of its individual components, and this attempt to befuddle the viewer is typical of the latter's work.</desc>
      <collection>The Denver Art Museum</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Chalk Mirror Displacement</title>
      <year>1969</year>
      <materials>Six mirrors, chalk</materials>
      <desc>Smithson began making the &lt;i&gt;Mirror Displacement&lt;/i&gt; series shortly after his &lt;i&gt;Site/Non-Site&lt;/i&gt; works. While the &lt;i&gt;Site&lt;/i&gt; pieces generally used material from outside the gallery - rocks, rubble - which was piled in low containers, the &lt;i&gt;Mirror Displacements&lt;/i&gt; saw the materials simply dumped in heaps on the floor and divided up by mirrors. And while the &lt;i&gt;Site&lt;/i&gt; pieces always contained a component situated in the gallery, the &lt;i&gt;Mirror Displacement&lt;/i&gt; pieces were sometimes situated outside - as was this example, which was set up in Oxted Quarry in England. Smithson described the difference between the two kinds of work: "In other &lt;i&gt;Non-sites&lt;/i&gt;, the container was rigid, the material amorphous. In this case, the container is amorphous, the mirror is the rigid thing." As in the &lt;i&gt;Site&lt;/i&gt; series, Smithson was preoccupied with the way material, or another site, might be represented; might the materials in the &lt;i&gt;Displacement&lt;/i&gt; be thought to "mirror" their presence elsewhere?</desc>
      <collection>Oxted Quarry, England</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Asphalt Rundown</title>
      <year>1969</year>
      <materials>Asphalt</materials>
      <desc>Smithson created &lt;i&gt;Asphalt Rundown&lt;/i&gt; - the first monumental Earthwork that he made outside, to be seen outside - in a quarry on the outskirts of Rome. He loaded a dump truck with hot asphalt, and then had the truck discharge the contents down the sides of a quarry, so that the mixture cooled and hardened as it fell, ultimately seeming to fuse with the sides of the quarry. Smithson said his intention was to "root it in the contour of the land, so that it's permanently there and subject to the [sic] weathering." It demonstrates the importance of entropy in his thinking, since here gravity and loss of energy are integral to the creation of the work.</desc>
      <collection>Cava dei Selce, Rome, Italy</collection>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Spiral Jetty</title>
      <year>1970</year>
      <materials>Mud, precipitated salt crystals, rocks, water coil</materials>
      <desc>The northern section of the Great Salt Lake, where Smithson chose to site &lt;i&gt;Spiral Jetty&lt;/i&gt;, was cut off from fresh water supplies when a nearby causeway was constructed by the Southern Pacific Railroad in 1959. This encouraged the water's unique red-violet coloration, because it produced a concentration of salt-tolerant bacteria and algae. Smithson particularly liked the combination of colors because it evoked a ruined and polluted sci-fi landscape. And, by inserting the &lt;i&gt;Jetty&lt;/i&gt; into this damaged section, and using entirely natural materials native to the area, Smithson called attention to environmental blight. Nevertheless, he also sought to reference the importance of time in eroding and transforming our environment. The coiling structure of the piece was inspired by the growth patterns of crystals, yet it also resembles a primeval symbol, making the landscape seem ancient, even while it also looks futuristic.</desc>
      <collection>Rozel Point, Great Salt Lake, Utah</collection>
      <use_big_image>true</use_big_image>
    </artwork>
    <artwork>
      <title>Amarillo Ramp</title>
      <year>1973</year>
      <materials>Soil, rocks, sand</materials>
      <desc>While tragically, Smithson played no role in the actual construction of &lt;i&gt;Amarillo Ramp&lt;/i&gt;, the posthumous piece is a fitting tribute to his life's work and artistic philosophy. The ramp has slowly eroded since its construction; thus, like all of Smithson's mature Earthworks, it will eventually succumb to the elements, much like natural landscapes themselves. The ramp was originally commissioned by Stanley Marsh, a local ranch owner, who also commissioned Ant Farm's &lt;i&gt;Cadillac Ranch&lt;/i&gt; (1974) and several other sculptures located along his 200 square miles of land near Amarillo. &lt;i&gt;Amarillo Ramp&lt;/i&gt; is comprised of a 140-foot diameter partial circle of rock, which ascends from level ground up to a height of 15 feet. At one time the ramp emerged from an artificial body of water called Tecovas Lake, which has since dried out.</desc>
      <collection>Tecovas Lake, 15 miles NW of Amarillo, Texas</collection>
    </artwork>
  </artworks>
  <sidebar>
    <category name="art story website" />
    <category name="where to see works" />
    <category name="featured books">
      <subcategory name="biography" class="biography">
        <entry>
          <title>Robert Smithson: Learning from New Jersey and Elsewhere</title>
          <link>0262681552</link>
          <info>By Ann Reynolds</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Earthwards: Robert Smithson and Art after Babel</title>
          <link>0520212355</link>
          <info>By Gary Shapiro</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Robert Smithson and the American Landscape</title>
          <link>0521827558</link>
          <info>By Ron Graziani</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="writings" class="written-by">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Robert Smithson: The Collected Writings</title>
          <link>0520203852</link>
          <info>By Robert Smithson, Jack Flam</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="artworks" class="artwork">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Robert Smithson</title>
          <link>0520244087</link>
          <info>By Alexander Alberro, Suzaan Boettger, Cornelia Butler, Thomas Crow, Eugenie Tsai</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Robert Smithson: Spiral Jetty</title>
          <link>0520245547</link>
          <info>By George Baker, Bob Phillips, Ann Reynolds, Lytle Shaw, Robert Smithson, Diana Thater, Lynne Cooke, Karen Kelly</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Mirror-Travels: Robert Smithson and History</title>
          <link>0300094973</link>
          <info>By Jennifer L. Roberts</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
    </category>
    <category name="web resources">
      <subcategory name="websites" class="websites">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Robert Smithson Official Website</title>
          <link>http://www.robertsmithson.com/</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Robert Smithson, American Minimalist Installation Artist</title>
          <link>http://robertsmithson.org/</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Dia Art Foundation - Robert Smithson, Spiral Jetty</title>
          <link>http://www.diaart.org/sites/main/spiraljetty</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Estate of Robert Smithson - Selected Works - James Cohan Gallery</title>
          <link>http://www.jamescohan.com/artists/estate-of-robert-smithson</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles/essays by Smithson" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>A Short Description of Two Mirrored Crystal Structures</title>
          <link>http://www.robertsmithson.com/essays/short.htm</link>
          <info>
						From Unpublished Writings in Robert Smithson: The Collected Writings
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Excerpt from "Some Void Thoughts On Museums"</title>
          <link>http://www.robertsmithson.com/essays/void.htm</link>
          <info>
						From The Writings of Robert Smithson
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>A Provisional Theory of Non-Sites</title>
          <link>http://www.robertsmithson.com/essays/provisional.htm</link>
          <info>
						From Unpublished Writings in Robert Smithson: The Collected Writings
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Cultural Confinement</title>
          <link>http://www.robertsmithson.com/essays/cultural.htm</link>
          <info>
						From The Writings of Robert Smithson
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="articles/essays about Smithson" class="articles">
        <entry>
          <title>How to Conserve Art That Lives in a Lake?</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/18/arts/design/18spiral.html?_r=1</link>
          <info>
						By Randy Kennedy
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br&gt;
						November 17, 2009
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Plans to Mix Oil Drilling and Art Clash in Utah</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/27/us/27spiral.html</link>
          <info>
						By Kirk Johnson
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br&gt;
						March 27, 2008
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Maximalist</title>
          <link>http://nymag.com/nymetro/arts/art/reviews/12113/</link>
          <info>
						By Mark Stevens
						&lt;br&gt;
						New York Magazine
						&lt;br&gt;
						June 26, 2005
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Sculpture From the Earth, But Never Limited by it</title>
          <link>http://www.robertsmithson.com/essays/tnytjun.html</link>
          <info>
						By Michael Kimmelman
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br&gt;
						June 24, 2005
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Robert Smithson and Floating Island</title>
          <link>http://www.haberarts.com/smithson.htm</link>
          <info>
						By John Haber
						&lt;br&gt;
						Haberarts.com
						&lt;br&gt;
						2005
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>The Salt of the Earth Sculpture; Debating Intervention as Nature does its Work</title>
          <link>http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/13/arts/the-salt-of-the-earth-sculpture-debating-intervention-as-nature-does-its-work.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm</link>
          <info>
						By Melissa Sanford
						&lt;br&gt;
						The New York Times
						&lt;br&gt;
						January 13, 2004
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Writer's Blocks: Robert Smithson's Drawings, 1962</title>
          <link>http://www.robertsmithson.com/essays/ratcliff.htm</link>
          <info>
						By Carter Ratcliff
						&lt;br&gt;
						Art on Paper
						&lt;br&gt;
						2000
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>A Tree Dies in Brooklyn</title>
          <link>http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0268/is_n6_v36/ai_20544480/</link>
          <info>
						By Frances Richard
						&lt;br&gt;
						Artforum
						&lt;br&gt;
						February 1998
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="interviews" class="interviews">
        <entry>
          <title>Entropy Made Visible</title>
          <link>http://www.robertsmithson.com/essays/entropy.htm</link>
          <info>
						Interview with Alison Sky
						&lt;br&gt;
						1973
					</info>
        </entry>
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Interview with Robert Smithson for the Archives of American Art/Smithsonian Institution</title>
          <link>http://www.robertsmithson.com/essays/interviews.htm</link>
          <info>
						Interview with Paul Cummings
						&lt;br&gt;
						July 14 and July 19, 1972
					</info>
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="audio clips" class="audioclips" />
      <subcategory name="video clips" class="clips">
        <entry recommended="true">
          <title>Robert Smithson - Asphalt Rundown (1969)</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A1M3HoZpXBc&amp;feature=results_video&amp;playnext=1&amp;list=PLB45351C52E5779D1</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Robert Smithson and Nancy Holt - Swamp (1971)</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RYPWcdty7DE</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
        <entry>
          <title>Robert Smithson - Floating Island (1970/2005)</title>
          <link>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UiimctQ9qWI&amp;feature=related</link>
          <info />
        </entry>
      </subcategory>
      <subcategory name="documentary films" class="clips" />
      <subcategory name="in pop culture" class="in-pop" />
    </category>
  </sidebar>
  <posters>
    <poster>
      <a_item />
      <a_image />
      <a_name />
    </poster>
  </posters>
</data>